<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Intertidal Innovators: Art + Science Collaboration Brings the Shoreline to Life</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-earthlab-intertidal/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>From April 2023 to March 2025, a team lead by <a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/people.html#chris-mantegna">Chris Mantegna</a> piloted Intertidal Innovators, an EarthLab Innovation Grant–funded program that blended art and science to connect local high school students with Seattle’s nearshore ecosystems. The program invited 11 students into a five-week internship where they explored foundational intertidal science concepts and translated their learning into creative expression.</p>
<section id="building-connections-through-art-and-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="building-connections-through-art-and-science">Building Connections Through Art and Science</h2>
<p>Working in small groups, students wrote, directed, photographed, and edited a geo-located guided walk through Golden Gardens Park, designed to reveal what remains hidden at high tide. Their final piece, The Golden Hour, is now publicly available on the <a href="https://explore.echoes.xyz/">Echoes app</a> for anyone to experience—on-site or remotely.</p>
<p>To celebrate the culmination of the program, students led family and community members on their guided walk at Golden Gardens. This showcase not only highlighted their new knowledge but also allowed them to teach their families about the shoreline environment, reinforcing connections across generations.</p>
<p>Alongside the student projects, the team developed a flexible art + science curriculum, including community-building activities, photography and sound recording methods, and editing techniques. This content has already been shared at national conferences, sparking dialogue on how to integrate creativity and environmental learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="lasting-impact-on-students-and-community" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lasting-impact-on-students-and-community">Lasting Impact on Students and Community</h2>
<p>The program’s impact can be seen in three ways:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Student empowerment</strong> – Students gained literacy and comfort in their local environment, transforming initial unfamiliarity into curiosity and pride.</li>
<li><strong>Community engagement</strong> – Families participated enthusiastically in the showcase, with students confidently leading and teaching.</li>
<li><strong>Interdisciplinary learning</strong> – The program demonstrated how art can deepen science learning and strengthen environmental connection.</li>
</ul>
<p>Feedback from both students and families revealed a surprising outcome: parents expressed interest in participating alongside their children. Future iterations will explore opportunities to involve families more directly.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-we-learned" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-learned">What We Learned</h2>
<p>EarthLab’s support made this interdisciplinary experiment possible. We learned how to foster curiosity in high school students outside of traditional grading systems, how to effectively blend art and science as teaching tools, and how to build trust and community in creative learning spaces.</p>
<p>For future rounds, we plan to lengthen the program, weave art and science even more tightly together, and expand opportunities for community members to take part. Continued mentorship with Garfield High School students is already underway, with plans to build on their intertidal research and experiential learning credits in spring 2025.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>Deliverables from Intertidal Innovators will continue to grow. In addition to the Echoes guided walk, an ArcGIS StoryMap and a complete open-source curriculum will be available by early 2026, along with a media library of student-created photos, videos, and recordings.</p>
<p>We are grateful to EarthLab for supporting this innovative project, and to our collaborators—UW School of Aquatic and Fishery Sciences, UW DXARTS, Black in Marine Science, and Sea Potential—for making this work possible. Together, we’ve shown how art and science can inspire the next generation of environmental stewards.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>earthlab</category>
  <category>intertidal</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-earthlab-intertidal/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_The_Golden_Hour_-_a_geolocated_audio_walk_by_Intertidal_Innovators_on_ECHOES_2024-08-19_12-50-25.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using Metabolomics and Lipidomics to Unlock Marine Resilience</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-metab/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>How do marine organisms adapt to an ocean that is rapidly warming, acidifying, and changing in countless other ways? A new <strong>Perspective article in Integrative and Comparative Biology</strong> by Yaamini R. Venkataraman and Ariana S. Huffmyer takes on this pressing question by focusing on <strong>metabolic plasticity</strong>—an organism’s capacity to adjust how it produces, allocates, and uses energy under stress.</p>
<p>The authors argue that while genomics, transcriptomics, and epigenomics have all advanced our understanding of stress responses, <strong>metabolomic and lipidomic approaches provide a direct lens into energy balance</strong>—a key driver of resilience. By quantifying the molecules that fuel and regulate cellular processes, researchers can uncover hidden physiological shifts that are invisible at the whole-organism level.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-09-24_10-54-17.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="why-this-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-this-matters"><strong>Why This Matters</strong></h3>
<p>Marine ecosystems are on the front lines of climate change. From corals to clams, invertebrates must constantly adjust to stressors like heat waves, hypoxia, and ocean acidification. The paper highlights how metabolic and lipidomic tools can:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Detect subtle but critical energy shifts before mortality occurs.</p></li>
<li><p>Reveal differences in resilience between species, populations, and even sexes.</p></li>
<li><p>Provide early biomarkers of stress tolerance that can inform conservation and aquaculture.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="a-framework-for-best-practices" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-framework-for-best-practices"><strong>A Framework for Best Practices</strong></h3>
<p>Recognizing that metabolomic and lipidomic studies are still emerging in marine biology, Venkataraman and Huffmyer provide a <strong>roadmap for experimental design and analysis</strong>. Their recommendations include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Careful sampling and preservation to prevent artifacts.</p></li>
<li><p>Strategic use of targeted, semi-targeted, or untargeted analyses.</p></li>
<li><p>Embracing time series designs to capture dynamic shifts.</p></li>
<li><p>Integrating molecular data with physiological and phenotypic metrics.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>They also call for <strong>multi-omic integration</strong>—combining metabolomics and lipidomics with gene expression, epigenetics, and physiology—to link molecular mechanisms with whole-organism outcomes</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead"><strong>Looking Ahead</strong></h3>
<p>The Perspective synthesizes findings from 68 studies published between 1993 and 2025, showing both how far the field has come and where opportunities lie. Importantly, it underscores that the <strong>marine science community must embrace metabolic complexity</strong> if we are to anticipate and mitigate the impacts of climate change on ecosystems.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/figure1.png" width="600"></p>
<p>By providing this framework, Venkataraman and Huffmyer hope to spark more rigorous, reproducible, and integrative research—work that can help answer one of the defining questions of our time: <strong>how will marine life persist in a rapidly changing ocean?</strong></p>
<p>👉 Read the full article here: <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Venkataraman_Huffmyer2025.pdf">Interrogating Metabolic Plasticity in Marine Organisms: A Framework for Best Practices Using Metabolomic and Lipidomic Approaches</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>metabolomics</category>
  <category>lipidomics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-metab/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-09-24_10-52-23.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building Resilient Oysters: Launching the SORMI Project</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sormi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>We are excited to share that our proposal, <em>Development of SORMI (Summer Oyster Resilience and Mortality Index): A Quantitative Tool for Improving Field Survival</em>, has been funded through the Western Regional Aquaculture Center. This multi-institutional effort will address one of the most pressing challenges in shellfish aquaculture—<strong>recurrent summer mortality in Pacific oysters</strong>.</p>
<section id="the-challenge" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge"><strong>The Challenge</strong></h3>
<p>For decades, oyster growers across the West Coast have faced sudden, large-scale summer die-offs linked to rising seawater temperatures, disease, and other stressors. These events threaten farm productivity and the economic stability of the shellfish industry. Despite years of research, a single cause has never been identified. Instead, we are taking a new approach: focusing on why oysters survive rather than why they die.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-sormi" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-sormi"><strong>What Is SORMI?</strong></h3>
<p>SORMI—the <em>Summer Oyster Resilience and Mortality Index</em>—will be a <strong>generalized stress resilience index</strong> for Pacific oysters. By integrating a suite of physiological and metabolic assays, the index will help predict which oyster families are most resilient under real-world conditions. This tool will directly support breeding programs and hatcheries, providing a practical way to select for survival and reduce the frequency of catastrophic summer mortality events .</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-35-37.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="our-role-at-uw" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-role-at-uw"><strong>Our Role at UW</strong></h3>
<p>At the Roberts Lab, our team will be leading development of innovative, high-throughput stress assays, including a new <a href="http://oyster.pink"><strong>resazurin-based metabolic assay</strong></a> we have been refining as a cost-effective, scalable way to measure oyster metabolism. We will also work closely with partners to analyze stress resilience across hundreds of oyster families and link these traits to field survival outcomes. Our focus is on providing growers and breeding programs with actionable, science-based tools that are accessible and easy to implement.</p>
</section>
<section id="project-leadership-and-partners" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="project-leadership-and-partners"><strong>Project Leadership and Partners</strong></h3>
<p>This project is led by <strong>Bobbi Hudson</strong>, Executive Director of the <strong>Pacific Shellfish Institute (PSI)</strong>. The collaborative team brings together expertise and resources from across the region, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>University of Washington (Roberts Lab)</strong> – stress physiology and assay development</p></li>
<li><p><strong>USDA Agricultural Research Service (Neil Thompson, Pacific Oyster Genomic Selection project)</strong> – breeding program integration and genetic analysis</p></li>
<li><p><strong>NOAA Fisheries (Mackenzie Gavery)</strong> – environmental physiology and genomics</p></li>
<li><p><strong>California Sea Grant (Kevin Johnson, Cal Poly)</strong> – aquaculture extension and grower engagement</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Industry partners</strong> – Goose Point Oyster Company (WA) and Hog Island Oyster Company (CA)</p></li>
</ul>
<p>This broad coalition ensures the project is grounded in industry needs while pushing forward fundamental science .</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-36-23.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="implications-for-the-shellfish-industry" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-for-the-shellfish-industry"><strong>Implications for the Shellfish Industry</strong></h3>
<p>The ultimate goal of SORMI is to give oyster growers a <strong>practical decision-making tool</strong>. With a reliable index, farmers could anticipate when their stocks are stressed and take proactive measures—harvesting before a mortality event, adjusting management practices, or prioritizing resilient broodstock. For breeding programs, SORMI will add a measurable, heritable trait that can accelerate development of hardier oyster lines.</p>
<p>In short, this project will help secure the future of West Coast oyster farming by <strong>turning science into survival.</strong></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sormi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-42-09.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scientific Breakthrough in Sustainable Aquaculture</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sablefish/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>As global demand for seafood continues to rise, the aquaculture industry faces growing pressure to produce more while minimizing ecological impacts. A key concern in marine fish farming is the risk of escapees interbreeding with wild populations, leading to genetic introgression and reduced fitness in native fish stocks. Now, a recent study led by former University of Washington CICOES postdoctoral researcher Dr.&nbsp;Yuzo R. Yanagitsuru offers a promising solution.</p>
<p>Published in <em>Aquaculture</em>, the study presents a <strong>proof-of-concept for a non-GMO, bath immersion–based technique for inducing sterility in sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria)</strong>—an emerging high-value aquaculture species also known as black cod. The approach targets a gene essential for reproductive cell development and aims to prevent escaped farmed fish from reproducing in the wild.</p>
<section id="a-scalable-gene-silencing-alternative-to-triploidy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-scalable-gene-silencing-alternative-to-triploidy"><strong>A Scalable, Gene-Silencing Alternative to Triploidy</strong></h3>
<p>While triploidization and genetic modification have been explored for sterility induction, both come with drawbacks—triploid fish can still be partially fertile, and GM fish face regulatory and public acceptance hurdles.</p>
<p>Instead, Dr.&nbsp;Yanagitsuru and collaborators used a <strong>Morpholino oligomer (MO)</strong> attached to a <strong>Vivo transporter</strong> to silence the <em>dead end</em> (<em>dnd</em>) gene—a critical regulator of primordial germ cell formation. The innovation lies in delivering this compound through a <strong>simple bath immersion</strong>, rather than invasive microinjection or genetic alteration.</p>
</section>
<section id="results-a-step-toward-sterile-sustainable-farming" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results-a-step-toward-sterile-sustainable-farming"><strong>Results: A Step Toward Sterile, Sustainable Farming</strong></h3>
<p>In controlled hatchery trials, sablefish eggs treated with the dnd-MO-Vivo compound before fertilization produced a subset of individuals that were completely sterile (8%) or had drastically reduced numbers of reproductive cells (18%). Importantly, sterile individuals developed normally in all other respects: they showed no major differences in growth, sex steroid hormone levels, or survival under semi-commercial rearing conditions.</p>
<p>Key findings include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Target specificity</strong>: dnd expression was limited to gonads and unfertilized eggs, confirming its value as a marker for germ cell presence.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>No adverse health effects</strong>: Sterile fish were physiologically indistinguishable from fertile fish in terms of somatic growth and overall condition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Higher efficacy pre-fertilization</strong>: The sterility induction was more effective when the treatment was applied before fertilization, likely due to increased permeability of the egg chorion.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="why-it-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-it-matters"><strong>Why It Matters</strong></h3>
<p>This method opens a new path for <strong>scalable, publicly acceptable sterility induction in marine finfish aquaculture</strong>. By eliminating the reproductive capability of escapees, it reduces ecological risk and helps safeguard the genetic integrity of wild populations—while also offering potential gains in growth efficiency and product quality for farmers.</p>
<p>Sablefish, already known for its rich flavor and high omega-3 content, now also stands to become a model species for innovative, sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next"><strong>What’s Next?</strong></h3>
<p>The authors emphasize that <strong>further optimization is needed</strong> to improve sterility rates and ensure consistent results across large-scale operations. Future research will likely explore different concentrations, immersion times, and additional species to assess broader applicability.</p>
<p>But for now, this work—driven by Dr.&nbsp;Yanagitsuru’s leadership—marks an important milestone in the development of non-GMO solutions to one of aquaculture’s biggest challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Citation</strong>:</p>
<p>Yanagitsuru, Y.R., Hayman, E.S., Fairgrieve, W.T., Zohar, Y., Wong, T-T., &amp; Luckenbach, J.A. (2025). <em>Proof-of-concept for sterility induction in sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria) via a scalable immersion-based gene silencing approach</em>. <em>Aquaculture</em>, 609, 742945. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2025.742945" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2025.742945</a></p>
<p>Podcast Episode featuring work: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/gene-pooling/id1802677296?i=1000718173868" class="uri">https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/gene-pooling/id1802677296?i=1000718173868</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>sterility</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sablefish/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Yanagitsuru_et_al_SterilityInduction_dnd_BathImmersion_SablefishProofOfConcept_2025.pdf_2025-07-20_13-09-45.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Celebrating Undergraduate Research</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-capstone/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>This spring, two outstanding undergraduate researchers in our lab—Genevieve Buchanan and Henry Berg—presented their senior capstone projects, showcasing months of hard work and scientific curiosity. Their research tackled critical questions related to marine invertebrate resilience in the face of environmental stress, and each presentation offered fresh insight into how shellfish species respond to changing ocean conditions.</p>
<section id="genevieve-buchanan-thermal-tolerance-in-a-stressful-world" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="genevieve-buchanan-thermal-tolerance-in-a-stressful-world">🦪 Genevieve Buchanan: Thermal Tolerance in a Stressful World</h2>
<p>Genevieve’s project, “Effects of Salinity and Ocean Acidification Stress on Pacific Oyster (Magallana gigas) Thermal Tolerance”, examined how prior exposure to low salinity and acidic conditions influences oyster survival during subsequent heat stress. Pacific oysters are economically vital to aquaculture industries and ecologically foundational to coastal ecosystems, yet they face increasing threats from climate change-induced stressors.</p>
<p>Through a carefully controlled experiment using oysters from the Point Whitney Shellfish Hatchery, Genevieve tested whether low pH or reduced salinity exposure would compound mortality under acute thermal stress. Her findings showed that, surprisingly, these prior stressors did not significantly impact thermal tolerance. This suggests that Pacific oysters may be energetically adapted to the variable conditions of the Pacific Northwest, offering a glimmer of hope for aquaculture resilience in the face of climate extremes.</p>
<p>🔗 <a href="https://youtu.be/4Yz1z1yZRGQ">Watch Genevieve’s full presentation on YouTube</a></p>
<p>📄 <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Genevieve_Buchanan_-_Capstone_Presentation.pptx">Download Genevieve’s Presentation Slides (PPTX)</a></p>
<p>⸻</p>
</section>
<section id="henry-berg-mussel-threads-and-climate-stress" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="henry-berg-mussel-threads-and-climate-stress">🧵 Henry Berg: Mussel Threads and Climate Stress</h2>
<p>Henry’s capstone, “Physiological Markers Associated with Byssus Attachment Following Environmental Perturbations in Marine Mussels”, focused on the byssal threads that mussels use to anchor themselves to surfaces—an essential trait for survival and aquaculture yield.</p>
<p>Comparing Mytilus trossulus and Mytilus galloprovincialis, Henry exposed mussels to ocean acidification, warming, and hypoxia, then measured thread production and metabolic rates. His results were striking: ocean acidification increased thread production in both species, while warming favored M. galloprovincialis. Hypoxia, however, drastically reduced thread output, particularly in M. galloprovincialis. These species-specific responses highlight the complexity of climate resilience and point to potential physiological markers that could inform aquaculture site selection and selective breeding strategies.</p>
<p>🔗 <a href="https://youtu.be/wkkv9eZpcik">Watch Henry’s full presentation on YouTube</a></p>
<p>📄 <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Marine_Mussels_Presentation.pptx">Download Henry’s Presentation Slides (PPTX)</a></p>
<p>⸻</p>
<p>A Proud Moment for Undergraduate Research</p>
<p>Projects were conducted under the guidance of Ariana Huffmyer and Matt George, respectively, and reflect the high caliber of undergraduate research in our lab. We are incredibly proud of Genevieve and Henry—not only for their scientific contributions but also for their clarity, creativity, and commitment to advancing our understanding of marine organism resilience in a changing world.</p>
<p>Please take a moment to view their presentations and join us in celebrating their accomplishments.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>shellfish</category>
  <category>capstone</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-capstone/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-06-16_10-44-13.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Environmental Priming in Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lewis-smith/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>We're proud to share a new publication by former lab member <strong>Connor Lewis-Smith</strong>, now a Social Scientist with NOAA's Northwest Fisheries Science Center. His article, <em>"Navigating ocean acidification in shellfish aquaculture: Stakeholder perspectives of developing strategies in the U.S. Pacific Region"</em>, was just released in <em>Aquaculture Reports</em> and offers an in-depth look at how shellfish growers across the U.S. Pacific Coast are responding to ocean acidification and related environmental stressors.</p>
<p>The study draws on structured interviews with producers from Washington, Oregon, California, Alaska, and Hawaii to capture evolving perceptions of ocean acidification and industry interest in emerging adaptation strategies. Notably, concern about ocean acidification appears to have declined in the past decade, as growers increasingly focus on intersecting threats such as harmful algal blooms, disease, and rising temperatures.</p>
<p>The paper explores two adaptation strategies under development: <strong>parental priming</strong>—a technique involving exposure of broodstock to stressful conditions to enhance offspring resilience—and <strong>native species portfolio expansion</strong>. While industry support for both strategies was mixed and often contingent on further scientific validation, the study emphasizes the importance of early engagement between researchers and growers to co-develop viable solutions.</p>
<p>Importantly, this research aligns directly with <strong>ongoing environmental priming work in our lab</strong>, where we are experimentally testing how exposure to low pH and high temperature conditions in adult shellfish can influence offspring performance. By integrating physiological, transcriptomic, and lipidomic data, our current NOAA-funded work seeks to identify the mechanisms underlying carryover effects and inform hatchery practices that enhance larval resilience under future ocean conditions.</p>
<p>Connor's collaboration with our group helped build the interdisciplinary foundation for this kind of applied science—where social, biological, and ecological factors intersect to shape adaptation in real-world settings. We're excited to see how his work complements and extends our efforts to support a more resilient shellfish aquaculture sector.</p>
<p>Read the full article <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aqrep.2025.102858">here</a>.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lewis-smith/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-05-07_11-42-09.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
