<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Exploring the Non-Coding RNA Landscape in Reef-Building Corals</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lncRNA-rep/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Coral reefs are among the most biodiverse ecosystems on the planet, yet they are increasingly threatened by climate change and human activities. Understanding the molecular mechanisms that govern coral resilience is crucial for their conservation. A <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.15.643469.">new study by Ashey et al.&nbsp;(2025)</a> provides a groundbreaking look into the non-coding RNA (ncRNA) repertoire of reef-building corals, shedding light on how these regulatory molecules contribute to coral gene expression and environmental adaptability.</p>
<section id="why-non-coding-rnas-matter" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-non-coding-rnas-matter"><strong>Why Non-Coding RNAs Matter</strong></h3>
<p>Long dismissed as “junk” DNA, ncRNAs have emerged as vital regulators of gene expression across all domains of life. Unlike protein-coding genes, ncRNAs do not translate into proteins but instead play critical roles in controlling genetic pathways, chromatin organization, and stress responses. In corals, these molecules could be key players in their ability to withstand environmental stressors such as rising ocean temperatures and pollution.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-study-a-comprehensive-analysis-of-coral-ncrnas" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-study-a-comprehensive-analysis-of-coral-ncrnas"><strong>The Study: A Comprehensive Analysis of Coral ncRNAs</strong></h3>
<p>Ashey et al.&nbsp;conducted the first large-scale characterization of ncRNAs in three ecologically significant coral species from Mo’orea, French Polynesia:&nbsp;<em>Acropora pulchra</em>,&nbsp;<em>Pocillopora tuahiniensis</em>, and&nbsp;<em>Porites evermanni</em>. These species exhibit diverse physiological traits and symbiotic relationships, making them excellent models for studying ncRNA variation.</p>
<section id="key-findings" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings"><strong>Key Findings:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Diverse ncRNA Repertoires:</strong>&nbsp;The study identified a broad array of ncRNAs, including long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs), microRNAs (miRNAs), and piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs), indicating that corals possess a complex ncRNA regulatory system.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Limited Conservation Across Species:</strong>&nbsp;While a few miRNAs (such as&nbsp;<em>mir-100</em>) were conserved across all three species, most lncRNAs and other ncRNAs exhibited high evolutionary turnover, suggesting species-specific adaptations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Functional Insights:</strong>&nbsp;Many ncRNAs were associated with immune regulation, stress response, and genomic stability. For example, lncRNAs were often found near immune-related genes, while piRNAs were enriched in transposable element regions, which are crucial for maintaining genomic integrity.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>miRNA-Target Interactions:</strong>&nbsp;The study predicted miRNA targets involved in immune response pathways and cellular stress mechanisms, providing new insights into how corals regulate gene expression in response to environmental changes.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="implications-for-coral-resilience" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-for-coral-resilience"><strong>Implications for Coral Resilience</strong></h3>
<p>These findings underscore the importance of ncRNAs in coral biology. By regulating gene expression and protecting genome stability, ncRNAs may influence corals’ ability to acclimate to shifting environmental conditions. This research also sets the stage for future studies on the role of ncRNAs in coral bleaching, symbiosis dynamics, and adaptation.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions"><strong>Future Directions</strong></h3>
<p>Given the rapid decline of coral reefs worldwide, understanding the molecular underpinnings of coral resilience is more critical than ever. Further investigations into ncRNA functions across additional coral species and environmental conditions will enhance our ability to predict and mitigate the impacts of climate change on these vital ecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts"><strong>Final Thoughts</strong></h3>
<p>The study by Ashey et al.&nbsp;provides a significant step forward in coral molecular biology, revealing how ncRNAs contribute to the complex regulatory networks that sustain coral health. As researchers continue to explore these molecular mechanisms, such insights could inform conservation strategies aimed at preserving coral reefs in a warming world.</p>
<p>For more details, the full study is available on bioRxiv:&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.15.643469" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.15.643469</a>.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>coral</category>
  <category>lncRNA</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lncRNA-rep/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_httpswww.biorxiv.orgcontent10.11012025.03.15.643469v1.full.pdf_2025-03-17_08-01-04.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unlocking the Future of Shellfish Aquaculture Through Genomics</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-genomics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Aquaculture is undergoing a revolution. The integration of cutting-edge genomic tools into breeding programs is transforming the industry, allowing for enhanced growth rates, disease resistance, and environmental adaptability in farmed species. While finfish often take center stage in discussions about genomic innovation, shellfish—particularly oysters, clams, and other bivalves—stand to benefit tremendously from these advancements. A recent review by <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-025-11247-z">Andersen et al.&nbsp;(2025), published in BMC Genomics</a>, outlines the progress and future priorities for U.S. aquaculture genomics, with significant implications for shellfish industries.</p>
<section id="why-genomics-matters-for-shellfish" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-genomics-matters-for-shellfish">Why Genomics Matters for Shellfish</h2>
<p>Shellfish farming is a cornerstone of coastal economies, providing a sustainable protein source while contributing to water filtration and habitat structure. However, challenges such as disease outbreaks, climate change-driven stressors (e.g., ocean acidification, salinity fluctuations), and genetic bottlenecks in breeding programs pose significant hurdles. The integration of genomics and multi-omics approaches is helping researchers and industry stakeholders address these issues head-on.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Advancing Reference Genomes for Shellfish</li>
</ol>
<p>One of the key priorities identified in the review is the need for high-quality genome assemblies for shellfish species. Reference genomes serve as blueprints for breeding programs, guiding selective breeding efforts toward desirable traits such as disease resistance, growth efficiency, and stress tolerance.</p>
<p>For instance:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The Pacific oyster (Magallana gigas) and Eastern oyster (Crassostrea virginica) now have improved genome assemblies, which are crucial for mapping genes associated with disease resilience.</p></li>
<li><p>Structural variations in oyster genomes have been linked to breeding success, helping hatcheries refine their selection of broodstock.</p></li>
<li><p>Functional annotation efforts, like those undertaken by the international FAANG (Functional Annotation of ANimal Genomes) initiative, are improving our understanding of how genes are regulated in response to environmental stressors.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Multi-Omics Approaches: Beyond the Genome</li>
</ol>
<p>While genomic sequencing provides a foundational understanding of shellfish biology, integrating other “omics” layers—epigenomics, transcriptomics, and microbiomics—adds depth to the picture.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Epigenomics &amp; Environmental Adaptation: Studies have shown that DNA methylation plays a key role in how oysters respond to stress, such as changes in salinity and temperature. This suggests that breeding for resilience might not just be about genetics but also about harnessing heritable epigenetic modifications.</p></li>
<li><p>Transcriptomics &amp; Disease Resistance: RNA sequencing has revealed that oysters activate specific immune pathways when exposed to pathogens like Perkinsus marinus (which causes Dermo disease). Understanding these pathways helps identify candidate genes for selective breeding.</p></li>
<li><p>Microbiomics &amp; Shellfish Health: The microbial communities living on and inside shellfish significantly impact their growth and survival. Some studies suggest that manipulating the oyster microbiome could enhance disease resistance.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Genomic Selection &amp; Breeding Programs</li>
</ol>
<p>Traditional shellfish breeding has relied on mass selection or family-based selection, which can be slow and inefficient. Genomic selection—where DNA markers are used to predict an individual’s breeding value—has revolutionized selective breeding in finfish and livestock, and now it is being applied to shellfish.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The use of genomic selection in oysters is improving survival rates in low-salinity environments, a crucial trait given the increasing frequency of extreme weather events that introduce large freshwater inputs into coastal farming areas.</p></li>
<li><p>Marker-assisted selection (MAS) is being employed to accelerate breeding for traits like shell strength, which is vital for both consumer preference and post-harvest handling.</p></li>
<li><p>Researchers are also exploring CRISPR and other gene-editing technologies to validate gene function, though regulatory challenges remain.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Overcoming Challenges: From Research to Industry Application</li>
</ol>
<p>Despite these advancements, challenges remain in translating genomic discoveries into tangible benefits for shellfish farmers.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Cost &amp; Accessibility: While sequencing costs are declining, implementing genomic selection on a commercial scale still requires investment in infrastructure, training, and data management.</p></li>
<li><p>Regulatory Landscape: The potential application of gene-editing technologies in aquaculture is still subject to regulatory scrutiny. While some countries are moving toward acceptance, others remain cautious.</p></li>
<li><p>Data Integration: The vast amount of genomic and phenotypic data generated requires sophisticated bioinformatics tools for analysis. Efforts like AquaMine (a genomic database for aquaculture species) are helping streamline this process ￼.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead-the-future-of-shellfish-aquaculture" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead-the-future-of-shellfish-aquaculture">Looking Ahead: The Future of Shellfish Aquaculture</h2>
<p>The next decade of shellfish aquaculture will be defined by how well the industry can harness the power of genomics. As sequencing technology becomes more affordable and bioinformatics tools become more accessible, we are likely to see:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>More refined and efficient breeding programs using genomic selection.</p></li>
<li><p>Greater adoption of multi-omics approaches to understand complex traits like disease resistance and stress tolerance.</p></li>
<li><p>The potential emergence of gene-edited shellfish with enhanced resilience to climate change.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>By integrating these tools into aquaculture operations, we can ensure that shellfish farming remains a sustainable and resilient industry—one that continues to provide ecological and economic benefits to coastal communities while supporting global food security.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-025-11247-z">The review by Andersen et al.&nbsp;(2025)</a> highlights an exciting and rapidly evolving field. Shellfish may not have received as much genomic attention as salmon or tilapia in the past, but that is changing. With continued investment in research, training, and industry partnerships, shellfish aquaculture is poised to become a model for sustainable, high-tech food production in the 21st century.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-genomics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Advancing_genetic_improvement_in_the_omics_era_status_and_priorities_for_United_States_aquaculture__BMC_Genomics__Full_Text_2025-02-21_12-15-32.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cracking the Code of Pacific Cod</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Spencer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-cod2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What if the future of an entire fish population hinged on tiny changes in their DNA? In the frigid waters of the North Pacific, juvenile Pacific cod are facing an uncertain future as ocean temperatures rise. Our research is uncovering how these fish respond to warming waters—at the molecular level—and what that means for their survival.</p>
<p><strong>The Science Behind Survival</strong></p>
<p>At first glance, Pacific cod might seem like just another fish. But beneath the surface, their genetic makeup holds clues to how they adapt—or struggle—when faced with environmental stress. In our latest study, we’re diving deep into the connection between a cod’s genes and its ability to thrive in different temperatures.</p>
<p>We analyzed DNA and gene activity (transcriptomics) in young Pacific cod exposed to a range of temperatures, from icy 0°C to a heatwave-like 16°C. By combining this “genome-to-phenome” data—essentially linking genetic information to physical traits—we’re beginning to see which fish have the genetic tools to survive in a warming world.</p>
<p><strong>A Genetic Blueprint for Resilience</strong></p>
<p>One of the most intriguing findings comes from a process called <strong>Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS)</strong>, where we scan the entire genome for small genetic differences linked to key traits. One of the most revealing traits we studied is the <strong>hepatosomatic index (HSI)</strong>—a measure of how much energy a fish stores in its liver. Since fat storage is critical for surviving harsh winters, understanding which fish can accumulate liver lipids under stress is essential.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-17-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our data revealed <strong>specific genetic variants linked to liver size</strong>, some of which are connected to genes regulating appetite and metabolism. One gene in particular, likely involved in serotonin signaling (which affects hunger), seems to influence whether a juvenile cod stores enough fat when temperatures rise.</p>
<p><strong>Can Genes Predict Performance?</strong></p>
<p>Beyond genetics, we also examined how <strong>gene expression (RNA activity) relates to fish growth and condition</strong>. We identified a set of genes that are highly active in the strongest, most resilient fish under warm conditions. This genetic “signature” could help scientists predict which fish populations are best suited to handle climate shifts.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-18-11.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>By looking at <strong>composite performance indices (CPI)</strong>—which combine growth rate, body condition, and liver fat content—we found a distinct pattern: some fish are naturally equipped to thrive in warming seas, while others may struggle.</p>
<p><strong>A Look to the Past—and the Future</strong></p>
<p>To understand if these genetic traits have changed over time, we’re also analyzing historical samples from Pacific cod collected near Kodiak, Alaska, dating back to 2008. This will help us determine if recent marine heatwaves have already begun shaping the genetic makeup of young cod. If we find shifts in key genes over time, it could be a sign that natural selection is at work—favoring fish that can cope with temperature extremes.</p>
<p><strong>Next Steps: From Lab to Ocean Conservation</strong></p>
<p>Right now, we’re fine-tuning our analyses and comparing our results with other research teams, including NOAA scientists studying broader environmental factors. Our goal? To pinpoint the most critical genetic regions that influence temperature tolerance—and ultimately, to inform fisheries management strategies that support the resilience of Pacific cod populations.</p>
<p>As marine heatwaves become more frequent, understanding these genetic adaptations is more than just an academic pursuit. It’s about safeguarding a vital species in the face of climate change—ensuring that Pacific cod, and the people who depend on them, have a future in our warming oceans.</p>
<section id="products-this-period" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="products-this-period">Products this period:&nbsp;</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer at the NOAA NWFSC Manchester Research Station monthly meeting on December 11th, 2025, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Manchester-Presentation-Dec2024.pdf">link to slides</a>.&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer at the NOAA AFSC groundfish seminar on December 17th, 2024, <a href="https://bcove.video/3DxO7xy">link to recording</a>, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Groundfish%20Seminar%2C%202024.pdf">link to slides</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer during the poster session of the Alaska Marine Science Symposium on January 27th, 2025 in Anchorage, AK, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Spencer%2CLH_Poster-AMSS-2025-final.pdf">link to poster</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Laura Spenccer’s lab notebook updates on analyses, lab work, and products, <a href="https://laurahspencer.github.io/LabNotebook/">link to notebook</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://d.pr/f/Cq3nsF">Technical Report</a>.</p></li>
</ul>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-cod2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-15-38.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Harnessing Shellfish Environmental Memory for a Resilient Future</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-WSG/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Shellfish aquaculture is facing increasing challenges due to climate change, ocean acidification, and other environmental stressors. However, research is showing that environmental memory—the ability of organisms to retain and transmit adaptive responses to stress—may offer a promising strategy for improving resilience in aquaculture species.</p>
<p>At the 2025 Washington Sea Grant workshop, researchers and industry professionals came together to explore how environmental priming—exposing shellfish to controlled stress conditions—could be leveraged to enhance survival, growth, and performance.</p>
<section id="industry-engagement-and-perceptions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="industry-engagement-and-perceptions">Industry Engagement and Perceptions</h2>
<p>To better understand industry perspectives, a survey of shellfish growers was conducted to gauge their views on environmental priming as an adaptation strategy. The results were enlightening:<br>
• 78% of hatchery operators indicated they would consider implementing environmental priming, though most preferred to see supporting data first.<br>
• 70% of respondents said they would be willing to pay more for primed seed, provided evidence from test plots or research-supported literature was available.</p>
<p>This feedback underscores the importance of continued scientific research to validate environmental priming techniques and demonstrate their effectiveness in real-world aquaculture operations.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-environmental-priming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-environmental-priming">What is Environmental Priming?</h2>
<p>Environmental priming involves exposing shellfish to controlled stressors—such as temperature fluctuations, salinity changes, or immune challenges—to enhance their resilience later in life. Research has shown promising results across multiple species:</p>
<p>• Olympia oysters: Parental priming increased offspring survival in field conditions.<br>
• Pacific geoduck: Early-life priming led to improved growth rates later in life.<br>
• Manila clams: Offspring from primed parents exhibited better growth and survival rates.</p>
</section>
<section id="ongoing-research-and-applications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ongoing-research-and-applications">Ongoing Research and Applications</h2>
<p>Scientists are now working to optimize environmental priming strategies across different species. Ongoing research at institutions like NOAA’s Manchester Field Station and the Jamestown S’Klallam Hatchery is exploring how priming can enhance the performance of shellfish under various stress conditions.</p>
<p>For Pacific oysters, researchers are testing multiple priming approaches, including:<br>
✅ Immune challenges<br>
✅ Temperature stress<br>
✅ Salinity shifts<br>
✅ Combination stress exposures</p>
</section>
<section id="moving-forward-bridging-science-and-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="moving-forward-bridging-science-and-industry">Moving Forward: Bridging Science and Industry</h2>
<p>The insights from this research are critical for both hatchery operators and policymakers as they work toward sustainable shellfish aquaculture. With growing industry interest and evidence-based strategies, environmental priming may become a tool in ensuring the future resilience of shellfish populations.</p>
<p>Slidedecck: https://github.com/sr320/talk-WSG-2025</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>wsg</category>
  <category>talk</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-WSG/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_2025-WSG-Roberts_2025-02-10_07-20-44.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Coral Larvae and Thermal Stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-paper/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As climate change continues to drive rising ocean temperatures, coral reef ecosystems face an unprecedented crisis. Coral bleaching events, characterized by the breakdown of the mutualistic relationship between corals and their algal endosymbionts (Symbiodiniaceae), have become increasingly common, threatening the persistence of coral reefs worldwide. While much research has focused on adult corals, new studies are shedding light on how early life stages respond to thermal stress. <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3002875">A recent study by Huffmyer et al.&nbsp;(2024), published in&nbsp;<em>PLOS Biology</em></a>, provides novel insights into how coral larvae cope with increased temperatures by modifying nitrogen assimilation to stabilize symbiotic relationships and mitigate bleaching risk.</p>
<section id="the-crucial-role-of-coral-larvae-in-reef-resilience" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-crucial-role-of-coral-larvae-in-reef-resilience"><strong>The Crucial Role of Coral Larvae in Reef Resilience</strong></h3>
<p>Reef-building corals rely on their symbionts to produce energy-rich photosynthates that fuel metabolic processes. However, when subjected to thermal stress, this delicate exchange can be disrupted, leading to the expulsion of symbionts and loss of critical energy sources. Understanding how coral larvae respond to environmental stress is particularly important, as their ability to establish symbiosis and successfully settle onto reefs determines the future of coral populations.</p>
<p>The study focused on&nbsp;<em>Montipora capitata</em>, a dominant reef-building coral in Hawai‘i that vertically transmits Symbiodiniaceae to its offspring. The researchers subjected symbiotic larvae to a 2.5°C increase in temperature for three days and assessed metabolic responses, photosynthetic performance, and stable isotope-labeled metabolite exchange.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-nitrogen-assimilation-as-a-protective-mechanism" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-nitrogen-assimilation-as-a-protective-mechanism"><strong>Key Findings: Nitrogen Assimilation as a Protective Mechanism</strong></h3>
<p>Contrary to expectations, the study found that while larvae exhibited significant metabolic depression under high temperatures—indicated by a 19% reduction in respiration rates—they did not experience bleaching or a decline in survival and settlement rates. Photosynthetic activity remained stable, and the symbiont population density was maintained despite thermal stress.</p>
<p>A crucial discovery was that coral larvae increased ammonium assimilation and urea metabolism while sequestering nitrogen into dipeptides. This shift suggests that larvae actively modulate nitrogen cycling to maintain symbiotic balance. By limiting nitrogen availability to the symbionts, the coral hosts may be promoting sustained photosynthate translocation, ensuring that energy supply remains uninterrupted under heat stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="metabolic-trade-offs-and-implications-for-coral-survival" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="metabolic-trade-offs-and-implications-for-coral-survival"><strong>Metabolic Trade-offs and Implications for Coral Survival</strong></h3>
<p>While glucose translocation from symbiont to host was maintained, the study revealed reduced metabolism of glucose through central carbon pathways such as glycolysis. This metabolic shift implies a trade-off: larvae prioritize nitrogen assimilation over carbohydrate breakdown, potentially conserving energy for essential physiological functions.</p>
<p>The authors propose that nitrogen limitation imposed on Symbiodiniaceae encourages continued carbon transfer to the host, preventing the symbionts from hoarding fixed carbon, which could otherwise disrupt the mutualistic relationship. This mechanism highlights a potential resilience strategy in coral early life stages that may influence reef recovery following bleaching events.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions-and-conservation-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions-and-conservation-implications"><strong>Future Directions and Conservation Implications</strong></h3>
<p>Understanding the physiological mechanisms that allow coral larvae to withstand heat stress has significant implications for reef conservation and restoration efforts. If coral larvae can naturally modulate nitrogen metabolism to maintain symbiosis, selective breeding or assisted evolution approaches may enhance these traits in vulnerable species.</p>
<p>Additionally, further research should investigate whether similar nitrogen assimilation strategies are present in adult corals or if this is a life-stage-specific adaptation. Given the increasing frequency of marine heatwaves, identifying and promoting heat-resilient traits in corals could be a crucial component of future conservation strategies.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>Huffmyer et al.&nbsp;(2024) provide compelling evidence that coral larvae can mitigate thermal stress through nitrogen assimilation, maintaining stable symbiosis even under elevated temperatures. By uncovering this metabolic adaptation, the study advances our understanding of coral resilience mechanisms and underscores the importance of protecting early life stages in reef conservation efforts. As climate change accelerates, these insights may inform new strategies to support coral reef survival in a warming world.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>paper</category>
  <category>coral</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-paper/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Coral_larvae_increase_nitrogen_assimilation_to_stabilize_algal_symbiosis_and_combat_bleaching_under_increased_temperature__PLO_2025-02-08_12-36-36.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery-based Environmental Conditioning Activities</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>During this past year a series of hatchery-based environmental conditioning activities (referred to as hardening) were completed with oysters out-planted onto three farms to evaluate performance. Additionally, climate resiliency was assessed in hardened oysters under controlled conditions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_overview.png_2024-08-29_13-35-45.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Experimental Overview</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="farm-outplanting" class="level1">
<h1>Farm Outplanting</h1>
<p>Early in the season, a cohort of oysters were subject to (a) daily thermal hardening for approximately two weeks prior to out planting in hanging bags on a farm in Sequim Bay, alongside a control group. These oyster will be assessed in early Autumn 2024. Later in the season oysters were subjected to a more diverse series of hardening conditions with oyster split between two commercial farms, one located in Willapa Bay and a second in the San Juan Islands. The combination of age classes and hardening conditions were as follows: b) small seed / daily thermal hardening, c) adult / daily thermal hardening, d) small seed / weekly thermal hardening, e1) large seed / weekly thermal hardening, e2) large seed / weekly zero salinity hardening. These hardening activities spanned from several weeks to months. For all hardening efforts controls were also outplanted. Oysters out planted in Willapa Bay will be assessed for survival and growth in early September 2024. Oysters out planted in the San Juan Islands have be subject to more routine monitoring. At this site we are currently observing a trend where oysters subjected to the daily hardening regime are surviving better than controls.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-37-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Wescott Bay Outplanting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-1" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 1</h1>
<p>To assess the effectiveness of hardening within a hatchery setting, four ages classes of oysters were examined: adults (40-100mm), juveniles (20-55mm), seed (6-15mm), and spat ()1-6mm). In order to assess hardening potential and environmental memory, oysters were subject to an initial chronic temperature stress, then subjected to a secondary stress to see if the response to secondary stress was impacted by initial exposure. During the chronic temperature stress period, oysters from each age class were exposed to a daily 25ºC temperature spike. This repeated for 14 days starting on October 1. Control oysters from each cohort were maintained at an ambient temperature of approximately 17ºC during the same time period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-38-28.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Hardening and acute stress temperature timeline</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Adult oysters in stress conditions were also subject to mechanical stress at day 1, 7, and 48, which was induced by 15 minutes. At day 147 (7 weeks after initial chronic stress), both stressed and non-stressed adult, juvenile, spat, and seed were subjected to a secondary stress of 30 minutes in 32ºC. Gill tissue was sampled immediately after and placed into RNAlater. Spat and seed that were too small to dissect gill tissue were sampled whole with all tissue used in gene expression assays. To date we have analyzed gene expression data from seed and spat. There was no mortality during this trial. Hardening increased growth (compared to controls) in spat. Further there was a reduced transcriptional response in spat. These data suggest temperature hardening of spat could result in a resiliency to later temperature stress whereby energy resources could favor growth.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-39-30.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Growth Performance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Gene expression profiles (spat)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-54.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic physiology explanation when hardened spat are exposed to acute temperature stress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-2" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 2</h1>
<p>In a second experimental regime, juvenile oysters were subjected to four hardening conditions 1) high temperature (35°C), 2) high temperature and freshwater, 3) freshwater, and 4) poly I:C immersion. These were exposures that occurred every other day for about 3 weeks. Approximately 1 month after hardening, oysters were brought to the lab and subjected to metabolic assessment using resazurin at 18°C and 42°C. Resazurin is a dye that is commonly used in cell viability, and it works by changing color as an organism consumes oxygen. Survival was assessed during the resazurin assay and 24 hours later. To date, our analysis suggests metabolic activity of the 42°C oysters was higher in the control oysters than previously hardened oysters. In the near future we will assess the relationship of metabolic activity and survival however it appears higher metabolic rate directly correlates with mortality. Taken together these sets of controlled experiments suggest hardening does have an impact on resiliency, though dependent on age, hardening duration, and subsequent environmental conditions.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_logo-resazuring_2024-08-29_13-50-31.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Resazurin assay (4 hour / 2 temperatures) on hardened oysters"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-10-49.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
