<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery-based Environmental Conditioning Activities</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>During this past year a series of hatchery-based environmental conditioning activities (referred to as hardening) were completed with oysters out-planted onto three farms to evaluate performance. Additionally, climate resiliency was assessed in hardened oysters under controlled conditions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_overview.png_2024-08-29_13-35-45.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Experimental Overview</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="farm-outplanting" class="level1">
<h1>Farm Outplanting</h1>
<p>Early in the season, a cohort of oysters were subject to (a) daily thermal hardening for approximately two weeks prior to out planting in hanging bags on a farm in Sequim Bay, alongside a control group. These oyster will be assessed in early Autumn 2024. Later in the season oysters were subjected to a more diverse series of hardening conditions with oyster split between two commercial farms, one located in Willapa Bay and a second in the San Juan Islands. The combination of age classes and hardening conditions were as follows: b) small seed / daily thermal hardening, c) adult / daily thermal hardening, d) small seed / weekly thermal hardening, e1) large seed / weekly thermal hardening, e2) large seed / weekly zero salinity hardening. These hardening activities spanned from several weeks to months. For all hardening efforts controls were also outplanted. Oysters out planted in Willapa Bay will be assessed for survival and growth in early September 2024. Oysters out planted in the San Juan Islands have be subject to more routine monitoring. At this site we are currently observing a trend where oysters subjected to the daily hardening regime are surviving better than controls.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-37-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Wescott Bay Outplanting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-1" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 1</h1>
<p>To assess the effectiveness of hardening within a hatchery setting, four ages classes of oysters were examined: adults (40-100mm), juveniles (20-55mm), seed (6-15mm), and spat ()1-6mm). In order to assess hardening potential and environmental memory, oysters were subject to an initial chronic temperature stress, then subjected to a secondary stress to see if the response to secondary stress was impacted by initial exposure. During the chronic temperature stress period, oysters from each age class were exposed to a daily 25ºC temperature spike. This repeated for 14 days starting on October 1. Control oysters from each cohort were maintained at an ambient temperature of approximately 17ºC during the same time period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-38-28.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Hardening and acute stress temperature timeline</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Adult oysters in stress conditions were also subject to mechanical stress at day 1, 7, and 48, which was induced by 15 minutes. At day 147 (7 weeks after initial chronic stress), both stressed and non-stressed adult, juvenile, spat, and seed were subjected to a secondary stress of 30 minutes in 32ºC. Gill tissue was sampled immediately after and placed into RNAlater. Spat and seed that were too small to dissect gill tissue were sampled whole with all tissue used in gene expression assays. To date we have analyzed gene expression data from seed and spat. There was no mortality during this trial. Hardening increased growth (compared to controls) in spat. Further there was a reduced transcriptional response in spat. These data suggest temperature hardening of spat could result in a resiliency to later temperature stress whereby energy resources could favor growth.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-39-30.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Growth Performance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Gene expression profiles (spat)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-54.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic physiology explanation when hardened spat are exposed to acute temperature stress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-2" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 2</h1>
<p>In a second experimental regime, juvenile oysters were subjected to four hardening conditions 1) high temperature (35°C), 2) high temperature and freshwater, 3) freshwater, and 4) poly I:C immersion. These were exposures that occurred every other day for about 3 weeks. Approximately 1 month after hardening, oysters were brought to the lab and subjected to metabolic assessment using resazurin at 18°C and 42°C. Resazurin is a dye that is commonly used in cell viability, and it works by changing color as an organism consumes oxygen. Survival was assessed during the resazurin assay and 24 hours later. To date, our analysis suggests metabolic activity of the 42°C oysters was higher in the control oysters than previously hardened oysters. In the near future we will assess the relationship of metabolic activity and survival however it appears higher metabolic rate directly correlates with mortality. Taken together these sets of controlled experiments suggest hardening does have an impact on resiliency, though dependent on age, hardening duration, and subsequent environmental conditions.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_logo-resazuring_2024-08-29_13-50-31.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Resazurin assay (4 hour / 2 temperatures) on hardened oysters"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-10-49.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Assessing Oyster Viability Under Environmental Stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lsamp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As part of our ongoing commitment to fostering innovative research, this summer was particularly thrilling due to the strides made in the <a href="https://www.washington.edu/omad/louis-stokes-alliance-for-minority-participation/">LSAMP Scientist Program</a>. One of our standout projects, led by an ambitious student researcher, Colby Elvrum, brought new insights into the resilience of oysters against environmental stressors. Get a <a href="https://genefish.wordpress.com/author/colbyelvrum/">first hand account of all of Colby’s science from his notebook!</a></p>
<section id="the-genesis-of-the-study" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-genesis-of-the-study">The Genesis of the Study</h3>
<p>Oysters, a crucial component of aquatic ecosystems, serve as indicators of environmental health and sustainability. Recognizing their role and the urgent need to understand how environmental changes affect these organisms, we embarked on a project to utilize a novel application of the resazurin assay, traditionally a cell viability test in microbiology. This assay, which exploits the color-changing properties of the resazurin dye in response to oxygen consumption, was adapted to measure the metabolic activity of oysters under stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-we-aimed-to-discover" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-aimed-to-discover">What We Aimed to Discover</h3>
<p>Our research was driven by two pivotal questions: Can resazurin effectively measure metabolism in oysters, and does prior exposure to stress (stress hardening) alter their metabolic response to subsequent stressors? Through meticulously designed experiments, Colby led the charge in optimizing the assay conditions, ensuring the reliability and accuracy of our measurements.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-33-23.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Colby presenting his research at the Summer Research Symposium</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-and-methodological-innovations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-and-methodological-innovations">Key Findings and Methodological Innovations</h3>
<p>Our findings were enlightening. We observed that resazurin is not only a viable marker for oyster metabolism but also that it clearly illustrates the metabolic shifts caused by environmental stressors such as temperature fluctuations. Notably, oysters exposed to elevated temperatures displayed a rapid increase in metabolic rate, which was a precursor to subsequent mortality. This initial surge and later plateau in metabolism provided critical clues about the stress thresholds of these organisms.</p>
<p>Moreover, the study also highlighted how oysters previously conditioned to withstand stress exhibited altered survival rates under extreme temperatures, suggesting a potential sensitization rather than hardening effect. These insights are crucial for understanding how oysters might respond to the escalating challenges of climate change.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h3>
<p>The implications of this research extend beyond the academic sphere. They beckon a reevaluation of how we manage and conserve our aquatic resources in the face of rapid environmental changes. The potential to scale up this assay and automate aspects of the procedure could revolutionize aquaculture, and provide a more dynamic understanding of environmental impacts on marine life.</p>
</section>
<section id="gratitude-and-acknowledgments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gratitude-and-acknowledgments">Gratitude and Acknowledgments</h3>
<p>This research was made possible through the support of the National Science Foundation. We are immensely proud of Colby and all associated researchers for their dedication and hard work.</p>
<p><strong>Poster</strong> (<a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Colby_Poster_LSAMP.pdf">download hi-res pdf</a>)</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-40-33.png" class="img-fluid"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lsamp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-42-08.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Intertidal Innovators</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-intertidal/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_1373.png_2024-08-19_12-59-21.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 16, participants in the Intertidal Innovators program presented their work to the community. The program, which was a collaboration sponsored by the UW Earthlab program, provided students with the opportunity to learn about marine science and conservation through art.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-19_13-09-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Quote
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This program has lasted for 10 days, but during those days we have learned and worked very hard to give you this project. And we are proud to say that there are a bunch of hard working members in our program that have learned new skills and have gained knowledge in this program So in this journey, you will learn a lot about our work and marine life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>At the community showcase, students guide small groups around the intertidal, sharing their art with tablets and speakers. It was a great experience that showcased videos, poems, live demonostrations, and stories. Anyone can checkout their guided tour at Golden Garden Park via the echoes app - <a href="https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC" class="uri">https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC</a></p>
<p>Below is a video that takes you behind the scenes on the 10-day experience students participated in.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PsVyUPzu2_A" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-intertidal/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_The_Golden_Hour_-_a_geolocated_audio_walk_by_Intertidal_Innovators_on_ECHOES_2024-08-19_12-50-25.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ostras en Chile</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-ostras/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_6806.jpg_19801320_pixels_2024-08-14_11-49-59.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 6, 2024, approximately sixty participants gathered at the Professor Alamiro Robledo Auditorium of the Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences at the University of Concepción. They were there to delve into the promising sector of oyster aquaculture in Chile during the seminar titled “Oysters in Chile: Opportunities and Challenges for Aquaculture Diversification.” This event was meticulously organized by the Interdisciplinary Center for Aquaculture Research (INCAR).</p>
<p>The seminar showcased six presentations from both national and international experts, followed by a panel discussion. The diverse audience included academia, public and private sector representatives, producers, aquaculturists, industry leaders, professionals, and both secondary and postgraduate students. The gathering aimed to foster a comprehensive dialogue on the development of oyster aquaculture in the country.</p>
<p>Manira Matamala, the regional director of the Undersecretary of Fisheries and Aquaculture (Subpesca) for Valparaíso, O’Higgins, and Maule, commended INCAR’s initiative. She highlighted the seminar’s focus on enhancing the genetic and genomic understanding of oysters, which is vital for promoting sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
<p>Among the speakers, Justo García, an aquaculturist and founder of “Cultivos Cholche,” shared insights from his hands-on experience in various stages of oyster production, emphasizing the importance of adding value to the aquaculture processes.</p>
<p>Key Presentations Highlighted at the Seminar:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Steven Roberts from the University of Washington offered an international perspective with his presentation on the “<a href="https://github.com/sr320/talk-ostras-2024">Olympia Oyster (Ostrea lurida) Restoration in the United States</a>,” focusing on physiological and genomic insights.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardo-Escárate, deputy director of Incar, discussed the genome of the Chilean oyster (Ostrea chilensis) as a critical tool for the restoration and conservation of natural oyster banks.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Francisco Cárcamo shared experiences on co-cultivating Japanese oysters and algae both in field and laboratory settings, presenting an alternative approach for Environmental Performance Enhancement (APE). Justo García recounted his local experiences in small-scale aquaculture for both Chilean and Japanese oysters.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Rodrigo Rojas from the Catholic University of the North introduced advances from a technological program aimed at the sustainable development of Japanese oyster cultivation.</p></li>
<li><p>Meyling Tang, vice president of the Cocinamar Foundation, proposed strategies to reinvigorate oyster consumption in Chile with her presentation titled “Oysters Everywhere: Ideas to Reactivate Oyster Consumption in Chile.”</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Renato Quiñones, the director of Incar, emphasized the seminar’s role in bringing together experts from varied fields to create a multidimensional space for all stakeholders involved in oyster cultivation. This interaction is crucial for transforming scientific knowledge into a community and national heritage.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The event concluded with a panel discussion moderated by Dr.&nbsp;Doris Soto, principal investigator at Incar, where experts discussed the multifaceted opportunities and challenges facing aquaculture diversification in Chile.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-36-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This seminar not only highlighted the collaborative efforts required to advance oyster aquaculture but also showcased the commitment of INCAR to foster a sustainable and innovative aquaculture industry in Chile.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>presentation</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-ostras/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-33-39.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring How Environmental Conditions Impact Atlantic Salmon’s Defense Against Sea Lice</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38876411/">In our latest study, we delved into the complex interplay between environmental factors and the immune responses of Atlantic salmon (<em>Salmo salar</em>) during infestations by sea lice (<em>Caligus rogercresseyi</em>).</a> This research is particularly significant for both aquaculture and the management of natural marine ecosystems.</p>
<section id="our-research-approach" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-research-approach">Our Research Approach</h4>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardos’ team set up an experimental infestation of Atlantic salmon with sea lice, controlling for variations in temperature and salinity: specifically, conditions were set at 8°C and 16°C, and 32 and 26 practical salinity units (PSU). We then collected tissues from these fish to conduct analyses via reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) and whole transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq).</p>
</section>
<section id="key-discoveries" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-discoveries">Key Discoveries</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Impact of Environment on Parasitic Load</strong>: We observed that the parasitic load varied significantly with environmental conditions, noting the lowest abundance of lice in salmon kept at cooler and less saline conditions (8°C/26PSU).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Transcriptional Changes and Splicing Events</strong>: Environmental conditions were found to influence the salmon’s transcriptome profiles substantially. Notably, there was an increase in alternative splicing events in fish under low temperature and salinity, suggesting that environmental stress can induce genomic adaptations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Methylation Patterns</strong>: We also noted significant changes in methylation levels in response to temperature variations, with more pronounced differential methylation regions (DMRs) at the higher temperature of 16°C. These methylation changes correlated with the expression of alternatively spliced transcripts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Biological Pathways</strong>: Our analyses revealed significant correlations between methylation, transcript expression, and key biological pathways such as Ferroptosis and TLR signaling pathways, which are crucial for immune response and cellular integrity.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="implications-of-our-findings" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-of-our-findings">Implications of Our Findings</h4>
<p>This research highlights the nuanced ways in which environmental conditions can influence the genomic and epigenomic landscapes of marine organisms. For the aquaculture industry, understanding these dynamics is essential for developing effective management strategies to combat sea lice infestations, which are a major challenge for the sustainability and economic success of salmon farming.</p>
<p>Moreover, the link between environmental conditions, alternative splicing, and methylation opens new research avenues into the genetic mechanisms of resilience and adaptability in marine organisms. This knowledge advances our understanding of how species adapt to their changing environments, which is critical for preserving and enhancing the health of our global marine resources.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>salmon</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Environmental_influence_on_the_Atlantic_salmon_transcriptome_and_methylome_during_sea_lice_infestations_-_ScienceDirect_2024-08-14_12-12-07.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unraveling the Intricacies of Enrichment Analysis</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-enrich/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In our most recent lab meeting, we delved into the fascinating world of enrichment analysis. This statistical method is a cornerstone of our research, helping us identify significantly over-represented subsets of proteins or genes within our data.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/GMT20240509-195925_Recording_gallery_1920x1080.mp4"></video></div>
<section id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis">The Power of Enrichment Analysis</h2>
<p>Enrichment analysis allows us to compare a small subset of genes or proteins to a larger set, identifying overrepresentation. This can provide valuable insights into the biological processes that are most relevant to our research.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-deep-dive-into-david" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-deep-dive-into-david">A Deep Dive into David</h2>
<p>One of the tools we use for enrichment analysis is David. During the meeting, we explored how to upload gene lists and backgrounds into David, and how to interpret the results it provides. This tool is invaluable in helping us understand the complex relationships and patterns within our data.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-reference-list-debate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-reference-list-debate">The Reference List Debate</h2>
<p>An interesting discussion arose around what to use as a reference list in enrichment analysis. Should it be all the genes detected in the data set, or all genes in a reference genome? This question sparked a lively debate, highlighting the complexities and nuances of enrichment analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo">Visualizing Gene Ontology with Revigo</h2>
<p>To help us visualize gene ontology, we use a tool called Revigo. This tool provides a visual representation of the relationships between genes, making it easier to understand the complex data we work with.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-lighter-moment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-lighter-moment">A Lighter Moment</h2>
<p>Amidst the serious scientific discussions, we also had a lighter moment when a team member shared a story about narrowly avoiding a parking ticket. It’s moments like these that remind us of the importance of camaraderie and humor in the lab.</p>
<hr>
<p>Our lab meetings are a crucial part of our research process, providing a space for us to discuss, debate, and learn together. Stay tuned for more insights from our lab meetings in future posts!</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-enrich/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/enrich.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery Field Day at Point Whitney</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On May 6, 2024, Dr.&nbsp;Ariana Huffmyer, an NSF Ocean Sciences Postdoctoral Fellow from the University of Rhode Island and University of Washington, shared insights from a field day at Point Whitney. This comprehensive post revealed the detailed process of managing and monitoring oyster growth and stress testing, providing a clear framework for hatchery management.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Link to Full Notebook Post
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/" class="uri">https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Overview of Field Day Activities</strong> The objective was to monitor the health and stress responses of oyster cohorts at the hatchery. Key activities included calibrating monitoring equipment, feeding the oysters, and assessing the impacts of temperature and freshwater stress.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Monitoring Equipment Calibration:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer set up and calibrated an Orion Star A325 probe to measure pH, temperature, and conductivity. By using buffers of varying pH and a conductivity solution, she ensured accurate measurements. The pH was measured on the NBS scale, considered sufficient since ocean acidification experiments weren’t being conducted.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Feeding Protocol:</strong> The oysters were pulse-fed, where approximately 1/3 of a 5-gallon bucket was distributed among the tanks. This ensured that the animals received sufficient nutrition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fluorometry and Physiochemical Measurements:</strong> Fluorometry measurements were conducted before and after feeding, providing data on oyster metabolic activity. Additionally, pH, temperature, and conductivity were measured across different tanks, offering valuable weekly insights into water quality.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stress Testing Regimen:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer conducted a 30-minute stress test for specific oyster cohorts using freshwater and elevated temperature exposures. Animals were subjected to 25°C temperature and freshwater immersion, replicating environmental stressors they might face. Trays were labeled and organized by stressor type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Growth Characterization:</strong> Size measurements were taken using a waterproof digital caliper. Cohorts were categorized based on their respective stressors, creating a comprehensive understanding of their growth patterns.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ploidy Testing Preparations:</strong> A selection of oysters from different cohorts was collected for ploidy testing to distinguish between diploid and triploid oysters. They were stored in mesh bags, and the testing results would provide critical information for future breeding programs.</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Hatchery_field_day_at_Point_Whitney_May_6_2024__Ariana_S_Huffmyer__NSF_Ocean_Sciences_Postdoctoral_Fellow_University_of_Rhod_2024-05-11_14-51-46.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">heath-tray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Takeaways for Hatchery Science</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer’s systematic approach highlights the significance of precise monitoring and stress testing in hatchery science. Understanding oyster resilience to environmental stressors is crucial for aquaculture sustainability. Her work at Point Whitney offers a detailed protocol that could be replicated or adapted by other researchers to monitor and improve hatchery operations.</p>
<p>The future of hatchery management will depend heavily on such frameworks, where real-time data collection and analysis enable researchers to respond promptly to environmental changes.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/bucket.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hardening in oysters drives increased growth</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the meticulously orchestrated world of marine science, a groundbreaking experiment has unfolded in the hands of <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io">Eric Essington</a>, casting the spotlight on an unlikely protagonist: the oyster. This narrative begins with the arrival of 235 adult oysters from Pacific Hybreed, their sizes ranging impressively from 40 to 100mm, and further complemented by a diverse younger contingent—120 juveniles, 120 seed, and approximately 120 spat, all courtesy of the USDA’s 2023 spawn.</p>
<p>The experimental setup divided these oysters into two groups: one destined for a control tank, mirroring their natural aquatic environment at a serene 17ºC, and the other for a treatment tank, where conditions were significantly altered. The latter group was subjected to a deliberate increase in temperature, a gradual ascent of 2ºC per hour until the water reached a stress-inducing 26ºC, maintained for six hours daily over a seven-week span (began 10 2 2023, ended 11 21 2023). This thermal regimen aimed to simulate the increasingly erratic and harsh conditions wrought by climate change.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Explanation_2024-03-08_15-17-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Adding a layer of complexity, adults and juveniles were subjected to mechanical stress, an innovative use of a salad spinner for 15 minutes on selected dates (10/2/2023, 10/4/2023, 10/11/2023). This unusual methodology aimed to mimic the physical disturbances oysters might face in their natural habitats, from tumbling in currents to encounters with predators and debris.</p>
<p>The culmination of this phase was marked by a meticulous sampling process on November 21, 2023. Selected groups of oysters were divided for detailed analysis, with some undergoing immediate tissue sampling for RNA and DNA analysis, while others faced an additional stress test—a 30-minute immersion in 32ºC water followed by a tumbling session in the salad spinner. This process was designed to simulate an acute stress event, allowing researchers to gauge the oysters’ physiological responses to compounded stressors.</p>
<p>Several months later, on February 28, 2024, the experiment was revisited with a focused approach. This time, the younger generation of oysters was spotlighted, undergoing tissue sampling without the prior mechanical stress, to isolate the effects of thermal stress.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/growth.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Take-away to date</strong> - Stress hardening in spat in October and November resulted in increased growth compared to controls in February.</p>
<p>This experiment is not merely an investigation into the resilience of oysters to thermal and mechanical stress; it’s a narrative about adaptation, survival, and the intricate dance of life beneath the waves.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io/data-explanation/">Eric’s Post</a> for more details.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/pw.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="124" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Are you really prepared?</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-prep/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/people.html#ariana-s.-huffmyer-phd">Ariana</a> lead a great tutorial on being prepared and planning for science. The narrative underscored the importance of thorough preparation and planning, including considering alternative uses for collected data, planning for potential pitfalls, and ensuring that experimental designs are robust against unforeseen challenges. This includes the practical aspects of laboratory work, field studies, and data analysis, emphasizing the value of learning from past experiences and being flexible in research approaches.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Exp_prep.mov"></video></div>
<p>Designing scientific experiments requires extensive planning to ensure projects run smoothly and yield meaningful results. Here are some important aspects to consider when preparing for research:</p>
<p><strong>Clearly Define Your Hypothesis and Objectives</strong>: Having a clear hypothesis drives your experimental design and analysis approach. Define what you aim to test upfront.</p>
<p><strong>Prepare Detailed Protocols</strong>: Write step-by-step protocols for all procedures well before starting. Practice techniques on mock datasets to work out kinks.</p>
<p><strong>Plan Your Data Collection</strong>: Design data sheets, name conventions, and metadata standards early. Consider sample sizes and ensure you collect the right data to answer your questions.</p>
<p><strong>Schedule Carefully</strong>: Block out experiment timelines, factoring permitting needs and collaborator availability. Leave buffer time for unexpected issues.</p>
<p><strong>Create Organizational Systems</strong>: Use checklists, spreadsheets, and visual aids to track tasks and ensure all preparation steps are completed thoroughly.</p>
<p><strong>Anticipate Challenges</strong>: Brainstorm potential pitfalls and have contingency plans. Run test analyses to flag problems before using real data.</p>
<p>Proper preparation is key to running successful, high-quality experiments that yield meaningful scientific insights. Taking the time to carefully plan experimental design and logistics pays off in efficient, productive research.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-prep/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/prep.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
