<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Building Resilient Oysters: Launching the SORMI Project</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sormi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>We are excited to share that our proposal, <em>Development of SORMI (Summer Oyster Resilience and Mortality Index): A Quantitative Tool for Improving Field Survival</em>, has been funded through the Western Regional Aquaculture Center. This multi-institutional effort will address one of the most pressing challenges in shellfish aquaculture—<strong>recurrent summer mortality in Pacific oysters</strong>.</p>
<section id="the-challenge" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge"><strong>The Challenge</strong></h3>
<p>For decades, oyster growers across the West Coast have faced sudden, large-scale summer die-offs linked to rising seawater temperatures, disease, and other stressors. These events threaten farm productivity and the economic stability of the shellfish industry. Despite years of research, a single cause has never been identified. Instead, we are taking a new approach: focusing on why oysters survive rather than why they die.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-sormi" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-sormi"><strong>What Is SORMI?</strong></h3>
<p>SORMI—the <em>Summer Oyster Resilience and Mortality Index</em>—will be a <strong>generalized stress resilience index</strong> for Pacific oysters. By integrating a suite of physiological and metabolic assays, the index will help predict which oyster families are most resilient under real-world conditions. This tool will directly support breeding programs and hatcheries, providing a practical way to select for survival and reduce the frequency of catastrophic summer mortality events .</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-35-37.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="our-role-at-uw" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-role-at-uw"><strong>Our Role at UW</strong></h3>
<p>At the Roberts Lab, our team will be leading development of innovative, high-throughput stress assays, including a new <a href="http://oyster.pink"><strong>resazurin-based metabolic assay</strong></a> we have been refining as a cost-effective, scalable way to measure oyster metabolism. We will also work closely with partners to analyze stress resilience across hundreds of oyster families and link these traits to field survival outcomes. Our focus is on providing growers and breeding programs with actionable, science-based tools that are accessible and easy to implement.</p>
</section>
<section id="project-leadership-and-partners" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="project-leadership-and-partners"><strong>Project Leadership and Partners</strong></h3>
<p>This project is led by <strong>Bobbi Hudson</strong>, Executive Director of the <strong>Pacific Shellfish Institute (PSI)</strong>. The collaborative team brings together expertise and resources from across the region, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>University of Washington (Roberts Lab)</strong> – stress physiology and assay development</p></li>
<li><p><strong>USDA Agricultural Research Service (Neil Thompson, Pacific Oyster Genomic Selection project)</strong> – breeding program integration and genetic analysis</p></li>
<li><p><strong>NOAA Fisheries (Mackenzie Gavery)</strong> – environmental physiology and genomics</p></li>
<li><p><strong>California Sea Grant (Kevin Johnson, Cal Poly)</strong> – aquaculture extension and grower engagement</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Industry partners</strong> – Goose Point Oyster Company (WA) and Hog Island Oyster Company (CA)</p></li>
</ul>
<p>This broad coalition ensures the project is grounded in industry needs while pushing forward fundamental science .</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-36-23.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="implications-for-the-shellfish-industry" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-for-the-shellfish-industry"><strong>Implications for the Shellfish Industry</strong></h3>
<p>The ultimate goal of SORMI is to give oyster growers a <strong>practical decision-making tool</strong>. With a reliable index, farmers could anticipate when their stocks are stressed and take proactive measures—harvesting before a mortality event, adjusting management practices, or prioritizing resilient broodstock. For breeding programs, SORMI will add a measurable, heritable trait that can accelerate development of hardier oyster lines.</p>
<p>In short, this project will help secure the future of West Coast oyster farming by <strong>turning science into survival.</strong></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sormi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-42-09.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scientific Breakthrough in Sustainable Aquaculture</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sablefish/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>As global demand for seafood continues to rise, the aquaculture industry faces growing pressure to produce more while minimizing ecological impacts. A key concern in marine fish farming is the risk of escapees interbreeding with wild populations, leading to genetic introgression and reduced fitness in native fish stocks. Now, a recent study led by former University of Washington CICOES postdoctoral researcher Dr.&nbsp;Yuzo R. Yanagitsuru offers a promising solution.</p>
<p>Published in <em>Aquaculture</em>, the study presents a <strong>proof-of-concept for a non-GMO, bath immersion–based technique for inducing sterility in sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria)</strong>—an emerging high-value aquaculture species also known as black cod. The approach targets a gene essential for reproductive cell development and aims to prevent escaped farmed fish from reproducing in the wild.</p>
<section id="a-scalable-gene-silencing-alternative-to-triploidy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-scalable-gene-silencing-alternative-to-triploidy"><strong>A Scalable, Gene-Silencing Alternative to Triploidy</strong></h3>
<p>While triploidization and genetic modification have been explored for sterility induction, both come with drawbacks—triploid fish can still be partially fertile, and GM fish face regulatory and public acceptance hurdles.</p>
<p>Instead, Dr.&nbsp;Yanagitsuru and collaborators used a <strong>Morpholino oligomer (MO)</strong> attached to a <strong>Vivo transporter</strong> to silence the <em>dead end</em> (<em>dnd</em>) gene—a critical regulator of primordial germ cell formation. The innovation lies in delivering this compound through a <strong>simple bath immersion</strong>, rather than invasive microinjection or genetic alteration.</p>
</section>
<section id="results-a-step-toward-sterile-sustainable-farming" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results-a-step-toward-sterile-sustainable-farming"><strong>Results: A Step Toward Sterile, Sustainable Farming</strong></h3>
<p>In controlled hatchery trials, sablefish eggs treated with the dnd-MO-Vivo compound before fertilization produced a subset of individuals that were completely sterile (8%) or had drastically reduced numbers of reproductive cells (18%). Importantly, sterile individuals developed normally in all other respects: they showed no major differences in growth, sex steroid hormone levels, or survival under semi-commercial rearing conditions.</p>
<p>Key findings include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Target specificity</strong>: dnd expression was limited to gonads and unfertilized eggs, confirming its value as a marker for germ cell presence.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>No adverse health effects</strong>: Sterile fish were physiologically indistinguishable from fertile fish in terms of somatic growth and overall condition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Higher efficacy pre-fertilization</strong>: The sterility induction was more effective when the treatment was applied before fertilization, likely due to increased permeability of the egg chorion.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="why-it-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-it-matters"><strong>Why It Matters</strong></h3>
<p>This method opens a new path for <strong>scalable, publicly acceptable sterility induction in marine finfish aquaculture</strong>. By eliminating the reproductive capability of escapees, it reduces ecological risk and helps safeguard the genetic integrity of wild populations—while also offering potential gains in growth efficiency and product quality for farmers.</p>
<p>Sablefish, already known for its rich flavor and high omega-3 content, now also stands to become a model species for innovative, sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next"><strong>What’s Next?</strong></h3>
<p>The authors emphasize that <strong>further optimization is needed</strong> to improve sterility rates and ensure consistent results across large-scale operations. Future research will likely explore different concentrations, immersion times, and additional species to assess broader applicability.</p>
<p>But for now, this work—driven by Dr.&nbsp;Yanagitsuru’s leadership—marks an important milestone in the development of non-GMO solutions to one of aquaculture’s biggest challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Citation</strong>:</p>
<p>Yanagitsuru, Y.R., Hayman, E.S., Fairgrieve, W.T., Zohar, Y., Wong, T-T., &amp; Luckenbach, J.A. (2025). <em>Proof-of-concept for sterility induction in sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria) via a scalable immersion-based gene silencing approach</em>. <em>Aquaculture</em>, 609, 742945. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2025.742945" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2025.742945</a></p>
<p>Podcast Episode featuring work: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/gene-pooling/id1802677296?i=1000718173868" class="uri">https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/gene-pooling/id1802677296?i=1000718173868</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>sterility</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sablefish/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Yanagitsuru_et_al_SterilityInduction_dnd_BathImmersion_SablefishProofOfConcept_2025.pdf_2025-07-20_13-09-45.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Celebrating Undergraduate Research</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-capstone/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>This spring, two outstanding undergraduate researchers in our lab—Genevieve Buchanan and Henry Berg—presented their senior capstone projects, showcasing months of hard work and scientific curiosity. Their research tackled critical questions related to marine invertebrate resilience in the face of environmental stress, and each presentation offered fresh insight into how shellfish species respond to changing ocean conditions.</p>
<section id="genevieve-buchanan-thermal-tolerance-in-a-stressful-world" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="genevieve-buchanan-thermal-tolerance-in-a-stressful-world">🦪 Genevieve Buchanan: Thermal Tolerance in a Stressful World</h2>
<p>Genevieve’s project, “Effects of Salinity and Ocean Acidification Stress on Pacific Oyster (Magallana gigas) Thermal Tolerance”, examined how prior exposure to low salinity and acidic conditions influences oyster survival during subsequent heat stress. Pacific oysters are economically vital to aquaculture industries and ecologically foundational to coastal ecosystems, yet they face increasing threats from climate change-induced stressors.</p>
<p>Through a carefully controlled experiment using oysters from the Point Whitney Shellfish Hatchery, Genevieve tested whether low pH or reduced salinity exposure would compound mortality under acute thermal stress. Her findings showed that, surprisingly, these prior stressors did not significantly impact thermal tolerance. This suggests that Pacific oysters may be energetically adapted to the variable conditions of the Pacific Northwest, offering a glimmer of hope for aquaculture resilience in the face of climate extremes.</p>
<p>🔗 <a href="https://youtu.be/4Yz1z1yZRGQ">Watch Genevieve’s full presentation on YouTube</a></p>
<p>📄 <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Genevieve_Buchanan_-_Capstone_Presentation.pptx">Download Genevieve’s Presentation Slides (PPTX)</a></p>
<p>⸻</p>
</section>
<section id="henry-berg-mussel-threads-and-climate-stress" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="henry-berg-mussel-threads-and-climate-stress">🧵 Henry Berg: Mussel Threads and Climate Stress</h2>
<p>Henry’s capstone, “Physiological Markers Associated with Byssus Attachment Following Environmental Perturbations in Marine Mussels”, focused on the byssal threads that mussels use to anchor themselves to surfaces—an essential trait for survival and aquaculture yield.</p>
<p>Comparing Mytilus trossulus and Mytilus galloprovincialis, Henry exposed mussels to ocean acidification, warming, and hypoxia, then measured thread production and metabolic rates. His results were striking: ocean acidification increased thread production in both species, while warming favored M. galloprovincialis. Hypoxia, however, drastically reduced thread output, particularly in M. galloprovincialis. These species-specific responses highlight the complexity of climate resilience and point to potential physiological markers that could inform aquaculture site selection and selective breeding strategies.</p>
<p>🔗 <a href="https://youtu.be/wkkv9eZpcik">Watch Henry’s full presentation on YouTube</a></p>
<p>📄 <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Marine_Mussels_Presentation.pptx">Download Henry’s Presentation Slides (PPTX)</a></p>
<p>⸻</p>
<p>A Proud Moment for Undergraduate Research</p>
<p>Projects were conducted under the guidance of Ariana Huffmyer and Matt George, respectively, and reflect the high caliber of undergraduate research in our lab. We are incredibly proud of Genevieve and Henry—not only for their scientific contributions but also for their clarity, creativity, and commitment to advancing our understanding of marine organism resilience in a changing world.</p>
<p>Please take a moment to view their presentations and join us in celebrating their accomplishments.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>shellfish</category>
  <category>capstone</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-capstone/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-06-16_10-44-13.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spotlight on Fellowship Success</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-fellowships/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>We are proud to celebrate two exceptional students in our lab who have each recently received prestigious fellowships in recognition of their innovative research tackling the urgent challenges of climate change and biodiversity conservation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_lab-photo-20250213-edited-SJW-01.JPG_36302626_pixels_2025-06-11_18-26-37.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>photo of fellows</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="zachary-bengtsson-nw-casc-fellow" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="zachary-bengtsson-nw-casc-fellow">Zachary Bengtsson – NW CASC Fellow</h2>
<p><a href="https://zbengt.github.io/notebook/">Zach</a> has been awarded a <strong>Northwest Climate Adaptation Science Center (NW CASC) Fellowship</strong>, joining a distinguished cohort of graduate researchers from institutions across the Northwest. His project, titled <em>Developing computational tools for genetic risk assessment of Olympia oyster (Ostrea lurida) populations in the Puget Sound</em>, focuses on advancing genetic tools that help guide the sustainable restoration of Washington’s native oyster.<br>
</p>
<p>Zach’s research integrates environmental drivers of local adaptation, hatchery management, and climate resilience to evaluate how restoration practices affect the genetic diversity of wild oyster populations. The selection committee praised his proposal for its clear relevance to stakeholder needs—highlighted by strong support from the Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife—and his deep commitment to co-produced, actionable science. His work will provide valuable tools for conservation managers as they balance ecological recovery with long-term resilience in Puget Sound estuaries.</p>
</section>
<section id="kathleen-durkin-smithsonian-fellow" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kathleen-durkin-smithsonian-fellow">Kathleen Durkin – Smithsonian Fellow</h2>
<p><a href="https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/">Kathleen</a> has received a fellowship to conduct groundbreaking research at the <strong>Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History</strong>, where she will pioneer the use of <strong>nanopore sequencing to map DNA methylation in archival coral specimens</strong>. Her project represents one of the first efforts to explore historical DNA methylation (hDNA) in invertebrates using museum collections.</p>
<p>Drawing from coral samples that span over a century of collection history, Kathleen’s work will assess how epigenetic changes—particularly DNA methylation—can offer insights into coral stress responses and environmental resilience over time. By applying Oxford Nanopore Technology’s direct sequencing platform, she aims to overcome the limitations of traditional bisulfite sequencing in degraded DNA and establish a robust method for tracking historical epigenomic signatures.</p>
<p>This innovative research will not only advance our understanding of coral adaptation during a period of unprecedented climate change but also expand the utility of natural history collections for modern genomic and conservation science.</p>
<hr>
<p>These fellowships reflect the drive and creativity that Zach and Kathleen bring to their work, and we are excited to watch their projects unfold over the coming year. Their success exemplifies the kind of interdisciplinary, forward-thinking science that will shape the future of marine conservation and climate adaptation.</p>
<p>Please join us in congratulating Zachary and Kathleen on these outstanding achievements!</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>climate</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-fellowships/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_lab-photo-20250213-edited-SJW-01.JPG_36302626_pixels_2025-06-11_18-26-37.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Decoding Marine Memory</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-epimar/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>At EPIMAR2025 in Barcelona, a gathering of global marine scientists illuminated the hidden world of epigenetic regulation in marine invertebrates. These tiny organisms, often overlooked in genomic studies, are now at the forefront of revealing how life beneath the waves adapts, survives, and thrives in rapidly changing oceans.</p>
<p>In this post, we highlight key presentations that explored how DNA methylation, RNA modifications, and chromatin remodeling influence invertebrate development, stress response, and even intergenerational adaptation.</p>
<hr>
<section id="mussels-and-methylation-maps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mussels-and-methylation-maps">Mussels and Methylation Maps</h3>
<p><strong>Enrico D’Aniello</strong>&nbsp;and colleagues presented the first high-resolution DNA methylation map in the mussel&nbsp;<em>Mytilus galloprovincialis</em>. This map revealed key regulatory elements and tissue-specific methylation patterns, providing a baseline for understanding how gene expression is modulated in response to environmental shifts.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="modifications-in-oysters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modifications-in-oysters">Modifications in Oysters</h3>
<p>In&nbsp;<em>Crassostrea gigas</em>,&nbsp;<strong>Natacha Clairet</strong>&nbsp;demonstrated that m6A RNA methylation plays a pivotal role in neural development and transcript splicing. Her work showed that these epitranscriptomic changes are not only developmentally regulated but may also mediate environmental responses.</p>
<p>Building on the oyster story,&nbsp;<strong>Guillaume Rivière</strong>&nbsp;showed that thermal stress leaves lasting epigenetic marks on oyster gill tissues. This “epigenetic memory” alters gene expression patterns in subsequent exposures, pointing to methylation as a resilience mechanism.</p>
<p>Meanwhile,&nbsp;<strong>Sophie Valk</strong>&nbsp;examined oysters undergoing natural sex transitions, finding unique DNA methylation signatures in hermaphrodites. Her work hints at epigenetic regulation as a driver of reproductive plasticity.</p>
<p><strong>Elyna Bouchereau</strong> from the University of Perpignan explored the methylome of <em>Vibrio aestuarianus</em>, a bacterial pathogen of oysters, revealing how epigenetic signatures may influence virulence and host interaction, while <strong>Amélie Dellong</strong> presented a multi-omics approach to decipher chromatin structure in <em>Magallana gigas</em>, offering new insight into the regulatory architecture of oyster genomes.</p>
<p><strong>Marta Pascual</strong> presented a population epigenomics study of <em>Crassostrea gigas</em> along the Iberian Atlantic coast, showing that DNA methylation patterns vary significantly between wild and farmed populations, suggesting a potential role in local adaptation and domestication.</p>
<p><strong>Lénaig Boulard</strong> investigated the epigenetic responses of Pacific oysters to ocean acidification, demonstrating methylation changes in genes associated with shell formation and oxidative stress defense.</p>
<p><strong>Céline Cosseau</strong> explored transgenerational epigenetic inheritance in oysters, showing that environmental exposures in adult oysters can lead to stable methylation changes in offspring, particularly in stress-response genes.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="corals-and-the-code-of-light" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="corals-and-the-code-of-light">Corals and the Code of Light</h3>
<p>Reef-building corals were another highlight.&nbsp;<strong>Kathleen Durkin</strong>&nbsp;described how miRNAs and lncRNAs shape coral development and immunity under heat stress.&nbsp;<strong>Kelly Gómez-Campo</strong>&nbsp;added that light exposure during development can modulate DNA methylation patterns and downstream gene networks in corals, underscoring how tightly environment and epigenome are interlinked.<br>
<strong>Hollie Putnam</strong> presented a comprehensive study on the spatial and temporal dynamics of epigenetic regulation in reef-building corals, while <strong>Jill Ashey</strong> highlighted the critical roles of non-coding RNAs during early coral development, particularly in mediating the maternal-to-zygotic transition.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="histone-modifications-in-sea-anemones" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="histone-modifications-in-sea-anemones">Histone Modifications in Sea Anemones</h3>
<p>In the heat-stressed sea anemone&nbsp;<em>Exaiptasia diaphana</em>,&nbsp;<strong>Mascha Dix</strong>&nbsp;presented findings on histone modifications (H3K27me3 and H3K4me3) as key players in regulating gene expression. These modifications allow rapid but reversible responses to changing thermal conditions.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="hypoxia-and-neural-epigenetics-in-sea-hares" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hypoxia-and-neural-epigenetics-in-sea-hares">Hypoxia and Neural Epigenetics in Sea Hares</h3>
<p><strong>Javier Rodriguez-Casariego</strong>&nbsp;studied the sea hare&nbsp;<em>Aplysia californica</em>&nbsp;and showed that DNA methylation shifts in neural tissues under hypoxic conditions suggest a role for epigenetic plasticity in environmental stress tolerance.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-epigenetics-as-a-unifying-language" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-epigenetics-as-a-unifying-language">Conclusion: Epigenetics as a Unifying Language</h3>
<p>These studies collectively show that epigenetic mechanisms are not just molecular curiosities—they are central to how marine invertebrates sense, remember, and adapt to their environment. Whether through methylation, non-coding RNA, or histone marks, the language of the epigenome is being translated into actionable insights for conservation, aquaculture, and understanding evolution under climate change.</p>
<p>EPIMAR2025 made one thing clear: the future of marine biology will be written in epigenetic code.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-epimar/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_EPIMAR_2025__Barcelona_Spain_-_May_27-30_2025-06-11_17-59-29.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Environmental Priming in Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lewis-smith/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>We're proud to share a new publication by former lab member <strong>Connor Lewis-Smith</strong>, now a Social Scientist with NOAA's Northwest Fisheries Science Center. His article, <em>"Navigating ocean acidification in shellfish aquaculture: Stakeholder perspectives of developing strategies in the U.S. Pacific Region"</em>, was just released in <em>Aquaculture Reports</em> and offers an in-depth look at how shellfish growers across the U.S. Pacific Coast are responding to ocean acidification and related environmental stressors.</p>
<p>The study draws on structured interviews with producers from Washington, Oregon, California, Alaska, and Hawaii to capture evolving perceptions of ocean acidification and industry interest in emerging adaptation strategies. Notably, concern about ocean acidification appears to have declined in the past decade, as growers increasingly focus on intersecting threats such as harmful algal blooms, disease, and rising temperatures.</p>
<p>The paper explores two adaptation strategies under development: <strong>parental priming</strong>—a technique involving exposure of broodstock to stressful conditions to enhance offspring resilience—and <strong>native species portfolio expansion</strong>. While industry support for both strategies was mixed and often contingent on further scientific validation, the study emphasizes the importance of early engagement between researchers and growers to co-develop viable solutions.</p>
<p>Importantly, this research aligns directly with <strong>ongoing environmental priming work in our lab</strong>, where we are experimentally testing how exposure to low pH and high temperature conditions in adult shellfish can influence offspring performance. By integrating physiological, transcriptomic, and lipidomic data, our current NOAA-funded work seeks to identify the mechanisms underlying carryover effects and inform hatchery practices that enhance larval resilience under future ocean conditions.</p>
<p>Connor's collaboration with our group helped build the interdisciplinary foundation for this kind of applied science—where social, biological, and ecological factors intersect to shape adaptation in real-world settings. We're excited to see how his work complements and extends our efforts to support a more resilient shellfish aquaculture sector.</p>
<p>Read the full article <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aqrep.2025.102858">here</a>.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lewis-smith/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-05-07_11-42-09.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
