<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Turning the tide</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/lspencer-cod/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Chris is featured on UW’s “Be Boundless” site. Read full article <a href="https://www.washington.edu/boundless/turning-the-tide-marine-biology/">here</a>. Below is a short snippet of the feature along with an amazing video!</strong></p>
<p>On a windy June afternoon, Chris Mantegna, ’21, encourages a half-dozen undergraduates to flip over barnacle-studded rocks and sift through seaweed. Equipped with clipboards to record their findings, they’re creating a snapshot of the organisms in the island’s intertidal zone — from orange sea cucumbers to the camouflaged armored mollusks called chitons.</p>
<p>Mantegna, a third-year graduate student in aquatic and fishery sciences, has spent the past three summers in Washington’s San Juan Islands, mentoring undergrads here on Yellow Island — a pristine 11-acre nature preserve owned by the Nature Conservancy. She created this eight-week program for students to get their hands dirty in the field and learn cutting-edge lab techniques at the UW Friday Harbor Laboratories — where she had a transformational research experience herself as a Husky undergrad.</p>
<p>This mentorship program reflects Mantegna’s passion both for advancing the science and for making it more inclusive and accessible to others. Her face lights up when she spots a small chiton (her favorite) clinging to the bottom of a rock, and she invites others to feel the mollusk’s tough plated back. Even Mantegna’s doctoral work — examining the genetic response of shellfish to contaminants in Puget Sound waterways — has a focus on community outreach and environmental literacy.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VLLocGcP9S8?si=UzEadZGT7XryVpEV" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Mantegna says we have a better chance at fighting climate change when everyone — scientists and community members — feels connected to their environment and each other. “I can tell you that the ocean is dying or that we have too much acidification,” says Mantegna, a U.S. Navy veteran who is the first in her family to graduate from college. “But it doesn’t matter if you’ve never had the chance to feel the joy that comes from this place.”</p>
<p>Finish feature <a href="https://www.washington.edu/boundless/turning-the-tide-marine-biology/">here</a>.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>dna</category>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/lspencer-cod/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-07_12-56-13.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring Pacific Cod Resilience in a Warming Ocean</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Spencer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-boundless/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In our latest update on the Pacific cod juvenile temperature study, we've gained deeper insights into how these remarkable fish respond to different temperatures. This research is part of a larger effort to understand the resilience of marine species in changing environments.</p>
<p><strong>Genetic Insights Reveal Population Origins</strong></p>
<p>We began with genetic analyses, using data from thousands of genetic markers to determine the origin of our experimental fish. All our test fish were linked to the spawning grounds in the western Gulf of Alaska (wGOA) and the Eastern Bering Sea (EBS). This finding allows us to focus on the thermal resilience of cod from this particular region, which is vital as they face shifts in temperature in their natural habitats.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-00-51.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Temperature's Role in Energy and Lipid Storage</strong></p>
<p>Our collaborator Louise Copement analyzed liver lipids in these juvenile cod, focusing on triglycerides and other key lipid types that are crucial for overwinter survival. The results showed a clear trend: energy storage, primarily in the form of triglycerides, peaked at 9°C, then dropped sharply at higher temperatures, especially at 16°C. This suggests that extreme warmth could deplete essential energy reserves, reducing the fish's survival prospects in the cold winter months.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-01-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Optimal Growth Temperatures and Physiological Responses</strong></p>
<p>We also observed that juvenile cod exhibit optimal growth at approximately 12.3°C, slightly higher than previous findings. With higher temperatures, growth rates plateau or decline, mirroring the energy storage patterns. Interestingly, the gene expression data from liver tissues revealed significant temperature-driven shifts, especially in energy production, lipid metabolism, and immune response genes. This molecular data adds a new layer to our understanding of temperature tolerance.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-01-22.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Integrated Data: A Pathway to Genomic Resilience Markers</strong></p>
<p>Combining growth, lipid, and gene expression data, we've started identifying genes that correlate with enhanced resilience at specific temperatures. This approach could spotlight genetic markers for thermal resilience, offering clues about cod populations best suited to future ocean conditions.</p>
<p>In summary, this research underscores the delicate balance juvenile Pacific cod must maintain in their energy reserves and growth under variable temperatures. These findings will help guide conservation and management efforts as we work to protect Pacific cod populations in a warming world.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-boundless/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_13-57-57.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep dive into the handbook</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-handbook/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A unique perspective. You will never guess what they reveal!</p>
<section id="audio" class="level1">
<h1>Audio</h1>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/handbook.wav"></video></div>
</section>
<section id="transcript" class="level1">
<h1>Transcript</h1>
<p>Welcome to The Deep Dive, where we dig into the nitty gritty of fascinating topics.</p>
<p>Today, we’re taking a deep dive into the Roberts Lab at the University of Washington, and we’re doing that through the lens of their handbook.</p>
<p>It’s more than just a rule book, though, isn’t it?</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p>It’s like a window into their whole approach to science.</p>
<p>Everything from, like, groundbreaking research to how they actually build their research culture.</p>
<p>And they’re known for being incredibly transparent, which this handbook really embodies.</p>
<p>Yeah, it’s refreshing.</p>
<p>And speaking of refreshing, I have to ask you about this freezer alarm situation.</p>
<p>Oh, yes.</p>
<p>So they have, like, a dedicated alarm for their ultra-low temperature freezers, right?</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>But there’s this 15-minute delay before anyone actually gets notified if it goes off.</p>
<p>Can you imagine?</p>
<p>It’s like a slow-motion heart attack for a researcher.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>All those precious samples.</p>
<p>I’d be a wreck.</p>
<p>It really highlights the fragility of these biological materials they’re working with.</p>
<p>RNA, proteins, these things have to be stored at, like, negative 80 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Wow.</p>
<p>Even a short power outage could be disastrous.</p>
<p>So is that delay, like, a safety net to give the system a chance to recover?</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>It’s a calculated risk.</p>
<p>They’re trying to balance preventing false alarms while also, you know, protecting those invaluable research materials.</p>
<p>Makes sense.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And it seems like that emphasis on meticulousness, on minimizing risk, it really comes through in the whole handbook, especially when they talk about lab safety and chemicals.</p>
<p>It’s serious business.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>Like with Arnazole RT, they’re very clear about it being corrosive, potentially harmful if you inhale it, even disposing of it.</p>
<p>It’s a whole multi-step process.</p>
<p>Well, they’re dealing with some pretty potent stuff.</p>
<p>It underscores their dedication to, you know, not just scientific rigor, but the actual well-being of their researchers.</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>It’s like they’re creating an environment where cutting-edge science can happen, but it can happen safely.</p>
<p>Safety first.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And that meticulousness, that doing things by the book, it goes beyond just lab safety, you know.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>It’s woven into their whole research philosophy, which makes you wonder, if they’re this careful with safety, how does that translate to, say, data management or collaboration?</p>
<p>Good question.</p>
<p>And as luck would have it, that’s exactly what we’re going to be digging into in the rest of this deep dive.</p>
<p>You know, it’s funny you should mention that because the next thing that really struck me about this handbook was their code of conduct.</p>
<p>Oh, interesting.</p>
<p>How so?</p>
<p>Well, for one, it’s incredibly detailed, even for like their diversity, equity, and inclusion meetings.</p>
<p>You don’t always see that level of, I don’t know, formality in a lab handbook.</p>
<p>What kinds of things are we talking about here?</p>
<p>They have these great phrases like, “Elevate impact above intent,” and, “Expect and accept non-closure.”</p>
<p>Like, really specific guidelines.</p>
<p>Huh.</p>
<p>It sounds like they’re trying to foster a very specific kind of research environment.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>One where people feel comfortable admitting they don’t know everything, which, let’s be honest, is most of the time in research, right?</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p>Science is all about embracing uncertainty.</p>
<p>But it takes a certain culture to really allow for that.</p>
<p>Totally.</p>
<p>And it seems like they’re putting a lot of emphasis on making sure everyone feels heard and respected, especially in those DEI meetings.</p>
<p>Well, and that makes sense, right?</p>
<p>If you want to have those tough conversations about diversity and inclusion, you need to create a space where people feel safe to speak their minds.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>No, you’re right.</p>
<p>It all ties together.</p>
<p>And then there’s this whole thing about mentorship.</p>
<p>They really encourage lab members to have multiple mentors, not just one.</p>
<p>That’s interesting.</p>
<p>Most labs I’ve seen, it’s pretty standard to have one primary mentor.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>So I thought that was really unique.</p>
<p>It kind of speaks to this idea of providing a well-rounded experience, right?</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>Different mentors bring different perspectives, different areas of expertise.</p>
<p>It can really enrich a researcher’s training.</p>
<p>Okay, so we’ve got meticulous safety protocols, a very deliberate approach to their lab culture.</p>
<p>But we also know they’re dealing with a massive amount of data.</p>
<p>Like their handbook mentions Nightingale for sequencing this whole network attached storage system called Gannett.</p>
<p>Don’t forget the supercomputer.</p>
<p>MOCs, was it?</p>
<p>Oh, right.</p>
<p>MOCs.</p>
<p>I mean, it’s a lot.</p>
<p>It really makes you wonder how they manage it all.</p>
<p>It’s a data tsunami.</p>
<p>How do they keep from drowning?</p>
<p>Well, for one thing, they’re incredibly organized.</p>
<p>Like religiously organized.</p>
<p>Give me the details.</p>
<p>Think detailed metadata for every single experiment, strict folder structures on their network.</p>
<p>They even have readme files.</p>
<p>Readme files for every folder, seriously.</p>
<p>Seriously.</p>
<p>And it’s all part of this commitment to open science.</p>
<p>They want their research to be accessible, transparent.</p>
<p>So anyone could theoretically go in and understand their data, their methods.</p>
<p>That’s the idea.</p>
<p>It’s about breaking down those silos, you know, fostering collaboration, avoiding unnecessary redundancy, ultimately speeding up discoveries.</p>
<p>It’s kind of inspiring, actually.</p>
<p>It’s like they’re playing the long game, advancing science as a whole, not just their own work.</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>But okay, even with perfect organization, all that data analysis, it’s got to be intense.</p>
<p>They mentioned Jupiter notebooks in the handbook.</p>
<p>Right, and mocks the supercomputer.</p>
<p>And they even talk about using like the command line.</p>
<p>Hard course, so they’re not messing around.</p>
<p>Well, they’re equipping their researchers with a seriously powerful toolkit.</p>
<p>But it goes beyond just the tech.</p>
<p>They even recommend this book, Getting Things Done.</p>
<p>Time management.</p>
<p>Time management.</p>
<p>It’s all about efficiency.</p>
<p>They don’t just give them the tools.</p>
<p>They give them the training, the resources to actually use them well.</p>
<p>It’s like they’ve thought of everything.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And it doesn’t stop there.</p>
<p>They have a whole section on conferences, funding opportunities, even like travel grants.</p>
<p>They want their researchers to be well-rounded, right?</p>
<p>Not just stuck in the lab, but out there presenting, collaborating, getting their work funded.</p>
<p>It’s impressive, I have to say.</p>
<p>Looking at the Roberts Lab this way, through their handbook, you really get a sense of the thoughtfulness, the care that goes into building a successful research environment.</p>
<p>It’s not just about, you know, the results, the discoveries.</p>
<p>It’s the people, the culture.</p>
<p>And that commitment to moving science forward in a way that’s open and collaborative, it’s really something.</p>
<p>Makes you wonder what they’ll accomplish, what amazing discoveries are on the horizon for them.</p>
<p>It does, doesn’t it?</p>
<p>And that’s something to ponder as we wrap up this deep dive into the world of the Roberts Lab.</p>
<p>Until next time, keep exploring, keep questioning, and keep diving deep.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>handbook</category>
  <category>audio</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-handbook/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Roberts_Lab_Handbook_2024-09-14_13-23-52.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery-based Environmental Conditioning Activities</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>During this past year a series of hatchery-based environmental conditioning activities (referred to as hardening) were completed with oysters out-planted onto three farms to evaluate performance. Additionally, climate resiliency was assessed in hardened oysters under controlled conditions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_overview.png_2024-08-29_13-35-45.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Experimental Overview</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="farm-outplanting" class="level1">
<h1>Farm Outplanting</h1>
<p>Early in the season, a cohort of oysters were subject to (a) daily thermal hardening for approximately two weeks prior to out planting in hanging bags on a farm in Sequim Bay, alongside a control group. These oyster will be assessed in early Autumn 2024. Later in the season oysters were subjected to a more diverse series of hardening conditions with oyster split between two commercial farms, one located in Willapa Bay and a second in the San Juan Islands. The combination of age classes and hardening conditions were as follows: b) small seed / daily thermal hardening, c) adult / daily thermal hardening, d) small seed / weekly thermal hardening, e1) large seed / weekly thermal hardening, e2) large seed / weekly zero salinity hardening. These hardening activities spanned from several weeks to months. For all hardening efforts controls were also outplanted. Oysters out planted in Willapa Bay will be assessed for survival and growth in early September 2024. Oysters out planted in the San Juan Islands have be subject to more routine monitoring. At this site we are currently observing a trend where oysters subjected to the daily hardening regime are surviving better than controls.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-37-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Wescott Bay Outplanting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-1" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 1</h1>
<p>To assess the effectiveness of hardening within a hatchery setting, four ages classes of oysters were examined: adults (40-100mm), juveniles (20-55mm), seed (6-15mm), and spat ()1-6mm). In order to assess hardening potential and environmental memory, oysters were subject to an initial chronic temperature stress, then subjected to a secondary stress to see if the response to secondary stress was impacted by initial exposure. During the chronic temperature stress period, oysters from each age class were exposed to a daily 25ºC temperature spike. This repeated for 14 days starting on October 1. Control oysters from each cohort were maintained at an ambient temperature of approximately 17ºC during the same time period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-38-28.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Hardening and acute stress temperature timeline</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Adult oysters in stress conditions were also subject to mechanical stress at day 1, 7, and 48, which was induced by 15 minutes. At day 147 (7 weeks after initial chronic stress), both stressed and non-stressed adult, juvenile, spat, and seed were subjected to a secondary stress of 30 minutes in 32ºC. Gill tissue was sampled immediately after and placed into RNAlater. Spat and seed that were too small to dissect gill tissue were sampled whole with all tissue used in gene expression assays. To date we have analyzed gene expression data from seed and spat. There was no mortality during this trial. Hardening increased growth (compared to controls) in spat. Further there was a reduced transcriptional response in spat. These data suggest temperature hardening of spat could result in a resiliency to later temperature stress whereby energy resources could favor growth.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-39-30.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Growth Performance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Gene expression profiles (spat)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-54.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic physiology explanation when hardened spat are exposed to acute temperature stress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-2" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 2</h1>
<p>In a second experimental regime, juvenile oysters were subjected to four hardening conditions 1) high temperature (35°C), 2) high temperature and freshwater, 3) freshwater, and 4) poly I:C immersion. These were exposures that occurred every other day for about 3 weeks. Approximately 1 month after hardening, oysters were brought to the lab and subjected to metabolic assessment using resazurin at 18°C and 42°C. Resazurin is a dye that is commonly used in cell viability, and it works by changing color as an organism consumes oxygen. Survival was assessed during the resazurin assay and 24 hours later. To date, our analysis suggests metabolic activity of the 42°C oysters was higher in the control oysters than previously hardened oysters. In the near future we will assess the relationship of metabolic activity and survival however it appears higher metabolic rate directly correlates with mortality. Taken together these sets of controlled experiments suggest hardening does have an impact on resiliency, though dependent on age, hardening duration, and subsequent environmental conditions.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_logo-resazuring_2024-08-29_13-50-31.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Resazurin assay (4 hour / 2 temperatures) on hardened oysters"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-10-49.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Intertidal Innovators</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-intertidal/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_1373.png_2024-08-19_12-59-21.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 16, participants in the Intertidal Innovators program presented their work to the community. The program, which was a collaboration sponsored by the UW Earthlab program, provided students with the opportunity to learn about marine science and conservation through art.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-19_13-09-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Quote
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This program has lasted for 10 days, but during those days we have learned and worked very hard to give you this project. And we are proud to say that there are a bunch of hard working members in our program that have learned new skills and have gained knowledge in this program So in this journey, you will learn a lot about our work and marine life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>At the community showcase, students guide small groups around the intertidal, sharing their art with tablets and speakers. It was a great experience that showcased videos, poems, live demonostrations, and stories. Anyone can checkout their guided tour at Golden Garden Park via the echoes app - <a href="https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC" class="uri">https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC</a></p>
<p>Below is a video that takes you behind the scenes on the 10-day experience students participated in.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PsVyUPzu2_A" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-intertidal/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_The_Golden_Hour_-_a_geolocated_audio_walk_by_Intertidal_Innovators_on_ECHOES_2024-08-19_12-50-25.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery Field Day at Point Whitney</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On May 6, 2024, Dr.&nbsp;Ariana Huffmyer, an NSF Ocean Sciences Postdoctoral Fellow from the University of Rhode Island and University of Washington, shared insights from a field day at Point Whitney. This comprehensive post revealed the detailed process of managing and monitoring oyster growth and stress testing, providing a clear framework for hatchery management.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Link to Full Notebook Post
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/" class="uri">https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Overview of Field Day Activities</strong> The objective was to monitor the health and stress responses of oyster cohorts at the hatchery. Key activities included calibrating monitoring equipment, feeding the oysters, and assessing the impacts of temperature and freshwater stress.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Monitoring Equipment Calibration:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer set up and calibrated an Orion Star A325 probe to measure pH, temperature, and conductivity. By using buffers of varying pH and a conductivity solution, she ensured accurate measurements. The pH was measured on the NBS scale, considered sufficient since ocean acidification experiments weren’t being conducted.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Feeding Protocol:</strong> The oysters were pulse-fed, where approximately 1/3 of a 5-gallon bucket was distributed among the tanks. This ensured that the animals received sufficient nutrition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fluorometry and Physiochemical Measurements:</strong> Fluorometry measurements were conducted before and after feeding, providing data on oyster metabolic activity. Additionally, pH, temperature, and conductivity were measured across different tanks, offering valuable weekly insights into water quality.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stress Testing Regimen:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer conducted a 30-minute stress test for specific oyster cohorts using freshwater and elevated temperature exposures. Animals were subjected to 25°C temperature and freshwater immersion, replicating environmental stressors they might face. Trays were labeled and organized by stressor type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Growth Characterization:</strong> Size measurements were taken using a waterproof digital caliper. Cohorts were categorized based on their respective stressors, creating a comprehensive understanding of their growth patterns.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ploidy Testing Preparations:</strong> A selection of oysters from different cohorts was collected for ploidy testing to distinguish between diploid and triploid oysters. They were stored in mesh bags, and the testing results would provide critical information for future breeding programs.</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Hatchery_field_day_at_Point_Whitney_May_6_2024__Ariana_S_Huffmyer__NSF_Ocean_Sciences_Postdoctoral_Fellow_University_of_Rhod_2024-05-11_14-51-46.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>heath-tray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Takeaways for Hatchery Science</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer’s systematic approach highlights the significance of precise monitoring and stress testing in hatchery science. Understanding oyster resilience to environmental stressors is crucial for aquaculture sustainability. Her work at Point Whitney offers a detailed protocol that could be replicated or adapted by other researchers to monitor and improve hatchery operations.</p>
<p>The future of hatchery management will depend heavily on such frameworks, where real-time data collection and analysis enable researchers to respond promptly to environmental changes.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/bucket.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
