<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Unraveling the Intricacies of Enrichment Analysis</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-enrich/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In our most recent lab meeting, we delved into the fascinating world of enrichment analysis. This statistical method is a cornerstone of our research, helping us identify significantly over-represented subsets of proteins or genes within our data.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/GMT20240509-195925_Recording_gallery_1920x1080.mp4"></video></div>
<section id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis">The Power of Enrichment Analysis</h2>
<p>Enrichment analysis allows us to compare a small subset of genes or proteins to a larger set, identifying overrepresentation. This can provide valuable insights into the biological processes that are most relevant to our research.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-deep-dive-into-david" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-deep-dive-into-david">A Deep Dive into David</h2>
<p>One of the tools we use for enrichment analysis is David. During the meeting, we explored how to upload gene lists and backgrounds into David, and how to interpret the results it provides. This tool is invaluable in helping us understand the complex relationships and patterns within our data.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-reference-list-debate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-reference-list-debate">The Reference List Debate</h2>
<p>An interesting discussion arose around what to use as a reference list in enrichment analysis. Should it be all the genes detected in the data set, or all genes in a reference genome? This question sparked a lively debate, highlighting the complexities and nuances of enrichment analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo">Visualizing Gene Ontology with Revigo</h2>
<p>To help us visualize gene ontology, we use a tool called Revigo. This tool provides a visual representation of the relationships between genes, making it easier to understand the complex data we work with.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-lighter-moment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-lighter-moment">A Lighter Moment</h2>
<p>Amidst the serious scientific discussions, we also had a lighter moment when a team member shared a story about narrowly avoiding a parking ticket. It’s moments like these that remind us of the importance of camaraderie and humor in the lab.</p>
<hr>
<p>Our lab meetings are a crucial part of our research process, providing a space for us to discuss, debate, and learn together. Stay tuned for more insights from our lab meetings in future posts!</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-enrich/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/enrich.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery Field Day at Point Whitney</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On May 6, 2024, Dr.&nbsp;Ariana Huffmyer, an NSF Ocean Sciences Postdoctoral Fellow from the University of Rhode Island and University of Washington, shared insights from a field day at Point Whitney. This comprehensive post revealed the detailed process of managing and monitoring oyster growth and stress testing, providing a clear framework for hatchery management.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Link to Full Notebook Post
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/" class="uri">https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Overview of Field Day Activities</strong> The objective was to monitor the health and stress responses of oyster cohorts at the hatchery. Key activities included calibrating monitoring equipment, feeding the oysters, and assessing the impacts of temperature and freshwater stress.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Monitoring Equipment Calibration:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer set up and calibrated an Orion Star A325 probe to measure pH, temperature, and conductivity. By using buffers of varying pH and a conductivity solution, she ensured accurate measurements. The pH was measured on the NBS scale, considered sufficient since ocean acidification experiments weren’t being conducted.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Feeding Protocol:</strong> The oysters were pulse-fed, where approximately 1/3 of a 5-gallon bucket was distributed among the tanks. This ensured that the animals received sufficient nutrition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fluorometry and Physiochemical Measurements:</strong> Fluorometry measurements were conducted before and after feeding, providing data on oyster metabolic activity. Additionally, pH, temperature, and conductivity were measured across different tanks, offering valuable weekly insights into water quality.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stress Testing Regimen:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer conducted a 30-minute stress test for specific oyster cohorts using freshwater and elevated temperature exposures. Animals were subjected to 25°C temperature and freshwater immersion, replicating environmental stressors they might face. Trays were labeled and organized by stressor type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Growth Characterization:</strong> Size measurements were taken using a waterproof digital caliper. Cohorts were categorized based on their respective stressors, creating a comprehensive understanding of their growth patterns.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ploidy Testing Preparations:</strong> A selection of oysters from different cohorts was collected for ploidy testing to distinguish between diploid and triploid oysters. They were stored in mesh bags, and the testing results would provide critical information for future breeding programs.</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/http:/gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Hatchery_field_day_at_Point_Whitney_May_6_2024__Ariana_S_Huffmyer__NSF_Ocean_Sciences_Postdoctoral_Fellow_University_of_Rhod_2024-05-11_14-51-46.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">heath-tray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Takeaways for Hatchery Science</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer’s systematic approach highlights the significance of precise monitoring and stress testing in hatchery science. Understanding oyster resilience to environmental stressors is crucial for aquaculture sustainability. Her work at Point Whitney offers a detailed protocol that could be replicated or adapted by other researchers to monitor and improve hatchery operations.</p>
<p>The future of hatchery management will depend heavily on such frameworks, where real-time data collection and analysis enable researchers to respond promptly to environmental changes.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/bucket.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hardening in oysters drives increased growth</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In the meticulously orchestrated world of marine science, a groundbreaking experiment has unfolded in the hands of <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io">Eric Essington</a>, casting the spotlight on an unlikely protagonist: the oyster. This narrative begins with the arrival of 235 adult oysters from Pacific Hybreed, their sizes ranging impressively from 40 to 100mm, and further complemented by a diverse younger contingent—120 juveniles, 120 seed, and approximately 120 spat, all courtesy of the USDA’s 2023 spawn.</p>
<p>The experimental setup divided these oysters into two groups: one destined for a control tank, mirroring their natural aquatic environment at a serene 17ºC, and the other for a treatment tank, where conditions were significantly altered. The latter group was subjected to a deliberate increase in temperature, a gradual ascent of 2ºC per hour until the water reached a stress-inducing 26ºC, maintained for six hours daily over a seven-week span (began 10 2 2023, ended 11 21 2023). This thermal regimen aimed to simulate the increasingly erratic and harsh conditions wrought by climate change.</p>
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/http:/gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Explanation_2024-03-08_15-17-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Adding a layer of complexity, adults and juveniles were subjected to mechanical stress, an innovative use of a salad spinner for 15 minutes on selected dates (10/2/2023, 10/4/2023, 10/11/2023). This unusual methodology aimed to mimic the physical disturbances oysters might face in their natural habitats, from tumbling in currents to encounters with predators and debris.</p>
<p>The culmination of this phase was marked by a meticulous sampling process on November 21, 2023. Selected groups of oysters were divided for detailed analysis, with some undergoing immediate tissue sampling for RNA and DNA analysis, while others faced an additional stress test—a 30-minute immersion in 32ºC water followed by a tumbling session in the salad spinner. This process was designed to simulate an acute stress event, allowing researchers to gauge the oysters’ physiological responses to compounded stressors.</p>
<p>Several months later, on February 28, 2024, the experiment was revisited with a focused approach. This time, the younger generation of oysters was spotlighted, undergoing tissue sampling without the prior mechanical stress, to isolate the effects of thermal stress.</p>
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/http:/gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/growth.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Take-away to date</strong> - Stress hardening in spat in October and November resulted in increased growth compared to controls in February.</p>
<p>This experiment is not merely an investigation into the resilience of oysters to thermal and mechanical stress; it’s a narrative about adaptation, survival, and the intricate dance of life beneath the waves.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io/data-explanation/">Eric’s Post</a> for more details.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/pw.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="124" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Are you really prepared?</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-prep/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/people.html#ariana-s.-huffmyer-phd">Ariana</a> lead a great tutorial on being prepared and planning for science. The narrative underscored the importance of thorough preparation and planning, including considering alternative uses for collected data, planning for potential pitfalls, and ensuring that experimental designs are robust against unforeseen challenges. This includes the practical aspects of laboratory work, field studies, and data analysis, emphasizing the value of learning from past experiences and being flexible in research approaches.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Exp_prep.mov"></video></div>
<p>Designing scientific experiments requires extensive planning to ensure projects run smoothly and yield meaningful results. Here are some important aspects to consider when preparing for research:</p>
<p><strong>Clearly Define Your Hypothesis and Objectives</strong>: Having a clear hypothesis drives your experimental design and analysis approach. Define what you aim to test upfront.</p>
<p><strong>Prepare Detailed Protocols</strong>: Write step-by-step protocols for all procedures well before starting. Practice techniques on mock datasets to work out kinks.</p>
<p><strong>Plan Your Data Collection</strong>: Design data sheets, name conventions, and metadata standards early. Consider sample sizes and ensure you collect the right data to answer your questions.</p>
<p><strong>Schedule Carefully</strong>: Block out experiment timelines, factoring permitting needs and collaborator availability. Leave buffer time for unexpected issues.</p>
<p><strong>Create Organizational Systems</strong>: Use checklists, spreadsheets, and visual aids to track tasks and ensure all preparation steps are completed thoroughly.</p>
<p><strong>Anticipate Challenges</strong>: Brainstorm potential pitfalls and have contingency plans. Run test analyses to flag problems before using real data.</p>
<p>Proper preparation is key to running successful, high-quality experiments that yield meaningful scientific insights. Taking the time to carefully plan experimental design and logistics pays off in efficient, productive research.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-prep/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/prep.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sharing the Good Word of Marine Epigenetics</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-asi/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The University of Concepción recently offered an eye-opening course that dove deep into the realms of climate change, epigenetics, and marine biology. Titled “<a href="https://sr320.github.io/course-ASI-2024/">Epigenetic Phenomena Connecting Climate Change and Coastal Marine Species</a>,” this graduate-level course provided an intensive one-week journey into the fascinating interplay between our changing climate and the genetic mechanisms of marine invertebrates.</p>
<section id="unraveling-the-mysteries-of-marine-invertebrates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="unraveling-the-mysteries-of-marine-invertebrates">Unraveling the Mysteries of Marine Invertebrates</h3>
<p>The course, designed for students with a foundational understanding of genetics and climate science, began by establishing a strong base in epigenetics, climate change, and marine invertebrate physiology. The highlight was on the often-overlooked role of marine invertebrates in coastal ecosystems, emphasizing their ecological importance and responses to climate change at an epigenetic level.</p>
</section>
<section id="real-world-applications-and-functional-genomics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-world-applications-and-functional-genomics">Real-World Applications and Functional Genomics</h3>
<p>A significant focus of the course was the application of functional genomics. Students explored how climate change leads to alterations in epigenetic mechanisms of various coastal marine invertebrates through real-world examples. This approach helped in understanding the broader implications of these changes for marine ecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="comprehensive-course-objectives" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comprehensive-course-objectives">Comprehensive Course Objectives</h3>
<p>The course had three primary objectives:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Understanding Climate Change and Epigenetics</strong>: Gaining a comprehensive understanding of how climate change impacts marine invertebrates’ physiological processes through an epigenetic lens.</li>
<li><strong>Proficiency in Functional Genomics</strong>: Learning about genomic techniques and their applications in studying epigenetic changes in marine invertebrates due to climate stressors.</li>
<li><strong>Analyzing Scientific Research</strong>: Developing skills to critically analyze and evaluate scientific literature in marine invertebrate epigenetics and climate change.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="course-content-a-rich-blend-of-science-and-research" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="course-content-a-rich-blend-of-science-and-research">Course Content: A Rich Blend of Science and Research</h3>
<p>The course content was diverse and in-depth:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Basics of Epigenetics and Climate Change</strong>: Introduced the intersection of these fields and the concept of environmental epigenetics.</li>
<li><strong>Physiology of Marine Invertebrates</strong>: Covered essential aspects like feeding, digestion, reproduction, and stress response.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of Climate Change on Physiology</strong>: Explored the specific impacts of climate factors on marine invertebrates.</li>
<li><strong>Functional Genomics and Epigenetics</strong>: Delved into genomic methodologies and applications.</li>
<li><strong>Case Studies and Current Research</strong>: Involved critical examination of recent research studies, emphasizing practical understanding.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="methodology-interactive-and-engaging" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methodology-interactive-and-engaging">Methodology: Interactive and Engaging</h3>
<p>The course used a mix of lectures, discussions, and interactive data analysis. It emphasized hands-on learning, particularly in the afternoons, where students engaged in data analysis using R and bash, providing a practical edge to the theoretical knowledge gained.</p>
</section>
<section id="scholarly-contributions-a-rich-bibliography" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scholarly-contributions-a-rich-bibliography">Scholarly Contributions: A Rich Bibliography</h3>
<p>The course drew from a rich bibliography, featuring works by renowned researchers like Grace Crandall, Steven B. Roberts, and Cristian Gallardo-Escárate. These publications covered various aspects, from the proteomic responses of Pacific Oysters to the genomic assembly of the Blue Mussel, offering students a comprehensive view of current research in the field.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-a-step-forward-in-marine-biology-education" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-a-step-forward-in-marine-biology-education">Conclusion: A Step Forward in Marine Biology Education</h3>
<p>This course at the University of Concepción marked a significant step in educating the next generation of marine biologists, geneticists, and climate scientists. By bridging the gap between climate change and epigenetic phenomena in marine species, it not only enhanced understanding but also prepared students to contribute meaningfully to marine conservation efforts in the face of global climate challenges.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>course</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-asi/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/asi.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Insights from Pacific Oysters in a Heating Ocean</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-DM/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In a recent <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16980">commentary by Donal T. Manahan</a>, the magnified effects of marine heatwaves on the mortality of triploid Pacific oysters have been thrust into the spotlight, underscoring the urgent need for deeper understanding of marine life’s tolerance to heat stress. Manahan’s piece, a commentary <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16880">our recent work led by Matt George</a>, delves into the realm where climate change meets marine biology and aquaculture.</p>
<section id="the-rising-heat-and-its-victims" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-rising-heat-and-its-victims">The Rising Heat and Its Victims</h2>
<p>The context is alarming: with ocean temperatures breaking records and coastal heatwaves causing mass marine mortality, researchers like Manahan stress the importance of grasping how different organisms will survive in this changing environment. The Pacific Northwest, as noted by White et al.&nbsp;(2023), has witnessed temperatures soaring to nearly 50°C, resulting in the death of over a million bivalve mussels in a mere 100-meter stretch.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-pacific-oyster-at-the-heart-of-study" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-pacific-oyster-at-the-heart-of-study">The Pacific Oyster at the Heart of Study</h2>
<p>Matt’s study, referenced by Manahan, brings under scrutiny the Pacific oyster, Crassostrea gigas, an organism of commercial significance and genetic interest. Their work dissects the responses of diploid and triploid oysters to heatwaves, revealing that the mortality rate among triploid oysters was 2.5 times higher than their diploid counterparts.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-triploid-dilemma" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-triploid-dilemma">A Triploid Dilemma</h2>
<p>Triploid oysters, engineered for their superior growth and yield, seem to face greater peril under thermal stress. Manahan points out that these oysters show signs of metabolic depression, reduced ATP production, and a slump in essential biological processes like glucose metabolism and immunity responses. This finding poses serious implications for aquaculture, as triploids are widely cultivated for food production.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-challenge-of-predicting-phenotypes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge-of-predicting-phenotypes">The Challenge of Predicting Phenotypes</h2>
<p>Manahan underscores a crucial challenge in marine biology: the prediction of phenotypes from gene expression. The commentary reflects on how data from different biological levels may not always align, and he calls for a cautious interpretation of such analyses. Integrative approaches are necessary for a comprehensive understanding of how organisms function and respond to environmental stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="energy-allocation-and-the-cost-of-reproduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="energy-allocation-and-the-cost-of-reproduction">Energy Allocation and the Cost of Reproduction</h2>
<p>The commentary also touches upon the energetic cost of being a triploid organism. With triploids being functionally sterile, Manahan questions whether there’s an unaccounted metabolic cost involved in maintaining redundant biosynthetic pathways.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-path-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-path-forward">A Path Forward</h2>
<p>Manahan highlights the value of multi-year, trans-generational breeding programs and commends the collaborative efforts exemplified by the team behind our study. Such partnerships across universities, governments, and industry are vital for sustained research and for breeding marine species that can withstand the pressures of climate change.</p>
<p>In summary, Manahan’s commentary not only sheds light on the specific challenges faced by triploid Pacific oysters under heat stress but also casts a wider net on the complexities of studying marine life’s response to a warming world. The findings are a crucial piece of the puzzle in our pursuit of sustainable “Blue Food” production and the broader understanding of marine ecosystem resilience.</p>
<p>Citation: Manahan, D. T. (2023). Marine heatwaves impact mortality of triploid Pacific oysters. Global Change Biology. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16980" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16980</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>triploid</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-DM/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_ChatGPT_2023-11-04_14-59-20.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
