<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Cracking the Code of Pacific Cod</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Spencer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-cod2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What if the future of an entire fish population hinged on tiny changes in their DNA? In the frigid waters of the North Pacific, juvenile Pacific cod are facing an uncertain future as ocean temperatures rise. Our research is uncovering how these fish respond to warming waters—at the molecular level—and what that means for their survival.</p>
<p><strong>The Science Behind Survival</strong></p>
<p>At first glance, Pacific cod might seem like just another fish. But beneath the surface, their genetic makeup holds clues to how they adapt—or struggle—when faced with environmental stress. In our latest study, we’re diving deep into the connection between a cod’s genes and its ability to thrive in different temperatures.</p>
<p>We analyzed DNA and gene activity (transcriptomics) in young Pacific cod exposed to a range of temperatures, from icy 0°C to a heatwave-like 16°C. By combining this “genome-to-phenome” data—essentially linking genetic information to physical traits—we’re beginning to see which fish have the genetic tools to survive in a warming world.</p>
<p><strong>A Genetic Blueprint for Resilience</strong></p>
<p>One of the most intriguing findings comes from a process called <strong>Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS)</strong>, where we scan the entire genome for small genetic differences linked to key traits. One of the most revealing traits we studied is the <strong>hepatosomatic index (HSI)</strong>—a measure of how much energy a fish stores in its liver. Since fat storage is critical for surviving harsh winters, understanding which fish can accumulate liver lipids under stress is essential.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-17-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our data revealed <strong>specific genetic variants linked to liver size</strong>, some of which are connected to genes regulating appetite and metabolism. One gene in particular, likely involved in serotonin signaling (which affects hunger), seems to influence whether a juvenile cod stores enough fat when temperatures rise.</p>
<p><strong>Can Genes Predict Performance?</strong></p>
<p>Beyond genetics, we also examined how <strong>gene expression (RNA activity) relates to fish growth and condition</strong>. We identified a set of genes that are highly active in the strongest, most resilient fish under warm conditions. This genetic “signature” could help scientists predict which fish populations are best suited to handle climate shifts.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-18-11.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>By looking at <strong>composite performance indices (CPI)</strong>—which combine growth rate, body condition, and liver fat content—we found a distinct pattern: some fish are naturally equipped to thrive in warming seas, while others may struggle.</p>
<p><strong>A Look to the Past—and the Future</strong></p>
<p>To understand if these genetic traits have changed over time, we’re also analyzing historical samples from Pacific cod collected near Kodiak, Alaska, dating back to 2008. This will help us determine if recent marine heatwaves have already begun shaping the genetic makeup of young cod. If we find shifts in key genes over time, it could be a sign that natural selection is at work—favoring fish that can cope with temperature extremes.</p>
<p><strong>Next Steps: From Lab to Ocean Conservation</strong></p>
<p>Right now, we’re fine-tuning our analyses and comparing our results with other research teams, including NOAA scientists studying broader environmental factors. Our goal? To pinpoint the most critical genetic regions that influence temperature tolerance—and ultimately, to inform fisheries management strategies that support the resilience of Pacific cod populations.</p>
<p>As marine heatwaves become more frequent, understanding these genetic adaptations is more than just an academic pursuit. It’s about safeguarding a vital species in the face of climate change—ensuring that Pacific cod, and the people who depend on them, have a future in our warming oceans.</p>
<section id="products-this-period" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="products-this-period">Products this period:&nbsp;</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer at the NOAA NWFSC Manchester Research Station monthly meeting on December 11th, 2025, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Manchester-Presentation-Dec2024.pdf">link to slides</a>.&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer at the NOAA AFSC groundfish seminar on December 17th, 2024, <a href="https://bcove.video/3DxO7xy">link to recording</a>, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Groundfish%20Seminar%2C%202024.pdf">link to slides</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer during the poster session of the Alaska Marine Science Symposium on January 27th, 2025 in Anchorage, AK, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Spencer%2CLH_Poster-AMSS-2025-final.pdf">link to poster</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Laura Spenccer’s lab notebook updates on analyses, lab work, and products, <a href="https://laurahspencer.github.io/LabNotebook/">link to notebook</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://d.pr/f/Cq3nsF">Technical Report</a>.</p></li>
</ul>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-cod2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-15-38.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Harnessing Shellfish Environmental Memory for a Resilient Future</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-WSG/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Shellfish aquaculture is facing increasing challenges due to climate change, ocean acidification, and other environmental stressors. However, research is showing that environmental memory—the ability of organisms to retain and transmit adaptive responses to stress—may offer a promising strategy for improving resilience in aquaculture species.</p>
<p>At the 2025 Washington Sea Grant workshop, researchers and industry professionals came together to explore how environmental priming—exposing shellfish to controlled stress conditions—could be leveraged to enhance survival, growth, and performance.</p>
<section id="industry-engagement-and-perceptions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="industry-engagement-and-perceptions">Industry Engagement and Perceptions</h2>
<p>To better understand industry perspectives, a survey of shellfish growers was conducted to gauge their views on environmental priming as an adaptation strategy. The results were enlightening:<br>
• 78% of hatchery operators indicated they would consider implementing environmental priming, though most preferred to see supporting data first.<br>
• 70% of respondents said they would be willing to pay more for primed seed, provided evidence from test plots or research-supported literature was available.</p>
<p>This feedback underscores the importance of continued scientific research to validate environmental priming techniques and demonstrate their effectiveness in real-world aquaculture operations.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-environmental-priming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-environmental-priming">What is Environmental Priming?</h2>
<p>Environmental priming involves exposing shellfish to controlled stressors—such as temperature fluctuations, salinity changes, or immune challenges—to enhance their resilience later in life. Research has shown promising results across multiple species:</p>
<p>• Olympia oysters: Parental priming increased offspring survival in field conditions.<br>
• Pacific geoduck: Early-life priming led to improved growth rates later in life.<br>
• Manila clams: Offspring from primed parents exhibited better growth and survival rates.</p>
</section>
<section id="ongoing-research-and-applications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ongoing-research-and-applications">Ongoing Research and Applications</h2>
<p>Scientists are now working to optimize environmental priming strategies across different species. Ongoing research at institutions like NOAA’s Manchester Field Station and the Jamestown S’Klallam Hatchery is exploring how priming can enhance the performance of shellfish under various stress conditions.</p>
<p>For Pacific oysters, researchers are testing multiple priming approaches, including:<br>
✅ Immune challenges<br>
✅ Temperature stress<br>
✅ Salinity shifts<br>
✅ Combination stress exposures</p>
</section>
<section id="moving-forward-bridging-science-and-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="moving-forward-bridging-science-and-industry">Moving Forward: Bridging Science and Industry</h2>
<p>The insights from this research are critical for both hatchery operators and policymakers as they work toward sustainable shellfish aquaculture. With growing industry interest and evidence-based strategies, environmental priming may become a tool in ensuring the future resilience of shellfish populations.</p>
<p>Slidedecck: https://github.com/sr320/talk-WSG-2025</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>wsg</category>
  <category>talk</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-WSG/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_2025-WSG-Roberts_2025-02-10_07-20-44.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Coral Larvae and Thermal Stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-paper/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As climate change continues to drive rising ocean temperatures, coral reef ecosystems face an unprecedented crisis. Coral bleaching events, characterized by the breakdown of the mutualistic relationship between corals and their algal endosymbionts (Symbiodiniaceae), have become increasingly common, threatening the persistence of coral reefs worldwide. While much research has focused on adult corals, new studies are shedding light on how early life stages respond to thermal stress. <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3002875">A recent study by Huffmyer et al.&nbsp;(2024), published in&nbsp;<em>PLOS Biology</em></a>, provides novel insights into how coral larvae cope with increased temperatures by modifying nitrogen assimilation to stabilize symbiotic relationships and mitigate bleaching risk.</p>
<section id="the-crucial-role-of-coral-larvae-in-reef-resilience" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-crucial-role-of-coral-larvae-in-reef-resilience"><strong>The Crucial Role of Coral Larvae in Reef Resilience</strong></h3>
<p>Reef-building corals rely on their symbionts to produce energy-rich photosynthates that fuel metabolic processes. However, when subjected to thermal stress, this delicate exchange can be disrupted, leading to the expulsion of symbionts and loss of critical energy sources. Understanding how coral larvae respond to environmental stress is particularly important, as their ability to establish symbiosis and successfully settle onto reefs determines the future of coral populations.</p>
<p>The study focused on&nbsp;<em>Montipora capitata</em>, a dominant reef-building coral in Hawai‘i that vertically transmits Symbiodiniaceae to its offspring. The researchers subjected symbiotic larvae to a 2.5°C increase in temperature for three days and assessed metabolic responses, photosynthetic performance, and stable isotope-labeled metabolite exchange.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-nitrogen-assimilation-as-a-protective-mechanism" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-nitrogen-assimilation-as-a-protective-mechanism"><strong>Key Findings: Nitrogen Assimilation as a Protective Mechanism</strong></h3>
<p>Contrary to expectations, the study found that while larvae exhibited significant metabolic depression under high temperatures—indicated by a 19% reduction in respiration rates—they did not experience bleaching or a decline in survival and settlement rates. Photosynthetic activity remained stable, and the symbiont population density was maintained despite thermal stress.</p>
<p>A crucial discovery was that coral larvae increased ammonium assimilation and urea metabolism while sequestering nitrogen into dipeptides. This shift suggests that larvae actively modulate nitrogen cycling to maintain symbiotic balance. By limiting nitrogen availability to the symbionts, the coral hosts may be promoting sustained photosynthate translocation, ensuring that energy supply remains uninterrupted under heat stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="metabolic-trade-offs-and-implications-for-coral-survival" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="metabolic-trade-offs-and-implications-for-coral-survival"><strong>Metabolic Trade-offs and Implications for Coral Survival</strong></h3>
<p>While glucose translocation from symbiont to host was maintained, the study revealed reduced metabolism of glucose through central carbon pathways such as glycolysis. This metabolic shift implies a trade-off: larvae prioritize nitrogen assimilation over carbohydrate breakdown, potentially conserving energy for essential physiological functions.</p>
<p>The authors propose that nitrogen limitation imposed on Symbiodiniaceae encourages continued carbon transfer to the host, preventing the symbionts from hoarding fixed carbon, which could otherwise disrupt the mutualistic relationship. This mechanism highlights a potential resilience strategy in coral early life stages that may influence reef recovery following bleaching events.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions-and-conservation-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions-and-conservation-implications"><strong>Future Directions and Conservation Implications</strong></h3>
<p>Understanding the physiological mechanisms that allow coral larvae to withstand heat stress has significant implications for reef conservation and restoration efforts. If coral larvae can naturally modulate nitrogen metabolism to maintain symbiosis, selective breeding or assisted evolution approaches may enhance these traits in vulnerable species.</p>
<p>Additionally, further research should investigate whether similar nitrogen assimilation strategies are present in adult corals or if this is a life-stage-specific adaptation. Given the increasing frequency of marine heatwaves, identifying and promoting heat-resilient traits in corals could be a crucial component of future conservation strategies.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>Huffmyer et al.&nbsp;(2024) provide compelling evidence that coral larvae can mitigate thermal stress through nitrogen assimilation, maintaining stable symbiosis even under elevated temperatures. By uncovering this metabolic adaptation, the study advances our understanding of coral resilience mechanisms and underscores the importance of protecting early life stages in reef conservation efforts. As climate change accelerates, these insights may inform new strategies to support coral reef survival in a warming world.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>paper</category>
  <category>coral</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-paper/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Coral_larvae_increase_nitrogen_assimilation_to_stabilize_algal_symbiosis_and_combat_bleaching_under_increased_temperature__PLO_2025-02-08_12-36-36.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Turning the tide</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-boundless/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Chris is featured on UW’s “Be Boundless” site. Read full article <a href="https://www.washington.edu/boundless/turning-the-tide-marine-biology/">here</a>. Below is a short snippet of the feature along with an amazing video!</strong></p>
<p>On a windy June afternoon, Chris Mantegna, ’21, encourages a half-dozen undergraduates to flip over barnacle-studded rocks and sift through seaweed. Equipped with clipboards to record their findings, they’re creating a snapshot of the organisms in the island’s intertidal zone — from orange sea cucumbers to the camouflaged armored mollusks called chitons.</p>
<p>Mantegna, a third-year graduate student in aquatic and fishery sciences, has spent the past three summers in Washington’s San Juan Islands, mentoring undergrads here on Yellow Island — a pristine 11-acre nature preserve owned by the Nature Conservancy. She created this eight-week program for students to get their hands dirty in the field and learn cutting-edge lab techniques at the UW Friday Harbor Laboratories — where she had a transformational research experience herself as a Husky undergrad.</p>
<p>This mentorship program reflects Mantegna’s passion both for advancing the science and for making it more inclusive and accessible to others. Her face lights up when she spots a small chiton (her favorite) clinging to the bottom of a rock, and she invites others to feel the mollusk’s tough plated back. Even Mantegna’s doctoral work — examining the genetic response of shellfish to contaminants in Puget Sound waterways — has a focus on community outreach and environmental literacy.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VLLocGcP9S8?si=UzEadZGT7XryVpEV" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Mantegna says we have a better chance at fighting climate change when everyone — scientists and community members — feels connected to their environment and each other. “I can tell you that the ocean is dying or that we have too much acidification,” says Mantegna, a U.S. Navy veteran who is the first in her family to graduate from college. “But it doesn’t matter if you’ve never had the chance to feel the joy that comes from this place.”</p>
<p>Finish feature <a href="https://www.washington.edu/boundless/turning-the-tide-marine-biology/">here</a>.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>dna</category>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-boundless/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-07_12-56-13.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring Pacific Cod Resilience in a Warming Ocean</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Spencer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/posts/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In our latest update on the Pacific cod juvenile temperature study, we've gained deeper insights into how these remarkable fish respond to different temperatures. This research is part of a larger effort to understand the resilience of marine species in changing environments.</p>
<p><strong>Genetic Insights Reveal Population Origins</strong></p>
<p>We began with genetic analyses, using data from thousands of genetic markers to determine the origin of our experimental fish. All our test fish were linked to the spawning grounds in the western Gulf of Alaska (wGOA) and the Eastern Bering Sea (EBS). This finding allows us to focus on the thermal resilience of cod from this particular region, which is vital as they face shifts in temperature in their natural habitats.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-00-51.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Temperature's Role in Energy and Lipid Storage</strong></p>
<p>Our collaborator Louise Copement analyzed liver lipids in these juvenile cod, focusing on triglycerides and other key lipid types that are crucial for overwinter survival. The results showed a clear trend: energy storage, primarily in the form of triglycerides, peaked at 9°C, then dropped sharply at higher temperatures, especially at 16°C. This suggests that extreme warmth could deplete essential energy reserves, reducing the fish's survival prospects in the cold winter months.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-01-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Optimal Growth Temperatures and Physiological Responses</strong></p>
<p>We also observed that juvenile cod exhibit optimal growth at approximately 12.3°C, slightly higher than previous findings. With higher temperatures, growth rates plateau or decline, mirroring the energy storage patterns. Interestingly, the gene expression data from liver tissues revealed significant temperature-driven shifts, especially in energy production, lipid metabolism, and immune response genes. This molecular data adds a new layer to our understanding of temperature tolerance.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-01-22.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Integrated Data: A Pathway to Genomic Resilience Markers</strong></p>
<p>Combining growth, lipid, and gene expression data, we've started identifying genes that correlate with enhanced resilience at specific temperatures. This approach could spotlight genetic markers for thermal resilience, offering clues about cod populations best suited to future ocean conditions.</p>
<p>In summary, this research underscores the delicate balance juvenile Pacific cod must maintain in their energy reserves and growth under variable temperatures. These findings will help guide conservation and management efforts as we work to protect Pacific cod populations in a warming world.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/posts/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_13-57-57.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep dive into the handbook</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-handbook/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A unique perspective. You will never guess what they reveal!</p>
<section id="audio" class="level1">
<h1>Audio</h1>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/handbook.wav"></video></div>
</section>
<section id="transcript" class="level1">
<h1>Transcript</h1>
<p>Welcome to The Deep Dive, where we dig into the nitty gritty of fascinating topics.</p>
<p>Today, we’re taking a deep dive into the Roberts Lab at the University of Washington, and we’re doing that through the lens of their handbook.</p>
<p>It’s more than just a rule book, though, isn’t it?</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p>It’s like a window into their whole approach to science.</p>
<p>Everything from, like, groundbreaking research to how they actually build their research culture.</p>
<p>And they’re known for being incredibly transparent, which this handbook really embodies.</p>
<p>Yeah, it’s refreshing.</p>
<p>And speaking of refreshing, I have to ask you about this freezer alarm situation.</p>
<p>Oh, yes.</p>
<p>So they have, like, a dedicated alarm for their ultra-low temperature freezers, right?</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>But there’s this 15-minute delay before anyone actually gets notified if it goes off.</p>
<p>Can you imagine?</p>
<p>It’s like a slow-motion heart attack for a researcher.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>All those precious samples.</p>
<p>I’d be a wreck.</p>
<p>It really highlights the fragility of these biological materials they’re working with.</p>
<p>RNA, proteins, these things have to be stored at, like, negative 80 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Wow.</p>
<p>Even a short power outage could be disastrous.</p>
<p>So is that delay, like, a safety net to give the system a chance to recover?</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>It’s a calculated risk.</p>
<p>They’re trying to balance preventing false alarms while also, you know, protecting those invaluable research materials.</p>
<p>Makes sense.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And it seems like that emphasis on meticulousness, on minimizing risk, it really comes through in the whole handbook, especially when they talk about lab safety and chemicals.</p>
<p>It’s serious business.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>Like with Arnazole RT, they’re very clear about it being corrosive, potentially harmful if you inhale it, even disposing of it.</p>
<p>It’s a whole multi-step process.</p>
<p>Well, they’re dealing with some pretty potent stuff.</p>
<p>It underscores their dedication to, you know, not just scientific rigor, but the actual well-being of their researchers.</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>It’s like they’re creating an environment where cutting-edge science can happen, but it can happen safely.</p>
<p>Safety first.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And that meticulousness, that doing things by the book, it goes beyond just lab safety, you know.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>It’s woven into their whole research philosophy, which makes you wonder, if they’re this careful with safety, how does that translate to, say, data management or collaboration?</p>
<p>Good question.</p>
<p>And as luck would have it, that’s exactly what we’re going to be digging into in the rest of this deep dive.</p>
<p>You know, it’s funny you should mention that because the next thing that really struck me about this handbook was their code of conduct.</p>
<p>Oh, interesting.</p>
<p>How so?</p>
<p>Well, for one, it’s incredibly detailed, even for like their diversity, equity, and inclusion meetings.</p>
<p>You don’t always see that level of, I don’t know, formality in a lab handbook.</p>
<p>What kinds of things are we talking about here?</p>
<p>They have these great phrases like, “Elevate impact above intent,” and, “Expect and accept non-closure.”</p>
<p>Like, really specific guidelines.</p>
<p>Huh.</p>
<p>It sounds like they’re trying to foster a very specific kind of research environment.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>One where people feel comfortable admitting they don’t know everything, which, let’s be honest, is most of the time in research, right?</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p>Science is all about embracing uncertainty.</p>
<p>But it takes a certain culture to really allow for that.</p>
<p>Totally.</p>
<p>And it seems like they’re putting a lot of emphasis on making sure everyone feels heard and respected, especially in those DEI meetings.</p>
<p>Well, and that makes sense, right?</p>
<p>If you want to have those tough conversations about diversity and inclusion, you need to create a space where people feel safe to speak their minds.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>No, you’re right.</p>
<p>It all ties together.</p>
<p>And then there’s this whole thing about mentorship.</p>
<p>They really encourage lab members to have multiple mentors, not just one.</p>
<p>That’s interesting.</p>
<p>Most labs I’ve seen, it’s pretty standard to have one primary mentor.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>So I thought that was really unique.</p>
<p>It kind of speaks to this idea of providing a well-rounded experience, right?</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>Different mentors bring different perspectives, different areas of expertise.</p>
<p>It can really enrich a researcher’s training.</p>
<p>Okay, so we’ve got meticulous safety protocols, a very deliberate approach to their lab culture.</p>
<p>But we also know they’re dealing with a massive amount of data.</p>
<p>Like their handbook mentions Nightingale for sequencing this whole network attached storage system called Gannett.</p>
<p>Don’t forget the supercomputer.</p>
<p>MOCs, was it?</p>
<p>Oh, right.</p>
<p>MOCs.</p>
<p>I mean, it’s a lot.</p>
<p>It really makes you wonder how they manage it all.</p>
<p>It’s a data tsunami.</p>
<p>How do they keep from drowning?</p>
<p>Well, for one thing, they’re incredibly organized.</p>
<p>Like religiously organized.</p>
<p>Give me the details.</p>
<p>Think detailed metadata for every single experiment, strict folder structures on their network.</p>
<p>They even have readme files.</p>
<p>Readme files for every folder, seriously.</p>
<p>Seriously.</p>
<p>And it’s all part of this commitment to open science.</p>
<p>They want their research to be accessible, transparent.</p>
<p>So anyone could theoretically go in and understand their data, their methods.</p>
<p>That’s the idea.</p>
<p>It’s about breaking down those silos, you know, fostering collaboration, avoiding unnecessary redundancy, ultimately speeding up discoveries.</p>
<p>It’s kind of inspiring, actually.</p>
<p>It’s like they’re playing the long game, advancing science as a whole, not just their own work.</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>But okay, even with perfect organization, all that data analysis, it’s got to be intense.</p>
<p>They mentioned Jupiter notebooks in the handbook.</p>
<p>Right, and mocks the supercomputer.</p>
<p>And they even talk about using like the command line.</p>
<p>Hard course, so they’re not messing around.</p>
<p>Well, they’re equipping their researchers with a seriously powerful toolkit.</p>
<p>But it goes beyond just the tech.</p>
<p>They even recommend this book, Getting Things Done.</p>
<p>Time management.</p>
<p>Time management.</p>
<p>It’s all about efficiency.</p>
<p>They don’t just give them the tools.</p>
<p>They give them the training, the resources to actually use them well.</p>
<p>It’s like they’ve thought of everything.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And it doesn’t stop there.</p>
<p>They have a whole section on conferences, funding opportunities, even like travel grants.</p>
<p>They want their researchers to be well-rounded, right?</p>
<p>Not just stuck in the lab, but out there presenting, collaborating, getting their work funded.</p>
<p>It’s impressive, I have to say.</p>
<p>Looking at the Roberts Lab this way, through their handbook, you really get a sense of the thoughtfulness, the care that goes into building a successful research environment.</p>
<p>It’s not just about, you know, the results, the discoveries.</p>
<p>It’s the people, the culture.</p>
<p>And that commitment to moving science forward in a way that’s open and collaborative, it’s really something.</p>
<p>Makes you wonder what they’ll accomplish, what amazing discoveries are on the horizon for them.</p>
<p>It does, doesn’t it?</p>
<p>And that’s something to ponder as we wrap up this deep dive into the world of the Roberts Lab.</p>
<p>Until next time, keep exploring, keep questioning, and keep diving deep.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>handbook</category>
  <category>audio</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-handbook/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Roberts_Lab_Handbook_2024-09-14_13-23-52.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery-based Environmental Conditioning Activities</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>During this past year a series of hatchery-based environmental conditioning activities (referred to as hardening) were completed with oysters out-planted onto three farms to evaluate performance. Additionally, climate resiliency was assessed in hardened oysters under controlled conditions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_overview.png_2024-08-29_13-35-45.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Experimental Overview</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="farm-outplanting" class="level1">
<h1>Farm Outplanting</h1>
<p>Early in the season, a cohort of oysters were subject to (a) daily thermal hardening for approximately two weeks prior to out planting in hanging bags on a farm in Sequim Bay, alongside a control group. These oyster will be assessed in early Autumn 2024. Later in the season oysters were subjected to a more diverse series of hardening conditions with oyster split between two commercial farms, one located in Willapa Bay and a second in the San Juan Islands. The combination of age classes and hardening conditions were as follows: b) small seed / daily thermal hardening, c) adult / daily thermal hardening, d) small seed / weekly thermal hardening, e1) large seed / weekly thermal hardening, e2) large seed / weekly zero salinity hardening. These hardening activities spanned from several weeks to months. For all hardening efforts controls were also outplanted. Oysters out planted in Willapa Bay will be assessed for survival and growth in early September 2024. Oysters out planted in the San Juan Islands have be subject to more routine monitoring. At this site we are currently observing a trend where oysters subjected to the daily hardening regime are surviving better than controls.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-37-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Wescott Bay Outplanting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-1" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 1</h1>
<p>To assess the effectiveness of hardening within a hatchery setting, four ages classes of oysters were examined: adults (40-100mm), juveniles (20-55mm), seed (6-15mm), and spat ()1-6mm). In order to assess hardening potential and environmental memory, oysters were subject to an initial chronic temperature stress, then subjected to a secondary stress to see if the response to secondary stress was impacted by initial exposure. During the chronic temperature stress period, oysters from each age class were exposed to a daily 25ºC temperature spike. This repeated for 14 days starting on October 1. Control oysters from each cohort were maintained at an ambient temperature of approximately 17ºC during the same time period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-38-28.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Hardening and acute stress temperature timeline</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Adult oysters in stress conditions were also subject to mechanical stress at day 1, 7, and 48, which was induced by 15 minutes. At day 147 (7 weeks after initial chronic stress), both stressed and non-stressed adult, juvenile, spat, and seed were subjected to a secondary stress of 30 minutes in 32ºC. Gill tissue was sampled immediately after and placed into RNAlater. Spat and seed that were too small to dissect gill tissue were sampled whole with all tissue used in gene expression assays. To date we have analyzed gene expression data from seed and spat. There was no mortality during this trial. Hardening increased growth (compared to controls) in spat. Further there was a reduced transcriptional response in spat. These data suggest temperature hardening of spat could result in a resiliency to later temperature stress whereby energy resources could favor growth.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-39-30.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Growth Performance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Gene expression profiles (spat)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-54.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic physiology explanation when hardened spat are exposed to acute temperature stress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-2" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 2</h1>
<p>In a second experimental regime, juvenile oysters were subjected to four hardening conditions 1) high temperature (35°C), 2) high temperature and freshwater, 3) freshwater, and 4) poly I:C immersion. These were exposures that occurred every other day for about 3 weeks. Approximately 1 month after hardening, oysters were brought to the lab and subjected to metabolic assessment using resazurin at 18°C and 42°C. Resazurin is a dye that is commonly used in cell viability, and it works by changing color as an organism consumes oxygen. Survival was assessed during the resazurin assay and 24 hours later. To date, our analysis suggests metabolic activity of the 42°C oysters was higher in the control oysters than previously hardened oysters. In the near future we will assess the relationship of metabolic activity and survival however it appears higher metabolic rate directly correlates with mortality. Taken together these sets of controlled experiments suggest hardening does have an impact on resiliency, though dependent on age, hardening duration, and subsequent environmental conditions.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_logo-resazuring_2024-08-29_13-50-31.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Resazurin assay (4 hour / 2 temperatures) on hardened oysters"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-usda-report/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-10-49.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Assessing Oyster Viability Under Environmental Stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lsamp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As part of our ongoing commitment to fostering innovative research, this summer was particularly thrilling due to the strides made in the <a href="https://www.washington.edu/omad/louis-stokes-alliance-for-minority-participation/">LSAMP Scientist Program</a>. One of our standout projects, led by an ambitious student researcher, Colby Elvrum, brought new insights into the resilience of oysters against environmental stressors. Get a <a href="https://genefish.wordpress.com/author/colbyelvrum/">first hand account of all of Colby’s science from his notebook!</a></p>
<section id="the-genesis-of-the-study" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-genesis-of-the-study">The Genesis of the Study</h3>
<p>Oysters, a crucial component of aquatic ecosystems, serve as indicators of environmental health and sustainability. Recognizing their role and the urgent need to understand how environmental changes affect these organisms, we embarked on a project to utilize a novel application of the resazurin assay, traditionally a cell viability test in microbiology. This assay, which exploits the color-changing properties of the resazurin dye in response to oxygen consumption, was adapted to measure the metabolic activity of oysters under stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-we-aimed-to-discover" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-aimed-to-discover">What We Aimed to Discover</h3>
<p>Our research was driven by two pivotal questions: Can resazurin effectively measure metabolism in oysters, and does prior exposure to stress (stress hardening) alter their metabolic response to subsequent stressors? Through meticulously designed experiments, Colby led the charge in optimizing the assay conditions, ensuring the reliability and accuracy of our measurements.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-33-23.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Colby presenting his research at the Summer Research Symposium</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-and-methodological-innovations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-and-methodological-innovations">Key Findings and Methodological Innovations</h3>
<p>Our findings were enlightening. We observed that resazurin is not only a viable marker for oyster metabolism but also that it clearly illustrates the metabolic shifts caused by environmental stressors such as temperature fluctuations. Notably, oysters exposed to elevated temperatures displayed a rapid increase in metabolic rate, which was a precursor to subsequent mortality. This initial surge and later plateau in metabolism provided critical clues about the stress thresholds of these organisms.</p>
<p>Moreover, the study also highlighted how oysters previously conditioned to withstand stress exhibited altered survival rates under extreme temperatures, suggesting a potential sensitization rather than hardening effect. These insights are crucial for understanding how oysters might respond to the escalating challenges of climate change.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h3>
<p>The implications of this research extend beyond the academic sphere. They beckon a reevaluation of how we manage and conserve our aquatic resources in the face of rapid environmental changes. The potential to scale up this assay and automate aspects of the procedure could revolutionize aquaculture, and provide a more dynamic understanding of environmental impacts on marine life.</p>
</section>
<section id="gratitude-and-acknowledgments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gratitude-and-acknowledgments">Gratitude and Acknowledgments</h3>
<p>This research was made possible through the support of the National Science Foundation. We are immensely proud of Colby and all associated researchers for their dedication and hard work.</p>
<p><strong>Poster</strong> (<a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Colby_Poster_LSAMP.pdf">download hi-res pdf</a>)</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-40-33.png" class="img-fluid"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lsamp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-42-08.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Intertidal Innovators</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-intertidal/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_1373.png_2024-08-19_12-59-21.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 16, participants in the Intertidal Innovators program presented their work to the community. The program, which was a collaboration sponsored by the UW Earthlab program, provided students with the opportunity to learn about marine science and conservation through art.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-19_13-09-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Quote
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This program has lasted for 10 days, but during those days we have learned and worked very hard to give you this project. And we are proud to say that there are a bunch of hard working members in our program that have learned new skills and have gained knowledge in this program So in this journey, you will learn a lot about our work and marine life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>At the community showcase, students guide small groups around the intertidal, sharing their art with tablets and speakers. It was a great experience that showcased videos, poems, live demonostrations, and stories. Anyone can checkout their guided tour at Golden Garden Park via the echoes app - <a href="https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC" class="uri">https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC</a></p>
<p>Below is a video that takes you behind the scenes on the 10-day experience students participated in.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PsVyUPzu2_A" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-intertidal/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_The_Golden_Hour_-_a_geolocated_audio_walk_by_Intertidal_Innovators_on_ECHOES_2024-08-19_12-50-25.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ostras en Chile</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-ostras/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_6806.jpg_19801320_pixels_2024-08-14_11-49-59.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 6, 2024, approximately sixty participants gathered at the Professor Alamiro Robledo Auditorium of the Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences at the University of Concepción. They were there to delve into the promising sector of oyster aquaculture in Chile during the seminar titled “Oysters in Chile: Opportunities and Challenges for Aquaculture Diversification.” This event was meticulously organized by the Interdisciplinary Center for Aquaculture Research (INCAR).</p>
<p>The seminar showcased six presentations from both national and international experts, followed by a panel discussion. The diverse audience included academia, public and private sector representatives, producers, aquaculturists, industry leaders, professionals, and both secondary and postgraduate students. The gathering aimed to foster a comprehensive dialogue on the development of oyster aquaculture in the country.</p>
<p>Manira Matamala, the regional director of the Undersecretary of Fisheries and Aquaculture (Subpesca) for Valparaíso, O’Higgins, and Maule, commended INCAR’s initiative. She highlighted the seminar’s focus on enhancing the genetic and genomic understanding of oysters, which is vital for promoting sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
<p>Among the speakers, Justo García, an aquaculturist and founder of “Cultivos Cholche,” shared insights from his hands-on experience in various stages of oyster production, emphasizing the importance of adding value to the aquaculture processes.</p>
<p>Key Presentations Highlighted at the Seminar:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Steven Roberts from the University of Washington offered an international perspective with his presentation on the “<a href="https://github.com/sr320/talk-ostras-2024">Olympia Oyster (Ostrea lurida) Restoration in the United States</a>,” focusing on physiological and genomic insights.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardo-Escárate, deputy director of Incar, discussed the genome of the Chilean oyster (Ostrea chilensis) as a critical tool for the restoration and conservation of natural oyster banks.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Francisco Cárcamo shared experiences on co-cultivating Japanese oysters and algae both in field and laboratory settings, presenting an alternative approach for Environmental Performance Enhancement (APE). Justo García recounted his local experiences in small-scale aquaculture for both Chilean and Japanese oysters.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Rodrigo Rojas from the Catholic University of the North introduced advances from a technological program aimed at the sustainable development of Japanese oyster cultivation.</p></li>
<li><p>Meyling Tang, vice president of the Cocinamar Foundation, proposed strategies to reinvigorate oyster consumption in Chile with her presentation titled “Oysters Everywhere: Ideas to Reactivate Oyster Consumption in Chile.”</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Renato Quiñones, the director of Incar, emphasized the seminar’s role in bringing together experts from varied fields to create a multidimensional space for all stakeholders involved in oyster cultivation. This interaction is crucial for transforming scientific knowledge into a community and national heritage.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The event concluded with a panel discussion moderated by Dr.&nbsp;Doris Soto, principal investigator at Incar, where experts discussed the multifaceted opportunities and challenges facing aquaculture diversification in Chile.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-36-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This seminar not only highlighted the collaborative efforts required to advance oyster aquaculture but also showcased the commitment of INCAR to foster a sustainable and innovative aquaculture industry in Chile.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>presentation</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-ostras/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-33-39.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring How Environmental Conditions Impact Atlantic Salmon’s Defense Against Sea Lice</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38876411/">In our latest study, we delved into the complex interplay between environmental factors and the immune responses of Atlantic salmon (<em>Salmo salar</em>) during infestations by sea lice (<em>Caligus rogercresseyi</em>).</a> This research is particularly significant for both aquaculture and the management of natural marine ecosystems.</p>
<section id="our-research-approach" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-research-approach">Our Research Approach</h4>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardos’ team set up an experimental infestation of Atlantic salmon with sea lice, controlling for variations in temperature and salinity: specifically, conditions were set at 8°C and 16°C, and 32 and 26 practical salinity units (PSU). We then collected tissues from these fish to conduct analyses via reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) and whole transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq).</p>
</section>
<section id="key-discoveries" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-discoveries">Key Discoveries</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Impact of Environment on Parasitic Load</strong>: We observed that the parasitic load varied significantly with environmental conditions, noting the lowest abundance of lice in salmon kept at cooler and less saline conditions (8°C/26PSU).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Transcriptional Changes and Splicing Events</strong>: Environmental conditions were found to influence the salmon’s transcriptome profiles substantially. Notably, there was an increase in alternative splicing events in fish under low temperature and salinity, suggesting that environmental stress can induce genomic adaptations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Methylation Patterns</strong>: We also noted significant changes in methylation levels in response to temperature variations, with more pronounced differential methylation regions (DMRs) at the higher temperature of 16°C. These methylation changes correlated with the expression of alternatively spliced transcripts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Biological Pathways</strong>: Our analyses revealed significant correlations between methylation, transcript expression, and key biological pathways such as Ferroptosis and TLR signaling pathways, which are crucial for immune response and cellular integrity.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="implications-of-our-findings" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-of-our-findings">Implications of Our Findings</h4>
<p>This research highlights the nuanced ways in which environmental conditions can influence the genomic and epigenomic landscapes of marine organisms. For the aquaculture industry, understanding these dynamics is essential for developing effective management strategies to combat sea lice infestations, which are a major challenge for the sustainability and economic success of salmon farming.</p>
<p>Moreover, the link between environmental conditions, alternative splicing, and methylation opens new research avenues into the genetic mechanisms of resilience and adaptability in marine organisms. This knowledge advances our understanding of how species adapt to their changing environments, which is critical for preserving and enhancing the health of our global marine resources.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>salmon</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Environmental_influence_on_the_Atlantic_salmon_transcriptome_and_methylome_during_sea_lice_infestations_-_ScienceDirect_2024-08-14_12-12-07.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cmplexities of Gene Expression</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-altsplice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a recent meeting focused on gene expression analysis, we delved into the intricacies of examining expression at the exon level, a crucial but complex aspect of understanding gene function and regulation. The discussion provided deep insights into both the challenges and potential breakthroughs in the field of genomics. Here’s a detailed recap of the key points and future directions highlighted during the conversation.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="https://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/GMT20240523-195855_Recording.m4a"></video></div>
<section id="emphasis-on-gene-expression-analysis" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="emphasis-on-gene-expression-analysis">Emphasis on Gene Expression Analysis</h4>
<p>Gene expression analysis remains a cornerstone of genomic studies, serving as a gateway to understanding the roles of genes in various biological processes and disease states. The meeting opened with a reaffirmation of the importance of mastering the techniques and tools that allow for such analysis, emphasizing that comprehensive understanding is necessary to advance research.</p>
</section>
<section id="workflow-and-tools" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workflow-and-tools">Workflow and Tools</h4>
<p>A significant portion of the discussion revolved around the workflow used in the analysis. The researchers outlined their use of HiSat for alignment—a choice reflecting HiSat’s efficiency in handling high-throughput RNA-seq data. StringTie was then introduced as the tool for identifying transcript units, highlighting its capability to assemble transcripts effectively. The differential expression analysis was conducted using DC2, a tool favored for its robust statistical methods in handling variance among biological replicates.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenges-in-interpretation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-in-interpretation">Challenges in Interpretation</h4>
<p>One of the central themes of the meeting was the challenge of interpreting results where genes do not show differential expression overall but do exhibit variations at the exon level. This scenario often leads to questions about alternative splicing or differential exon usage, which can have significant implications for gene function.</p>
<p>The group discussed several hypothetical situations:<br>
- <strong>Alternative Splicing</strong>: If only certain exons within a gene are differentially expressed, this might suggest alternative splicing, a process where the same gene can lead to different protein variants.<br>
- <strong>Alternative Start Sites</strong>: Differentially expressed exons at the gene’s boundaries might indicate alternative transcription start sites, affecting how transcription is initiated.</p>
</section>
<section id="biological-implications-and-interpretation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biological-implications-and-interpretation">Biological Implications and Interpretation</h4>
<p>The biological implications of these findings are profound, potentially impacting everything from gene regulation to the development of therapeutic strategies. For example, alternative splicing can result in proteins with differing, sometimes antagonistic functions. Understanding these nuances is essential for the development of targeted therapies.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-role-of-visual-aids" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-visual-aids">The Role of Visual Aids</h4>
<p>A noteworthy suggestion from the meeting was the use of visual aids to better explain complex data and analysis. Presentations with graphical representations of data can facilitate a clearer understanding, aiding in the interpretation of intricate patterns of gene expression that might otherwise be overlooked in raw numerical data.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions">Future Directions</h4>
<p>Looking to the future, the participants agreed on the need for more refined tools and methodologies to enhance the accuracy and granularity of exon-level expression analysis. They highlighted the potential for developing new computational tools that can integrate more complex layers of data, such as epigenetic modifications and non-coding RNA interactions, which could provide a more comprehensive view of gene regulation.</p>
<p>The meeting concluded with a sense of optimism about the path forward, acknowledging that while challenges remain, the ongoing advancements in technology and methodology will continue to illuminate the complexities of the genome.</p>
<p>This deep dive into exon-level analysis not only underscores the complexity inherent in genetic studies but also highlights the meticulous detail and sophisticated understanding required to truly grasp the implications of gene expression data. As researchers continue to unravel these complexities, each discussion and discovery adds a valuable piece to the puzzle of life sciences.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-altsplice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/enrich.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unraveling the Intricacies of Enrichment Analysis</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-enrich/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In our most recent lab meeting, we delved into the fascinating world of enrichment analysis. This statistical method is a cornerstone of our research, helping us identify significantly over-represented subsets of proteins or genes within our data.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/GMT20240509-195925_Recording_gallery_1920x1080.mp4"></video></div>
<section id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis">The Power of Enrichment Analysis</h2>
<p>Enrichment analysis allows us to compare a small subset of genes or proteins to a larger set, identifying overrepresentation. This can provide valuable insights into the biological processes that are most relevant to our research.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-deep-dive-into-david" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-deep-dive-into-david">A Deep Dive into David</h2>
<p>One of the tools we use for enrichment analysis is David. During the meeting, we explored how to upload gene lists and backgrounds into David, and how to interpret the results it provides. This tool is invaluable in helping us understand the complex relationships and patterns within our data.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-reference-list-debate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-reference-list-debate">The Reference List Debate</h2>
<p>An interesting discussion arose around what to use as a reference list in enrichment analysis. Should it be all the genes detected in the data set, or all genes in a reference genome? This question sparked a lively debate, highlighting the complexities and nuances of enrichment analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo">Visualizing Gene Ontology with Revigo</h2>
<p>To help us visualize gene ontology, we use a tool called Revigo. This tool provides a visual representation of the relationships between genes, making it easier to understand the complex data we work with.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-lighter-moment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-lighter-moment">A Lighter Moment</h2>
<p>Amidst the serious scientific discussions, we also had a lighter moment when a team member shared a story about narrowly avoiding a parking ticket. It’s moments like these that remind us of the importance of camaraderie and humor in the lab.</p>
<hr>
<p>Our lab meetings are a crucial part of our research process, providing a space for us to discuss, debate, and learn together. Stay tuned for more insights from our lab meetings in future posts!</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-enrich/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/enrich.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery Field Day at Point Whitney</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On May 6, 2024, Dr.&nbsp;Ariana Huffmyer, an NSF Ocean Sciences Postdoctoral Fellow from the University of Rhode Island and University of Washington, shared insights from a field day at Point Whitney. This comprehensive post revealed the detailed process of managing and monitoring oyster growth and stress testing, providing a clear framework for hatchery management.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Link to Full Notebook Post
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/" class="uri">https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Overview of Field Day Activities</strong> The objective was to monitor the health and stress responses of oyster cohorts at the hatchery. Key activities included calibrating monitoring equipment, feeding the oysters, and assessing the impacts of temperature and freshwater stress.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Monitoring Equipment Calibration:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer set up and calibrated an Orion Star A325 probe to measure pH, temperature, and conductivity. By using buffers of varying pH and a conductivity solution, she ensured accurate measurements. The pH was measured on the NBS scale, considered sufficient since ocean acidification experiments weren’t being conducted.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Feeding Protocol:</strong> The oysters were pulse-fed, where approximately 1/3 of a 5-gallon bucket was distributed among the tanks. This ensured that the animals received sufficient nutrition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fluorometry and Physiochemical Measurements:</strong> Fluorometry measurements were conducted before and after feeding, providing data on oyster metabolic activity. Additionally, pH, temperature, and conductivity were measured across different tanks, offering valuable weekly insights into water quality.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stress Testing Regimen:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer conducted a 30-minute stress test for specific oyster cohorts using freshwater and elevated temperature exposures. Animals were subjected to 25°C temperature and freshwater immersion, replicating environmental stressors they might face. Trays were labeled and organized by stressor type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Growth Characterization:</strong> Size measurements were taken using a waterproof digital caliper. Cohorts were categorized based on their respective stressors, creating a comprehensive understanding of their growth patterns.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ploidy Testing Preparations:</strong> A selection of oysters from different cohorts was collected for ploidy testing to distinguish between diploid and triploid oysters. They were stored in mesh bags, and the testing results would provide critical information for future breeding programs.</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Hatchery_field_day_at_Point_Whitney_May_6_2024__Ariana_S_Huffmyer__NSF_Ocean_Sciences_Postdoctoral_Fellow_University_of_Rhod_2024-05-11_14-51-46.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>heath-tray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Takeaways for Hatchery Science</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer’s systematic approach highlights the significance of precise monitoring and stress testing in hatchery science. Understanding oyster resilience to environmental stressors is crucial for aquaculture sustainability. Her work at Point Whitney offers a detailed protocol that could be replicated or adapted by other researchers to monitor and improve hatchery operations.</p>
<p>The future of hatchery management will depend heavily on such frameworks, where real-time data collection and analysis enable researchers to respond promptly to environmental changes.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/bucket.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hardening in oysters drives increased growth</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-oyster_stage/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the meticulously orchestrated world of marine science, a groundbreaking experiment has unfolded in the hands of <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io">Eric Essington</a>, casting the spotlight on an unlikely protagonist: the oyster. This narrative begins with the arrival of 235 adult oysters from Pacific Hybreed, their sizes ranging impressively from 40 to 100mm, and further complemented by a diverse younger contingent—120 juveniles, 120 seed, and approximately 120 spat, all courtesy of the USDA’s 2023 spawn.</p>
<p>The experimental setup divided these oysters into two groups: one destined for a control tank, mirroring their natural aquatic environment at a serene 17ºC, and the other for a treatment tank, where conditions were significantly altered. The latter group was subjected to a deliberate increase in temperature, a gradual ascent of 2ºC per hour until the water reached a stress-inducing 26ºC, maintained for six hours daily over a seven-week span (began 10 2 2023, ended 11 21 2023). This thermal regimen aimed to simulate the increasingly erratic and harsh conditions wrought by climate change.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Explanation_2024-03-08_15-17-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Adding a layer of complexity, adults and juveniles were subjected to mechanical stress, an innovative use of a salad spinner for 15 minutes on selected dates (10/2/2023, 10/4/2023, 10/11/2023). This unusual methodology aimed to mimic the physical disturbances oysters might face in their natural habitats, from tumbling in currents to encounters with predators and debris.</p>
<p>The culmination of this phase was marked by a meticulous sampling process on November 21, 2023. Selected groups of oysters were divided for detailed analysis, with some undergoing immediate tissue sampling for RNA and DNA analysis, while others faced an additional stress test—a 30-minute immersion in 32ºC water followed by a tumbling session in the salad spinner. This process was designed to simulate an acute stress event, allowing researchers to gauge the oysters’ physiological responses to compounded stressors.</p>
<p>Several months later, on February 28, 2024, the experiment was revisited with a focused approach. This time, the younger generation of oysters was spotlighted, undergoing tissue sampling without the prior mechanical stress, to isolate the effects of thermal stress.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/growth.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Take-away to date</strong> - Stress hardening in spat in October and November resulted in increased growth compared to controls in February.</p>
<p>This experiment is not merely an investigation into the resilience of oysters to thermal and mechanical stress; it’s a narrative about adaptation, survival, and the intricate dance of life beneath the waves.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io/data-explanation/">Eric’s Post</a> for more details.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-oyster_stage/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/pw.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="124" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Decoding the Olympia Oyster</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/ostrea/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The listed publications collectively contribute to the genomic characterization and conservation of <em>Ostrea lurida</em>, the Olympia oyster, through various research focuses and methodologies:<br>
<br>
1. **Timmins-Schiffman et al.&nbsp;(2013)**: This paper lays the groundwork for genomic resource development in shellfish, including Ostrea lurida. It emphasizes the importance of genomic tools in conservation efforts, offering a foundational approach for subsequent research in the species’ genetic characterization.<br>
<br>
2. **White et al.&nbsp;(2017)**: Focusing on genotype-by-sequencing, this study investigates genetic variations in three different populations of Olympia oysters. It contributes to understanding population-specific genetic structures, which is crucial for conservation strategies tailored to different geographic regions.<br>
<br>
3. **Hintz et al.&nbsp;(2017)**: This research presents a nonlethal method for studying Olympia oysters, enabling ongoing research without harming the organisms. Such methods are vital for conservation as they allow for repeated observations and analyses over time.<br>
<br>
4. **Heare et al.&nbsp;(2017)**: This paper provides evidence of population structure in Puget Sound’s Ostrea lurida. Understanding population structure is key to conservation as it helps in identifying genetically distinct groups that may require different management approaches.<br>
<br>
5. **Heare et al.&nbsp;(2018)**: This study examines the differential response to stress in Ostrea lurida using gene expression. Insights into stress responses are important for conservation, especially in the face of environmental changes and stressors.<br>
<br>
6. **Silliman et al.&nbsp;(2018)**: This research highlights consistent differences in fitness traits across Olympia oyster generations. Fitness traits are essential for understanding the adaptive potential of species, which informs conservation and restoration efforts.<br>
<br>
7. **Silliman (2019)**: This study on population structure, genetic connectivity, and adaptation provides comprehensive insights into the genetic makeup and adaptive responses of Olympia oysters along the west coast of North America. This contributes significantly to conservation genetics.<br>
<br>
8. **Spencer et al.&nbsp;(2020)**: Investigating the carryover effects of temperature and pCO2, this study provides important information on how climate change factors affect Olympia oysters. This is crucial for predicting and mitigating future impacts on oyster populations.<br>
<br>
9. **Becker et al.&nbsp;(2020)**: Focusing on the spatial and temporal distribution of early life stages, this research informs about critical developmental phases of the Olympia oyster, aiding in the understanding of population dynamics and effective conservation strategies.<br>
<br>
10. **Spencer et al.&nbsp;(2021)**: Examining the latent effects of winter warming on reproduction and larval viability, this study adds to the understanding of how climate change could impact the reproductive success and long-term viability of Olympia oysters.<br>
<br>
11. **Spencer, Roberts, Silliman (2023)**: This paper explores the population-specific effects of ocean acidification, adding to the body of knowledge about how different environmental stressors impact Ostrea lurida, which is critical for predicting and mitigating the impacts of ocean acidification.<br>
<br>
12. **Silliman et al.&nbsp;(2023)**: This study investigates the coupled epigenetic and genetic population structure, providing a nuanced understanding of how genetic and epigenetic factors contribute to the population dynamics of marine invertebrates, including Ostrea lurida.<br>
<br>
In summary, these publications cover a range of topics from genetic diversity, population structure, stress responses, effects of environmental changes, nonlethal research methods, and early life stage dynamics, all of which are essential for the effective conservation and management of the Olympia oyster, Ostrea lurida.</p>
<p>REFERENCES</p>
<p>Timmins-Schiffman EB, Friedman CS, Metzger DC, White SJ and Roberts SB. (**2013**) [Genomic resource development for shellfish of conservation concern](<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1755-0998.12052/abstract" class="uri">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1755-0998.12052/abstract</a>) Molecular Ecology Resources. doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12052<br>
<br>
Samuel J. White, Brent Vadopalas, Katherine Silliman &amp; Steven B. Roberts (**2017**) [Genotoype-by-sequencing of three geographically distinct populations of Olympia oysters, _Ostrea lurida_](<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata2017130)Scientific" class="uri">https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata2017130)Scientific</a>&nbsp;Data 4, Article number: 170130 doi: 10.1038/sdata.2017.130<br>
<br>
Megan Hintz, Katherine Gratz, Bonnie Becker, Brent Vadopalas, and Steven Roberts (**2017**) [A Nonlethal Anesthesia Protocol for Accessing the Mantle Cavity of Olympia Oysters in the Laboratory or Field](<a href="https://doi.org/10.2983/035.036.0207" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.2983/035.036.0207</a>) Journal of Shellfish Research 2017 36 (2), 353-357 doi: 10.2983/035.036.0207<br>
<br>
Jake Emerson Heare, Brady Blake, Jonathan P Davis, Brent Vadopalas, Steven Roberts (**2017**) [Evidence of Ostrea lurida Carpenter, 1864 population structure in Puget Sound, WA](<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/maec.12458" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/maec.12458</a>) Marine Ecology 38:e12458 doi: 10.1111/maec.12458<br>
<br>
Heare JE, White SJ, Vadopalas B, Roberts SB. (**2018**) [Differential response to stress in _Ostrea lurida_ as measured by gene expression](<a href="https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.4261" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.4261</a>) PeerJ 6:e4261. doi: 10.7717/peerj.4261<br>
<br>
Silliman KE, Bowyer TK, Roberts SB. (**2018**) [Consistent differences in fitness traits across multiple generations of Olympia oysters](<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-24455-3" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-24455-3</a>) Scientific Reports volume 8, Article number:6080. doi:10.1038/s41598-018-24455-3<br>
<br>
Katherine Silliman. Population structure, genetic connectivity, and adaptation in the Olympia oyster<br>
(Ostrea lurida) along the west coast of North America. Evolutionary Applications, 11:697, 2019. doi:<br>
10.1111/eva.12766. GitHub Repo.<br>
<br>
Spencer, LH, Venkataraman, YR, Crim R, Ryan S, Horwith MJ, and Roberts SB (**2020**) [Carryover effects of temperature and pCO2 across multiple Olympia oyster populations](<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.2060" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.2060</a>). Ecological Applications 00( 00):e02060. doi:10.1002/eap.2060<br>
<br>
Bonnie J. Becker, Michael D. Behrens, Brian Allen, Megan Hintz, Hannah Parker, Michelle M. McCartha, and Sarah M. White (**2020**) [Spatial and Temporal Distribution of the Early Life History Stages of the Native Olympia Oyster Ostrea lurida (Carpenter, 1864) in a Restoration Site in Northern Puget Sound, Wa](<a href="http://doi.org/10.2983/035.039.0105" class="uri">http://doi.org/10.2983/035.039.0105</a>) Journal of Shellfish Research 39(1), 43-58. doi:/10.2983/035.039.0105<br>
<br>
Laura H. Spencer, Erin Horkan, Ryan Crim, Steven B. Roberts (2021) Latent effects of winter warming on Olympia oyster reproduction and larval viability Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology. doi:10.1016/j.jembe.2021.151604<br>
<br>
Population-specific effects of ocean acidification in the Olympia oyster Laura H Spencer, Steven B Roberts, Katherine Silliman bioRxiv 2023.09.08.556443; doi:&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.08.556443" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.08.556443</a><br>
<br>
Katherine Silliman and others, Epigenetic and Genetic Population Structure is Coupled in a Marine Invertebrate, Genome Biology and Evolution, Volume 15, Issue 2, February 2023, evad013,&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evad013" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evad013</a></p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>conservation</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/ostrea/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_httpswww.biorxiv.orgcontent10.11012023.09.08.556443v1.full.pdf_2024-03-09_15-20-38.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Are you really prepared?</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-prep/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/people.html#ariana-s.-huffmyer-phd">Ariana</a> lead a great tutorial on being prepared and planning for science. The narrative underscored the importance of thorough preparation and planning, including considering alternative uses for collected data, planning for potential pitfalls, and ensuring that experimental designs are robust against unforeseen challenges. This includes the practical aspects of laboratory work, field studies, and data analysis, emphasizing the value of learning from past experiences and being flexible in research approaches.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Exp_prep.mov"></video></div>
<p>Designing scientific experiments requires extensive planning to ensure projects run smoothly and yield meaningful results. Here are some important aspects to consider when preparing for research:</p>
<p><strong>Clearly Define Your Hypothesis and Objectives</strong>: Having a clear hypothesis drives your experimental design and analysis approach. Define what you aim to test upfront.</p>
<p><strong>Prepare Detailed Protocols</strong>: Write step-by-step protocols for all procedures well before starting. Practice techniques on mock datasets to work out kinks.</p>
<p><strong>Plan Your Data Collection</strong>: Design data sheets, name conventions, and metadata standards early. Consider sample sizes and ensure you collect the right data to answer your questions.</p>
<p><strong>Schedule Carefully</strong>: Block out experiment timelines, factoring permitting needs and collaborator availability. Leave buffer time for unexpected issues.</p>
<p><strong>Create Organizational Systems</strong>: Use checklists, spreadsheets, and visual aids to track tasks and ensure all preparation steps are completed thoroughly.</p>
<p><strong>Anticipate Challenges</strong>: Brainstorm potential pitfalls and have contingency plans. Run test analyses to flag problems before using real data.</p>
<p>Proper preparation is key to running successful, high-quality experiments that yield meaningful scientific insights. Taking the time to carefully plan experimental design and logistics pays off in efficient, productive research.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-prep/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/prep.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sharing the Good Word of Marine Epigenetics</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-asi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The University of Concepción recently offered an eye-opening course that dove deep into the realms of climate change, epigenetics, and marine biology. Titled “<a href="https://sr320.github.io/course-ASI-2024/">Epigenetic Phenomena Connecting Climate Change and Coastal Marine Species</a>,” this graduate-level course provided an intensive one-week journey into the fascinating interplay between our changing climate and the genetic mechanisms of marine invertebrates.</p>
<section id="unraveling-the-mysteries-of-marine-invertebrates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="unraveling-the-mysteries-of-marine-invertebrates">Unraveling the Mysteries of Marine Invertebrates</h3>
<p>The course, designed for students with a foundational understanding of genetics and climate science, began by establishing a strong base in epigenetics, climate change, and marine invertebrate physiology. The highlight was on the often-overlooked role of marine invertebrates in coastal ecosystems, emphasizing their ecological importance and responses to climate change at an epigenetic level.</p>
</section>
<section id="real-world-applications-and-functional-genomics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-world-applications-and-functional-genomics">Real-World Applications and Functional Genomics</h3>
<p>A significant focus of the course was the application of functional genomics. Students explored how climate change leads to alterations in epigenetic mechanisms of various coastal marine invertebrates through real-world examples. This approach helped in understanding the broader implications of these changes for marine ecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="comprehensive-course-objectives" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comprehensive-course-objectives">Comprehensive Course Objectives</h3>
<p>The course had three primary objectives:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Understanding Climate Change and Epigenetics</strong>: Gaining a comprehensive understanding of how climate change impacts marine invertebrates’ physiological processes through an epigenetic lens.</li>
<li><strong>Proficiency in Functional Genomics</strong>: Learning about genomic techniques and their applications in studying epigenetic changes in marine invertebrates due to climate stressors.</li>
<li><strong>Analyzing Scientific Research</strong>: Developing skills to critically analyze and evaluate scientific literature in marine invertebrate epigenetics and climate change.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="course-content-a-rich-blend-of-science-and-research" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="course-content-a-rich-blend-of-science-and-research">Course Content: A Rich Blend of Science and Research</h3>
<p>The course content was diverse and in-depth:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Basics of Epigenetics and Climate Change</strong>: Introduced the intersection of these fields and the concept of environmental epigenetics.</li>
<li><strong>Physiology of Marine Invertebrates</strong>: Covered essential aspects like feeding, digestion, reproduction, and stress response.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of Climate Change on Physiology</strong>: Explored the specific impacts of climate factors on marine invertebrates.</li>
<li><strong>Functional Genomics and Epigenetics</strong>: Delved into genomic methodologies and applications.</li>
<li><strong>Case Studies and Current Research</strong>: Involved critical examination of recent research studies, emphasizing practical understanding.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="methodology-interactive-and-engaging" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methodology-interactive-and-engaging">Methodology: Interactive and Engaging</h3>
<p>The course used a mix of lectures, discussions, and interactive data analysis. It emphasized hands-on learning, particularly in the afternoons, where students engaged in data analysis using R and bash, providing a practical edge to the theoretical knowledge gained.</p>
</section>
<section id="scholarly-contributions-a-rich-bibliography" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scholarly-contributions-a-rich-bibliography">Scholarly Contributions: A Rich Bibliography</h3>
<p>The course drew from a rich bibliography, featuring works by renowned researchers like Grace Crandall, Steven B. Roberts, and Cristian Gallardo-Escárate. These publications covered various aspects, from the proteomic responses of Pacific Oysters to the genomic assembly of the Blue Mussel, offering students a comprehensive view of current research in the field.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-a-step-forward-in-marine-biology-education" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-a-step-forward-in-marine-biology-education">Conclusion: A Step Forward in Marine Biology Education</h3>
<p>This course at the University of Concepción marked a significant step in educating the next generation of marine biologists, geneticists, and climate scientists. By bridging the gap between climate change and epigenetic phenomena in marine species, it not only enhanced understanding but also prepared students to contribute meaningfully to marine conservation efforts in the face of global climate challenges.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>course</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-asi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/asi.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring the Impact of Marine Heatwaves on Pacific Cod</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-cod/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In recent years, the Northeastern Pacific has been hit by a series of unprecedented marine heatwaves, notably “The Blob” from 2014-2016 and another in 2019, causing significant ecological disruptions. A compelling article titled “Beyond the Blob: Pinpointing the Mechanisms of Pacific Cod Population Decline” by the CICOES staff, delves into the alarming decline of Pacific cod populations in the Gulf of Alaska, a critical concern given the species’ ecological and economic significance.</p>
<p>The Pacific cod, a vital component of Alaska’s groundfish fishery, generating over $100 million annually, faced a dramatic 71% reduction in population between 2015 and 2017 surveys. This decline coincides with the marine heatwaves, raising urgent questions about the survival of early life stages of Pacific cod in a rapidly changing climate.</p>
<p>Researchers from CICOES, the University of Washington’s School of Aquatic and Fishery Sciences, Oregon State University, and NOAA are collaborating to unravel how increased temperatures impact Pacific cod. Their focus is on the vulnerable early life stages – developing eggs, larvae, and juveniles. Intriguingly, higher temperatures, while accelerating growth, also diminish liver size and alter key metabolic enzymes in young Pacific cod, hinting at deeper metabolic disruptions.</p>
<p>One innovative approach used by these researchers is RNA-Seq, a next-generation sequencing technology. It allows for a comprehensive analysis of gene activity, shedding light on how warming affects Pacific cod at a molecular level. Initial findings suggest that high temperatures during larval rearing disrupt lipid metabolism processes, potentially reducing energy availability, a crucial resource during this stage.</p>
<p>The ultimate goal of these studies is to identify the mechanisms driving the mortality of Pacific cod post marine heatwaves. If these mechanisms are more clearly understood, it could lead to the identification of populations or individuals with a better genetic and physiological predisposition to withstand warmer conditions.</p>
<p>For anyone interested in marine biology, climate change impacts, or fisheries management, this article is a must-read. It not only provides a deep dive into the challenges faced by Pacific cod but also highlights the cutting-edge research being conducted to safeguard these vital marine populations. To explore this topic further and understand the intricacies of this crucial research, I highly recommend reading the full article in the CICOES Magazine 2023 issue. <a href="../../img/CICOES.pdf"><em>Read the full article</em></a> <em>below</em> to gain a deeper understanding of the interplay between marine heatwaves and marine life.</p>
<p><object data="/img/CICOES.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="600" height="400"><p>Unable to display PDF file. <a href="../../img/CICOES.pdf">Download</a> instead.</p></object></p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>rna-seq</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-cod/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/cod.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="139" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Clam Gonad RNAseq Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Megan Ewing</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Write up for <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/resources/issues/1748">this github issue</a></p>
<p>Github repo available <a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples">here</a> but each step’s chunk is also linked in workflow write up.</p>
<section id="the-data" class="level1">
<h1>The Data</h1>
<p>The RNA-seq data that was analyzed for this issue was from manila clam (<em>Ruditapes philippinarum</em>) samples of a control and treatment group. There were 15 control samples and 15 treatment samples, each with 2 reads. Each fasta file had the naming scheme <code>M-?-###_R#_001</code> where <code>?</code> = C (control) or T(treatment), <code>###</code> = sample number, and <code>R#</code> = R1 (read 1) or R2 (read 2). Raw files can be found <a href="https://gannet.fish.washington.edu/mewing0/Man_clam_raw/">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-workflow" class="level1">
<h1>The Workflow</h1>
<section id="retrieving-files-from-gannet" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="retrieving-files-from-gannet">Retrieving Files From Gannet</h3>
<p>To start the analysis, I retrieved the raw reads from gannet using wget.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/01-RNAseq.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="checking-file-integrity-via-md5sums" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="checking-file-integrity-via-md5sums">Checking File Integrity via MD5sums</h3>
<p>Typically, the next step would be to check the file integrity by comparing the md5sums of the downloaded files with those on the remote server (gannet). However, the directory containing our reads did not have a text file of the md5sums for me to run <code>md5sum</code> on. So we skipped this step.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/02-md5sums.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="fastqc-and-multiqc" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fastqc-and-multiqc">FastQC and MultiQC</h3>
<p>The next step was to evaluate the quality of our sequences using FastQC and MultiQC. I generated a FastQC file for each of the reads, and then combined all of those using MultiQC to look at the quality of all of our reads together. The MultiQC report can be found <a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/output/fastQC-output/multiqc_report.html">here</a> (note to view the “pretty version” you will need to download the html file and open the local file since github just shows the raw). Here’s some of the results from that:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_sequence_counts_plot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_base_sequence_quality_plot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_sequence_quality_scores_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_sequence_gc_content_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_base_n_content_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_sequence_duplication_levels_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_overrepresented_sequences_plot.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/Screen Shot 2024-01-04 at 3.16.31 PM.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc-status-check-heatmap.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Software Used:</p>
<ul>
<li>FastQC (v0.12.1)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/03-fastqc_multiqc.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="psuedo-alignment-with-kallisto" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="psuedo-alignment-with-kallisto">Psuedo Alignment with Kallisto</h3>
<p>Next I pseudo aligned the reads and quantified expression using Kallisto. I did not trim prior to this as it is not wholly necessary for pseudo alignment. An index for alignment and quantification was created using a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/datasets/genome/GCF_026571515.1/">reference transcriptome for <em>Ruditapes philippinarum</em></a> (note: ensure to select for RNA file)<em>.</em> Paired end reads for each sample were then aligned and quantified against this index.</p>
<p>Following pseudo alignment and quantification, a trinity matrix was created with the Kallisto output to build an abundance matrix.</p>
<p>Software Used:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Kallisto (Linux)(v0.50.1)</p></li>
<li><p>TrinityRNAseq (v2.12.0)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/05-kallisto.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="differential-expression-and-visualization-with-deseq2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="differential-expression-and-visualization-with-deseq2">Differential Expression and Visualization with DESeq2</h3>
<p>Using the quantification in the trinity matrix created, I ran DESeq2 to show deferentially expressed genes, and filtering for those who’s expression showed a difference with a p value &lt;= 0.05. Differential expression was also visualized via a volcano plot and heatmap of the top 25 deferentially expressed genes)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/volcanoplot-01.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/heatmap.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Along with the visualzations, I created a dataframe with the differentially expressed genes and associated statistics (base mean, log 2fold change, lfcSE, stat, pvalue, padj) and saved as a tab file for the next steps.</p>
<p>Software used:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>BiocManager (v1.30.22)</p></li>
<li><p>DESeq2 (v1.38.3)</p></li>
<li><p>pheatmap (v1.0.12)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/06-deseq2.Rmd">Code on GitHub</a></p>
</section>
<section id="identifying-deg-functions-with-blastx" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="identifying-deg-functions-with-blastx">Identifying DEG Functions with Blastx</h3>
<p>Once we had a tab file with differentially expressed genes, we could run blast on our <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/datasets/genome/GCF_026571515.1/">reference genome</a> (note: be sure to select for RNA file). Doing this creates a list of all of the genes (and gene short names) in our reference genome for us to get the names of our DEGs in the next step.</p>
<p>Software used:</p>
<ul>
<li>NCBI Blast (v2.11.0)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/07-blast.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="joining-deg-with-blast-results-and-uniprot-gene-ontology-annotations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="joining-deg-with-blast-results-and-uniprot-gene-ontology-annotations">Joining DEG with Blast Results and UniProt Gene Ontology Annotations</h3>
<p>Using the file created from the reference genome Blast, I combined the Blast results with the DEG file by the common gene names. This dataframe contained the gene ID, gene short name, base mean, log 2fold change, pvalue, and padj. I isolated the UniProt IDs from the gene short names in order to retrieve the gene ontology (GO) annotations of interest.</p>
<p>I looked up the annotations on <a href="https://www.uniprot.org/id-mapping">UniProt’s web interface</a> and saved the output as a tab file. Finally, I merged the Blast/DEG data frame with the GO data frame by the common UniProt ID’s/Entries to get a file of our GO annotations for the significantly deferentially expressed genes. The annotation file is available <a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/output/clam_GO_annotations.csv">here</a>.</p>
<p><a href="08-join_annotations.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="general-non-step-specific-software-and-hardware-info" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-non-step-specific-software-and-hardware-info">General (non-step specific) software and hardware info:</h3>
<p>Computer: 2016 MacBook Pro 8GB 13” with macOS Big Sur (v11.2)</p>
<p>IDE: R Studio (v4.2.3)(via raven)</p>


<!-- -->

</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rnaseq</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>clam</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_mewing-notebook_-_Clam_Gonad_RNAseq_Analysis_2024-01-06_07-25-10.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
