<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Intertidal Innovators</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-intertidal/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Quote
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This program has lasted for 10 days, but during those days we have learned and worked very hard to give you this project. And we are proud to say that there are a bunch of hard working members in our program that have learned new skills and have gained knowledge in this program So in this journey, you will learn a lot about our work and marine life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PsVyUPzu2_A" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-intertidal/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_The_Golden_Hour_-_a_geolocated_audio_walk_by_Intertidal_Innovators_on_ECHOES_2024-08-19_12-50-25.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ostras en Chile</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-ostras/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_6806.jpg_19801320_pixels_2024-08-14_11-49-59.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 6, 2024, approximately sixty participants gathered at the Professor Alamiro Robledo Auditorium of the Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences at the University of Concepción. They were there to delve into the promising sector of oyster aquaculture in Chile during the seminar titled “Oysters in Chile: Opportunities and Challenges for Aquaculture Diversification.” This event was meticulously organized by the Interdisciplinary Center for Aquaculture Research (INCAR).</p>
<p>The seminar showcased six presentations from both national and international experts, followed by a panel discussion. The diverse audience included academia, public and private sector representatives, producers, aquaculturists, industry leaders, professionals, and both secondary and postgraduate students. The gathering aimed to foster a comprehensive dialogue on the development of oyster aquaculture in the country.</p>
<p>Manira Matamala, the regional director of the Undersecretary of Fisheries and Aquaculture (Subpesca) for Valparaíso, O’Higgins, and Maule, commended INCAR’s initiative. She highlighted the seminar’s focus on enhancing the genetic and genomic understanding of oysters, which is vital for promoting sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
<p>Among the speakers, Justo García, an aquaculturist and founder of “Cultivos Cholche,” shared insights from his hands-on experience in various stages of oyster production, emphasizing the importance of adding value to the aquaculture processes.</p>
<p>Key Presentations Highlighted at the Seminar:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Steven Roberts from the University of Washington offered an international perspective with his presentation on the “<a href="https://github.com/sr320/talk-ostras-2024">Olympia Oyster (Ostrea lurida) Restoration in the United States</a>,” focusing on physiological and genomic insights.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardo-Escárate, deputy director of Incar, discussed the genome of the Chilean oyster (Ostrea chilensis) as a critical tool for the restoration and conservation of natural oyster banks.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Francisco Cárcamo shared experiences on co-cultivating Japanese oysters and algae both in field and laboratory settings, presenting an alternative approach for Environmental Performance Enhancement (APE). Justo García recounted his local experiences in small-scale aquaculture for both Chilean and Japanese oysters.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Rodrigo Rojas from the Catholic University of the North introduced advances from a technological program aimed at the sustainable development of Japanese oyster cultivation.</p></li>
<li><p>Meyling Tang, vice president of the Cocinamar Foundation, proposed strategies to reinvigorate oyster consumption in Chile with her presentation titled “Oysters Everywhere: Ideas to Reactivate Oyster Consumption in Chile.”</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Renato Quiñones, the director of Incar, emphasized the seminar’s role in bringing together experts from varied fields to create a multidimensional space for all stakeholders involved in oyster cultivation. This interaction is crucial for transforming scientific knowledge into a community and national heritage.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The event concluded with a panel discussion moderated by Dr.&nbsp;Doris Soto, principal investigator at Incar, where experts discussed the multifaceted opportunities and challenges facing aquaculture diversification in Chile.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-36-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This seminar not only highlighted the collaborative efforts required to advance oyster aquaculture but also showcased the commitment of INCAR to foster a sustainable and innovative aquaculture industry in Chile.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>presentation</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-ostras/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-33-39.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring How Environmental Conditions Impact Atlantic Salmon’s Defense Against Sea Lice</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38876411/">In our latest study, we delved into the complex interplay between environmental factors and the immune responses of Atlantic salmon (<em>Salmo salar</em>) during infestations by sea lice (<em>Caligus rogercresseyi</em>).</a> This research is particularly significant for both aquaculture and the management of natural marine ecosystems.</p>
<section id="our-research-approach" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-research-approach">Our Research Approach</h4>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardos’ team set up an experimental infestation of Atlantic salmon with sea lice, controlling for variations in temperature and salinity: specifically, conditions were set at 8°C and 16°C, and 32 and 26 practical salinity units (PSU). We then collected tissues from these fish to conduct analyses via reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) and whole transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq).</p>
</section>
<section id="key-discoveries" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-discoveries">Key Discoveries</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Impact of Environment on Parasitic Load</strong>: We observed that the parasitic load varied significantly with environmental conditions, noting the lowest abundance of lice in salmon kept at cooler and less saline conditions (8°C/26PSU).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Transcriptional Changes and Splicing Events</strong>: Environmental conditions were found to influence the salmon’s transcriptome profiles substantially. Notably, there was an increase in alternative splicing events in fish under low temperature and salinity, suggesting that environmental stress can induce genomic adaptations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Methylation Patterns</strong>: We also noted significant changes in methylation levels in response to temperature variations, with more pronounced differential methylation regions (DMRs) at the higher temperature of 16°C. These methylation changes correlated with the expression of alternatively spliced transcripts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Biological Pathways</strong>: Our analyses revealed significant correlations between methylation, transcript expression, and key biological pathways such as Ferroptosis and TLR signaling pathways, which are crucial for immune response and cellular integrity.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="implications-of-our-findings" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-of-our-findings">Implications of Our Findings</h4>
<p>This research highlights the nuanced ways in which environmental conditions can influence the genomic and epigenomic landscapes of marine organisms. For the aquaculture industry, understanding these dynamics is essential for developing effective management strategies to combat sea lice infestations, which are a major challenge for the sustainability and economic success of salmon farming.</p>
<p>Moreover, the link between environmental conditions, alternative splicing, and methylation opens new research avenues into the genetic mechanisms of resilience and adaptability in marine organisms. This knowledge advances our understanding of how species adapt to their changing environments, which is critical for preserving and enhancing the health of our global marine resources.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>salmon</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Environmental_influence_on_the_Atlantic_salmon_transcriptome_and_methylome_during_sea_lice_infestations_-_ScienceDirect_2024-08-14_12-12-07.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unraveling the Intricacies of Enrichment Analysis</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-enrich/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In our most recent lab meeting, we delved into the fascinating world of enrichment analysis. This statistical method is a cornerstone of our research, helping us identify significantly over-represented subsets of proteins or genes within our data.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/GMT20240509-195925_Recording_gallery_1920x1080.mp4"></video></div>
<section id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-power-of-enrichment-analysis">The Power of Enrichment Analysis</h2>
<p>Enrichment analysis allows us to compare a small subset of genes or proteins to a larger set, identifying overrepresentation. This can provide valuable insights into the biological processes that are most relevant to our research.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-deep-dive-into-david" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-deep-dive-into-david">A Deep Dive into David</h2>
<p>One of the tools we use for enrichment analysis is David. During the meeting, we explored how to upload gene lists and backgrounds into David, and how to interpret the results it provides. This tool is invaluable in helping us understand the complex relationships and patterns within our data.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-reference-list-debate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-reference-list-debate">The Reference List Debate</h2>
<p>An interesting discussion arose around what to use as a reference list in enrichment analysis. Should it be all the genes detected in the data set, or all genes in a reference genome? This question sparked a lively debate, highlighting the complexities and nuances of enrichment analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visualizing-gene-ontology-with-revigo">Visualizing Gene Ontology with Revigo</h2>
<p>To help us visualize gene ontology, we use a tool called Revigo. This tool provides a visual representation of the relationships between genes, making it easier to understand the complex data we work with.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-lighter-moment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-lighter-moment">A Lighter Moment</h2>
<p>Amidst the serious scientific discussions, we also had a lighter moment when a team member shared a story about narrowly avoiding a parking ticket. It’s moments like these that remind us of the importance of camaraderie and humor in the lab.</p>
<hr>
<p>Our lab meetings are a crucial part of our research process, providing a space for us to discuss, debate, and learn together. Stay tuned for more insights from our lab meetings in future posts!</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-enrich/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/enrich.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery Field Day at Point Whitney</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On May 6, 2024, Dr.&nbsp;Ariana Huffmyer, an NSF Ocean Sciences Postdoctoral Fellow from the University of Rhode Island and University of Washington, shared insights from a field day at Point Whitney. This comprehensive post revealed the detailed process of managing and monitoring oyster growth and stress testing, providing a clear framework for hatchery management.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Link to Full Notebook Post
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/" class="uri">https://ahuffmyer.github.io/ASH_Putnam_Lab_Notebook/Hatchery-field-day-at-Point-Whitney-May-6-2024/</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Overview of Field Day Activities</strong> The objective was to monitor the health and stress responses of oyster cohorts at the hatchery. Key activities included calibrating monitoring equipment, feeding the oysters, and assessing the impacts of temperature and freshwater stress.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Monitoring Equipment Calibration:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer set up and calibrated an Orion Star A325 probe to measure pH, temperature, and conductivity. By using buffers of varying pH and a conductivity solution, she ensured accurate measurements. The pH was measured on the NBS scale, considered sufficient since ocean acidification experiments weren’t being conducted.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Feeding Protocol:</strong> The oysters were pulse-fed, where approximately 1/3 of a 5-gallon bucket was distributed among the tanks. This ensured that the animals received sufficient nutrition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fluorometry and Physiochemical Measurements:</strong> Fluorometry measurements were conducted before and after feeding, providing data on oyster metabolic activity. Additionally, pH, temperature, and conductivity were measured across different tanks, offering valuable weekly insights into water quality.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stress Testing Regimen:</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer conducted a 30-minute stress test for specific oyster cohorts using freshwater and elevated temperature exposures. Animals were subjected to 25°C temperature and freshwater immersion, replicating environmental stressors they might face. Trays were labeled and organized by stressor type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Growth Characterization:</strong> Size measurements were taken using a waterproof digital caliper. Cohorts were categorized based on their respective stressors, creating a comprehensive understanding of their growth patterns.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ploidy Testing Preparations:</strong> A selection of oysters from different cohorts was collected for ploidy testing to distinguish between diploid and triploid oysters. They were stored in mesh bags, and the testing results would provide critical information for future breeding programs.</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Hatchery_field_day_at_Point_Whitney_May_6_2024__Ariana_S_Huffmyer__NSF_Ocean_Sciences_Postdoctoral_Fellow_University_of_Rhod_2024-05-11_14-51-46.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>heath-tray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Takeaways for Hatchery Science</strong> Dr.&nbsp;Huffmyer’s systematic approach highlights the significance of precise monitoring and stress testing in hatchery science. Understanding oyster resilience to environmental stressors is crucial for aquaculture sustainability. Her work at Point Whitney offers a detailed protocol that could be replicated or adapted by other researchers to monitor and improve hatchery operations.</p>
<p>The future of hatchery management will depend heavily on such frameworks, where real-time data collection and analysis enable researchers to respond promptly to environmental changes.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/ariana-hatchery/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/bucket.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hardening in oysters drives increased growth</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the meticulously orchestrated world of marine science, a groundbreaking experiment has unfolded in the hands of <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io">Eric Essington</a>, casting the spotlight on an unlikely protagonist: the oyster. This narrative begins with the arrival of 235 adult oysters from Pacific Hybreed, their sizes ranging impressively from 40 to 100mm, and further complemented by a diverse younger contingent—120 juveniles, 120 seed, and approximately 120 spat, all courtesy of the USDA’s 2023 spawn.</p>
<p>The experimental setup divided these oysters into two groups: one destined for a control tank, mirroring their natural aquatic environment at a serene 17ºC, and the other for a treatment tank, where conditions were significantly altered. The latter group was subjected to a deliberate increase in temperature, a gradual ascent of 2ºC per hour until the water reached a stress-inducing 26ºC, maintained for six hours daily over a seven-week span (began 10 2 2023, ended 11 21 2023). This thermal regimen aimed to simulate the increasingly erratic and harsh conditions wrought by climate change.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Explanation_2024-03-08_15-17-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Adding a layer of complexity, adults and juveniles were subjected to mechanical stress, an innovative use of a salad spinner for 15 minutes on selected dates (10/2/2023, 10/4/2023, 10/11/2023). This unusual methodology aimed to mimic the physical disturbances oysters might face in their natural habitats, from tumbling in currents to encounters with predators and debris.</p>
<p>The culmination of this phase was marked by a meticulous sampling process on November 21, 2023. Selected groups of oysters were divided for detailed analysis, with some undergoing immediate tissue sampling for RNA and DNA analysis, while others faced an additional stress test—a 30-minute immersion in 32ºC water followed by a tumbling session in the salad spinner. This process was designed to simulate an acute stress event, allowing researchers to gauge the oysters’ physiological responses to compounded stressors.</p>
<p>Several months later, on February 28, 2024, the experiment was revisited with a focused approach. This time, the younger generation of oysters was spotlighted, undergoing tissue sampling without the prior mechanical stress, to isolate the effects of thermal stress.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/growth.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Take-away to date</strong> - Stress hardening in spat in October and November resulted in increased growth compared to controls in February.</p>
<p>This experiment is not merely an investigation into the resilience of oysters to thermal and mechanical stress; it’s a narrative about adaptation, survival, and the intricate dance of life beneath the waves.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://eric-ess.github.io/data-explanation/">Eric’s Post</a> for more details.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-oyster_stage/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/pw.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="124" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Decoding the Olympia Oyster</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/ostrea/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The listed publications collectively contribute to the genomic characterization and conservation of <em>Ostrea lurida</em>, the Olympia oyster, through various research focuses and methodologies:<br>
<br>
1. **Timmins-Schiffman et al.&nbsp;(2013)**: This paper lays the groundwork for genomic resource development in shellfish, including Ostrea lurida. It emphasizes the importance of genomic tools in conservation efforts, offering a foundational approach for subsequent research in the species’ genetic characterization.<br>
<br>
2. **White et al.&nbsp;(2017)**: Focusing on genotype-by-sequencing, this study investigates genetic variations in three different populations of Olympia oysters. It contributes to understanding population-specific genetic structures, which is crucial for conservation strategies tailored to different geographic regions.<br>
<br>
3. **Hintz et al.&nbsp;(2017)**: This research presents a nonlethal method for studying Olympia oysters, enabling ongoing research without harming the organisms. Such methods are vital for conservation as they allow for repeated observations and analyses over time.<br>
<br>
4. **Heare et al.&nbsp;(2017)**: This paper provides evidence of population structure in Puget Sound’s Ostrea lurida. Understanding population structure is key to conservation as it helps in identifying genetically distinct groups that may require different management approaches.<br>
<br>
5. **Heare et al.&nbsp;(2018)**: This study examines the differential response to stress in Ostrea lurida using gene expression. Insights into stress responses are important for conservation, especially in the face of environmental changes and stressors.<br>
<br>
6. **Silliman et al.&nbsp;(2018)**: This research highlights consistent differences in fitness traits across Olympia oyster generations. Fitness traits are essential for understanding the adaptive potential of species, which informs conservation and restoration efforts.<br>
<br>
7. **Silliman (2019)**: This study on population structure, genetic connectivity, and adaptation provides comprehensive insights into the genetic makeup and adaptive responses of Olympia oysters along the west coast of North America. This contributes significantly to conservation genetics.<br>
<br>
8. **Spencer et al.&nbsp;(2020)**: Investigating the carryover effects of temperature and pCO2, this study provides important information on how climate change factors affect Olympia oysters. This is crucial for predicting and mitigating future impacts on oyster populations.<br>
<br>
9. **Becker et al.&nbsp;(2020)**: Focusing on the spatial and temporal distribution of early life stages, this research informs about critical developmental phases of the Olympia oyster, aiding in the understanding of population dynamics and effective conservation strategies.<br>
<br>
10. **Spencer et al.&nbsp;(2021)**: Examining the latent effects of winter warming on reproduction and larval viability, this study adds to the understanding of how climate change could impact the reproductive success and long-term viability of Olympia oysters.<br>
<br>
11. **Spencer, Roberts, Silliman (2023)**: This paper explores the population-specific effects of ocean acidification, adding to the body of knowledge about how different environmental stressors impact Ostrea lurida, which is critical for predicting and mitigating the impacts of ocean acidification.<br>
<br>
12. **Silliman et al.&nbsp;(2023)**: This study investigates the coupled epigenetic and genetic population structure, providing a nuanced understanding of how genetic and epigenetic factors contribute to the population dynamics of marine invertebrates, including Ostrea lurida.<br>
<br>
In summary, these publications cover a range of topics from genetic diversity, population structure, stress responses, effects of environmental changes, nonlethal research methods, and early life stage dynamics, all of which are essential for the effective conservation and management of the Olympia oyster, Ostrea lurida.</p>
<p>REFERENCES</p>
<p>Timmins-Schiffman EB, Friedman CS, Metzger DC, White SJ and Roberts SB. (**2013**) [Genomic resource development for shellfish of conservation concern](<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1755-0998.12052/abstract" class="uri">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1755-0998.12052/abstract</a>) Molecular Ecology Resources. doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12052<br>
<br>
Samuel J. White, Brent Vadopalas, Katherine Silliman &amp; Steven B. Roberts (**2017**) [Genotoype-by-sequencing of three geographically distinct populations of Olympia oysters, _Ostrea lurida_](<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata2017130)Scientific" class="uri">https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata2017130)Scientific</a>&nbsp;Data 4, Article number: 170130 doi: 10.1038/sdata.2017.130<br>
<br>
Megan Hintz, Katherine Gratz, Bonnie Becker, Brent Vadopalas, and Steven Roberts (**2017**) [A Nonlethal Anesthesia Protocol for Accessing the Mantle Cavity of Olympia Oysters in the Laboratory or Field](<a href="https://doi.org/10.2983/035.036.0207" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.2983/035.036.0207</a>) Journal of Shellfish Research 2017 36 (2), 353-357 doi: 10.2983/035.036.0207<br>
<br>
Jake Emerson Heare, Brady Blake, Jonathan P Davis, Brent Vadopalas, Steven Roberts (**2017**) [Evidence of Ostrea lurida Carpenter, 1864 population structure in Puget Sound, WA](<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/maec.12458" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/maec.12458</a>) Marine Ecology 38:e12458 doi: 10.1111/maec.12458<br>
<br>
Heare JE, White SJ, Vadopalas B, Roberts SB. (**2018**) [Differential response to stress in _Ostrea lurida_ as measured by gene expression](<a href="https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.4261" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.4261</a>) PeerJ 6:e4261. doi: 10.7717/peerj.4261<br>
<br>
Silliman KE, Bowyer TK, Roberts SB. (**2018**) [Consistent differences in fitness traits across multiple generations of Olympia oysters](<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-24455-3" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-24455-3</a>) Scientific Reports volume 8, Article number:6080. doi:10.1038/s41598-018-24455-3<br>
<br>
Katherine Silliman. Population structure, genetic connectivity, and adaptation in the Olympia oyster<br>
(Ostrea lurida) along the west coast of North America. Evolutionary Applications, 11:697, 2019. doi:<br>
10.1111/eva.12766. GitHub Repo.<br>
<br>
Spencer, LH, Venkataraman, YR, Crim R, Ryan S, Horwith MJ, and Roberts SB (**2020**) [Carryover effects of temperature and pCO2 across multiple Olympia oyster populations](<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.2060" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.2060</a>). Ecological Applications 00( 00):e02060. doi:10.1002/eap.2060<br>
<br>
Bonnie J. Becker, Michael D. Behrens, Brian Allen, Megan Hintz, Hannah Parker, Michelle M. McCartha, and Sarah M. White (**2020**) [Spatial and Temporal Distribution of the Early Life History Stages of the Native Olympia Oyster Ostrea lurida (Carpenter, 1864) in a Restoration Site in Northern Puget Sound, Wa](<a href="http://doi.org/10.2983/035.039.0105" class="uri">http://doi.org/10.2983/035.039.0105</a>) Journal of Shellfish Research 39(1), 43-58. doi:/10.2983/035.039.0105<br>
<br>
Laura H. Spencer, Erin Horkan, Ryan Crim, Steven B. Roberts (2021) Latent effects of winter warming on Olympia oyster reproduction and larval viability Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology. doi:10.1016/j.jembe.2021.151604<br>
<br>
Population-specific effects of ocean acidification in the Olympia oyster Laura H Spencer, Steven B Roberts, Katherine Silliman bioRxiv 2023.09.08.556443; doi:&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.08.556443" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.08.556443</a><br>
<br>
Katherine Silliman and others, Epigenetic and Genetic Population Structure is Coupled in a Marine Invertebrate, Genome Biology and Evolution, Volume 15, Issue 2, February 2023, evad013,&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evad013" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evad013</a></p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>conservation</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/ostrea/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_httpswww.biorxiv.orgcontent10.11012023.09.08.556443v1.full.pdf_2024-03-09_15-20-38.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Are you really prepared?</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-prep/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/people.html#ariana-s.-huffmyer-phd">Ariana</a> lead a great tutorial on being prepared and planning for science. The narrative underscored the importance of thorough preparation and planning, including considering alternative uses for collected data, planning for potential pitfalls, and ensuring that experimental designs are robust against unforeseen challenges. This includes the practical aspects of laboratory work, field studies, and data analysis, emphasizing the value of learning from past experiences and being flexible in research approaches.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Exp_prep.mov"></video></div>
<p>Designing scientific experiments requires extensive planning to ensure projects run smoothly and yield meaningful results. Here are some important aspects to consider when preparing for research:</p>
<p><strong>Clearly Define Your Hypothesis and Objectives</strong>: Having a clear hypothesis drives your experimental design and analysis approach. Define what you aim to test upfront.</p>
<p><strong>Prepare Detailed Protocols</strong>: Write step-by-step protocols for all procedures well before starting. Practice techniques on mock datasets to work out kinks.</p>
<p><strong>Plan Your Data Collection</strong>: Design data sheets, name conventions, and metadata standards early. Consider sample sizes and ensure you collect the right data to answer your questions.</p>
<p><strong>Schedule Carefully</strong>: Block out experiment timelines, factoring permitting needs and collaborator availability. Leave buffer time for unexpected issues.</p>
<p><strong>Create Organizational Systems</strong>: Use checklists, spreadsheets, and visual aids to track tasks and ensure all preparation steps are completed thoroughly.</p>
<p><strong>Anticipate Challenges</strong>: Brainstorm potential pitfalls and have contingency plans. Run test analyses to flag problems before using real data.</p>
<p>Proper preparation is key to running successful, high-quality experiments that yield meaningful scientific insights. Taking the time to carefully plan experimental design and logistics pays off in efficient, productive research.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>tools</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-prep/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/prep.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sharing the Good Word of Marine Epigenetics</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-asi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The University of Concepción recently offered an eye-opening course that dove deep into the realms of climate change, epigenetics, and marine biology. Titled “<a href="https://sr320.github.io/course-ASI-2024/">Epigenetic Phenomena Connecting Climate Change and Coastal Marine Species</a>,” this graduate-level course provided an intensive one-week journey into the fascinating interplay between our changing climate and the genetic mechanisms of marine invertebrates.</p>
<section id="unraveling-the-mysteries-of-marine-invertebrates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="unraveling-the-mysteries-of-marine-invertebrates">Unraveling the Mysteries of Marine Invertebrates</h3>
<p>The course, designed for students with a foundational understanding of genetics and climate science, began by establishing a strong base in epigenetics, climate change, and marine invertebrate physiology. The highlight was on the often-overlooked role of marine invertebrates in coastal ecosystems, emphasizing their ecological importance and responses to climate change at an epigenetic level.</p>
</section>
<section id="real-world-applications-and-functional-genomics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-world-applications-and-functional-genomics">Real-World Applications and Functional Genomics</h3>
<p>A significant focus of the course was the application of functional genomics. Students explored how climate change leads to alterations in epigenetic mechanisms of various coastal marine invertebrates through real-world examples. This approach helped in understanding the broader implications of these changes for marine ecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="comprehensive-course-objectives" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comprehensive-course-objectives">Comprehensive Course Objectives</h3>
<p>The course had three primary objectives:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Understanding Climate Change and Epigenetics</strong>: Gaining a comprehensive understanding of how climate change impacts marine invertebrates’ physiological processes through an epigenetic lens.</li>
<li><strong>Proficiency in Functional Genomics</strong>: Learning about genomic techniques and their applications in studying epigenetic changes in marine invertebrates due to climate stressors.</li>
<li><strong>Analyzing Scientific Research</strong>: Developing skills to critically analyze and evaluate scientific literature in marine invertebrate epigenetics and climate change.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="course-content-a-rich-blend-of-science-and-research" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="course-content-a-rich-blend-of-science-and-research">Course Content: A Rich Blend of Science and Research</h3>
<p>The course content was diverse and in-depth:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Basics of Epigenetics and Climate Change</strong>: Introduced the intersection of these fields and the concept of environmental epigenetics.</li>
<li><strong>Physiology of Marine Invertebrates</strong>: Covered essential aspects like feeding, digestion, reproduction, and stress response.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of Climate Change on Physiology</strong>: Explored the specific impacts of climate factors on marine invertebrates.</li>
<li><strong>Functional Genomics and Epigenetics</strong>: Delved into genomic methodologies and applications.</li>
<li><strong>Case Studies and Current Research</strong>: Involved critical examination of recent research studies, emphasizing practical understanding.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="methodology-interactive-and-engaging" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methodology-interactive-and-engaging">Methodology: Interactive and Engaging</h3>
<p>The course used a mix of lectures, discussions, and interactive data analysis. It emphasized hands-on learning, particularly in the afternoons, where students engaged in data analysis using R and bash, providing a practical edge to the theoretical knowledge gained.</p>
</section>
<section id="scholarly-contributions-a-rich-bibliography" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scholarly-contributions-a-rich-bibliography">Scholarly Contributions: A Rich Bibliography</h3>
<p>The course drew from a rich bibliography, featuring works by renowned researchers like Grace Crandall, Steven B. Roberts, and Cristian Gallardo-Escárate. These publications covered various aspects, from the proteomic responses of Pacific Oysters to the genomic assembly of the Blue Mussel, offering students a comprehensive view of current research in the field.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-a-step-forward-in-marine-biology-education" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-a-step-forward-in-marine-biology-education">Conclusion: A Step Forward in Marine Biology Education</h3>
<p>This course at the University of Concepción marked a significant step in educating the next generation of marine biologists, geneticists, and climate scientists. By bridging the gap between climate change and epigenetic phenomena in marine species, it not only enhanced understanding but also prepared students to contribute meaningfully to marine conservation efforts in the face of global climate challenges.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>course</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-asi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/asi.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring the Impact of Marine Heatwaves on Pacific Cod</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-cod/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In recent years, the Northeastern Pacific has been hit by a series of unprecedented marine heatwaves, notably “The Blob” from 2014-2016 and another in 2019, causing significant ecological disruptions. A compelling article titled “Beyond the Blob: Pinpointing the Mechanisms of Pacific Cod Population Decline” by the CICOES staff, delves into the alarming decline of Pacific cod populations in the Gulf of Alaska, a critical concern given the species’ ecological and economic significance.</p>
<p>The Pacific cod, a vital component of Alaska’s groundfish fishery, generating over $100 million annually, faced a dramatic 71% reduction in population between 2015 and 2017 surveys. This decline coincides with the marine heatwaves, raising urgent questions about the survival of early life stages of Pacific cod in a rapidly changing climate.</p>
<p>Researchers from CICOES, the University of Washington’s School of Aquatic and Fishery Sciences, Oregon State University, and NOAA are collaborating to unravel how increased temperatures impact Pacific cod. Their focus is on the vulnerable early life stages – developing eggs, larvae, and juveniles. Intriguingly, higher temperatures, while accelerating growth, also diminish liver size and alter key metabolic enzymes in young Pacific cod, hinting at deeper metabolic disruptions.</p>
<p>One innovative approach used by these researchers is RNA-Seq, a next-generation sequencing technology. It allows for a comprehensive analysis of gene activity, shedding light on how warming affects Pacific cod at a molecular level. Initial findings suggest that high temperatures during larval rearing disrupt lipid metabolism processes, potentially reducing energy availability, a crucial resource during this stage.</p>
<p>The ultimate goal of these studies is to identify the mechanisms driving the mortality of Pacific cod post marine heatwaves. If these mechanisms are more clearly understood, it could lead to the identification of populations or individuals with a better genetic and physiological predisposition to withstand warmer conditions.</p>
<p>For anyone interested in marine biology, climate change impacts, or fisheries management, this article is a must-read. It not only provides a deep dive into the challenges faced by Pacific cod but also highlights the cutting-edge research being conducted to safeguard these vital marine populations. To explore this topic further and understand the intricacies of this crucial research, I highly recommend reading the full article in the CICOES Magazine 2023 issue. <a href="../../img/CICOES.pdf"><em>Read the full article</em></a> <em>below</em> to gain a deeper understanding of the interplay between marine heatwaves and marine life.</p>
<p><object data="/img/CICOES.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="600" height="400"><p>Unable to display PDF file. <a href="../../img/CICOES.pdf">Download</a> instead.</p></object></p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>rna-seq</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-cod/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/cod.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="139" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Clam Gonad RNAseq Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Megan Ewing</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Write up for <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/resources/issues/1748">this github issue</a></p>
<p>Github repo available <a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples">here</a> but each step’s chunk is also linked in workflow write up.</p>
<section id="the-data" class="level1">
<h1>The Data</h1>
<p>The RNA-seq data that was analyzed for this issue was from manila clam (<em>Ruditapes philippinarum</em>) samples of a control and treatment group. There were 15 control samples and 15 treatment samples, each with 2 reads. Each fasta file had the naming scheme <code>M-?-###_R#_001</code> where <code>?</code> = C (control) or T(treatment), <code>###</code> = sample number, and <code>R#</code> = R1 (read 1) or R2 (read 2). Raw files can be found <a href="https://gannet.fish.washington.edu/mewing0/Man_clam_raw/">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-workflow" class="level1">
<h1>The Workflow</h1>
<section id="retrieving-files-from-gannet" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="retrieving-files-from-gannet">Retrieving Files From Gannet</h3>
<p>To start the analysis, I retrieved the raw reads from gannet using wget.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/01-RNAseq.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="checking-file-integrity-via-md5sums" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="checking-file-integrity-via-md5sums">Checking File Integrity via MD5sums</h3>
<p>Typically, the next step would be to check the file integrity by comparing the md5sums of the downloaded files with those on the remote server (gannet). However, the directory containing our reads did not have a text file of the md5sums for me to run <code>md5sum</code> on. So we skipped this step.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/02-md5sums.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="fastqc-and-multiqc" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fastqc-and-multiqc">FastQC and MultiQC</h3>
<p>The next step was to evaluate the quality of our sequences using FastQC and MultiQC. I generated a FastQC file for each of the reads, and then combined all of those using MultiQC to look at the quality of all of our reads together. The MultiQC report can be found <a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/output/fastQC-output/multiqc_report.html">here</a> (note to view the “pretty version” you will need to download the html file and open the local file since github just shows the raw). Here’s some of the results from that:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_sequence_counts_plot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_base_sequence_quality_plot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_sequence_quality_scores_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_sequence_gc_content_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_per_base_n_content_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_sequence_duplication_levels_plot.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc_overrepresented_sequences_plot.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/Screen Shot 2024-01-04 at 3.16.31 PM.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/fastqc-status-check-heatmap.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Software Used:</p>
<ul>
<li>FastQC (v0.12.1)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/03-fastqc_multiqc.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="psuedo-alignment-with-kallisto" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="psuedo-alignment-with-kallisto">Psuedo Alignment with Kallisto</h3>
<p>Next I pseudo aligned the reads and quantified expression using Kallisto. I did not trim prior to this as it is not wholly necessary for pseudo alignment. An index for alignment and quantification was created using a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/datasets/genome/GCF_026571515.1/">reference transcriptome for <em>Ruditapes philippinarum</em></a> (note: ensure to select for RNA file)<em>.</em> Paired end reads for each sample were then aligned and quantified against this index.</p>
<p>Following pseudo alignment and quantification, a trinity matrix was created with the Kallisto output to build an abundance matrix.</p>
<p>Software Used:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Kallisto (Linux)(v0.50.1)</p></li>
<li><p>TrinityRNAseq (v2.12.0)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/05-kallisto.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="differential-expression-and-visualization-with-deseq2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="differential-expression-and-visualization-with-deseq2">Differential Expression and Visualization with DESeq2</h3>
<p>Using the quantification in the trinity matrix created, I ran DESeq2 to show deferentially expressed genes, and filtering for those who’s expression showed a difference with a p value &lt;= 0.05. Differential expression was also visualized via a volcano plot and heatmap of the top 25 deferentially expressed genes)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/volcanoplot-01.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/images/heatmap.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Along with the visualzations, I created a dataframe with the differentially expressed genes and associated statistics (base mean, log 2fold change, lfcSE, stat, pvalue, padj) and saved as a tab file for the next steps.</p>
<p>Software used:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>BiocManager (v1.30.22)</p></li>
<li><p>DESeq2 (v1.38.3)</p></li>
<li><p>pheatmap (v1.0.12)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/06-deseq2.Rmd">Code on GitHub</a></p>
</section>
<section id="identifying-deg-functions-with-blastx" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="identifying-deg-functions-with-blastx">Identifying DEG Functions with Blastx</h3>
<p>Once we had a tab file with differentially expressed genes, we could run blast on our <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/datasets/genome/GCF_026571515.1/">reference genome</a> (note: be sure to select for RNA file). Doing this creates a list of all of the genes (and gene short names) in our reference genome for us to get the names of our DEGs in the next step.</p>
<p>Software used:</p>
<ul>
<li>NCBI Blast (v2.11.0)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/code/07-blast.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="joining-deg-with-blast-results-and-uniprot-gene-ontology-annotations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="joining-deg-with-blast-results-and-uniprot-gene-ontology-annotations">Joining DEG with Blast Results and UniProt Gene Ontology Annotations</h3>
<p>Using the file created from the reference genome Blast, I combined the Blast results with the DEG file by the common gene names. This dataframe contained the gene ID, gene short name, base mean, log 2fold change, pvalue, and padj. I isolated the UniProt IDs from the gene short names in order to retrieve the gene ontology (GO) annotations of interest.</p>
<p>I looked up the annotations on <a href="https://www.uniprot.org/id-mapping">UniProt’s web interface</a> and saved the output as a tab file. Finally, I merged the Blast/DEG data frame with the GO data frame by the common UniProt ID’s/Entries to get a file of our GO annotations for the significantly deferentially expressed genes. The annotation file is available <a href="https://github.com/meganewing/clamgonads-macsamples/blob/main/output/clam_GO_annotations.csv">here</a>.</p>
<p><a href="08-join_annotations.Rmd">Code on Github</a></p>
</section>
<section id="general-non-step-specific-software-and-hardware-info" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-non-step-specific-software-and-hardware-info">General (non-step specific) software and hardware info:</h3>
<p>Computer: 2016 MacBook Pro 8GB 13” with macOS Big Sur (v11.2)</p>
<p>IDE: R Studio (v4.2.3)(via raven)</p>


<!-- -->

</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rnaseq</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>clam</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/megan-rna/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_mewing-notebook_-_Clam_Gonad_RNAseq_Analysis_2024-01-06_07-25-10.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Western Society of Naturalists</title>
  <dc:creator>Grace Leuchtenberger</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/grace_L_WSN/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="poster-presentation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="poster-presentation">Poster presentation</h2>
<p>I presented some data from a summer pilot project that didn’t end up being significant, but sparked some good conversations! Flow rate is known to influence the amount of threads that mussels produce to stick onto rocky surfaces, so I was wondering if it influenced the actual composition of the threads as well! I kept mussels under three different flow rates and measured their attachment strength. Didn’t find anything significant, but saw some trends.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_graceleuchtenberger.github.iopost_images20231122WSN.jpeg_at_master__graceleuchtenbergergraceleuchtenberger.github.io_2023-12-11_14-07-16.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>img</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I haven’t ever presented data in person at a conference before (relic of being a college covid baby), so this was really exciting for me to get feedback from other ecomechanics people and brainstorm future directions for my work, especially as I’m trying to propose my thesis this spring.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>wsn</category>
  <category>meeting</category>
  <category>seastar</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/grace_L_WSN/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_graceleuchtenberger.github.iopost_images20231122WSN.jpeg_at_master__graceleuchtenbergergraceleuchtenberger.github.io_2023-12-11_14-07-16.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Celebrating LGBTQ+ in STEM</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-LGBTQ/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Full Article
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The following is an excerpt from a post on the SAFS Website: <a href="https://fish.uw.edu/2023/11/celebrating-lgbtq-in-stem" class="uri">https://fish.uw.edu/2023/11/celebrating-lgbtq-in-stem</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Celebrating and highlighting the work of LGBTQ+ people in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) has a special day on the calendar: November 18. Why this date? It is based on the 60<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;anniversary of American Astronomer and gay activist Frank Kameny’s fight against workplace discrimination, which he took to the U.S. Supreme Court.</p>
<p><img src="https://fish.uw.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/29/2023/11/LGBTQ-in-STEM-528x276.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt=""></p>
<p>Science is a place of innovation, research, and progress, but many communities are still marginalized in these spaces.&nbsp;<a href="https://prideinstem.org/lgbtstemday/">Pride in STEM</a> notes that 28% of LGBT+ people have considered leaving their jobs because of discrimination or workplace hostility.</p>
<p>On&nbsp;<a href="https://prideinstem.org/lgbtstemday">LGBTQ+ in STEM Day</a>, we celebrate the contribution of LGBTQ+ scientists, while also recognizing that barriers are still faced and that efforts have to continue to break these down. We spoke with SAFS graduate student, Aspen Coyle, who shared her thoughts on her journey so far in academia, what inclusion means for her, and some of the barriers and highlights she’s experienced. She also shares some advice for those concerned about a lack of representation in marine science.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
More information
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><em>For more information on Diversity, Equity and Inclusion activities and support at SAFS, visit our&nbsp;<a href="https://fish.uw.edu/about/diversity-equity-and-inclusion/">DEI page</a>.&nbsp;For UW-wide resources, visit&nbsp;<a href="https://sites.uw.edu/qcenter">The Q Center</a>.</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="what-led-you-to-pursue-studies-in-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-led-you-to-pursue-studies-in-science"><strong>What led you to pursue studies in science?</strong></h2>
<p><img src="https://fish.uw.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/29/2023/10/Aspen_selfie-259x528.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt=""></p>
<p>I’m one of those people that’s wanted to be a marine biologist ever since I was a little kid. I grew up in a fishing town in coastal Alaska, and my favorite thing in the world was scrambling along the intertidal, peering into tidepools and turning over rocks, trying to find the neatest critters. That base delight in hunting for cool creatures was augmented in undergrad with a deeper understanding of the ecological importance, and then after getting a job in another Alaskan fishing town, the economic importance.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-some-of-the-positive-experiences-as-lgbtq-in-stem-that-youve-had" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-some-of-the-positive-experiences-as-lgbtq-in-stem-that-youve-had"><strong>What are some of the positive experiences as LGBTQ+ in STEM that you’ve had?</strong></h2>
<p>From an outside perspective, I’ve existed in several different modes as a queer person in STEM – up until recently as a queer guy, and for the last six months or so as a transfemme. Before grad school, I was working for the Alaska Department of Fish and Game in a variety of fieldwork positions. Being queer in rural Alaska, especially around the fishing industry, is often met with confusion (and occasionally, mild hostility), but I never felt much of that from my coworkers.</p>
<p>Here at SAFS, my lab is mostly other queer people, which has been wonderful. When I was living as a queer guy, it was really great to have a bunch of people around with this shared experience and perspective. And since queer cis people are usually around more trans people than straight cis people, it really wasn’t that big of a deal when I started transitioning.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-does-inclusion-look-like-for-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-does-inclusion-look-like-for-you"><strong>What does inclusion look like for you?</strong></h2>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Full Article
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>To <em>see the answer to this and other questions read the full article at</em> <a href="https://fish.uw.edu/2023/11/celebrating-lgbtq-in-stem" class="uri">https://fish.uw.edu/2023/11/celebrating-lgbtq-in-stem</a></p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>LGBTQ+</category>
  <category>diversity</category>
  <category>inclusion</category>
  <category>dei</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-LGBTQ/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://fish.uw.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/29/2023/11/LGBTQ-in-STEM.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Western Society of Naturalists</title>
  <dc:creator>Grace Crandall</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/grace-ac-WSN/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Had an amazing week last week! See post for details!</p>
<section id="eelgrass-workshop" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="eelgrass-workshop">Eelgrass Workshop</h2>
<p>For the past year+ I’ve been fortunate to be part of an awesome team of folks working on an NSF Grant studying Eelgrass Wasting Disease, mostly centered in the Puget Sound/San Juan Islands, but also spanning along the West Coast. We had a great workshop pre-WSN where we chatted about the various aspects of the grant that folks have been working on and made plans and outlines for writing up the various projects. It was a great time and I’m looking forward to all the cool stuff coming up - keep an eye out!</p>
<p>Here’s the team!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://github.com/grace-ac/grace-ac.github.io/raw/master/notebook-images/2023-11-15-wsn-recap/IMG_1750.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>img</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Lindsay Alma, Dr.&nbsp;Colleen Burge, Dr.&nbsp;Drew Harvell, Dr.&nbsp;Eileen Hoffman, Dr.&nbsp;Maya Groner, Me, Dr.&nbsp;Becca Maher, and Dr.&nbsp;Olivia Graham!</p>
</section>
<section id="wsn-monterey-ca" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wsn-monterey-ca">WSN, Monterey, CA</h2>
<p>I haven’t been to a conference since the Alaska Marine Science Symposium in Anchorage, AK, January 2020… so it was a little nerve-wracking to head to my first one in so long! It was amazing, though! So much cool science, so many interesting and engaging talks and posters, and I had so much fun. Made some new connections that I’m excited to foster.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Olivia Graham did an amazing job putting together THREE Marine Disease Ecology sessions!! There were two sessions on Saturday - an eelgrass session during which a lot of the team pictured in the above section presented amazing work, and a miscellaneous section that had some great talks as well.</p>
<p>I was part of the Sunday morning session that was all about <em>Pycnopodia helianthoides</em>! Below is a photo of everyone who presented. My talk went well - I ended up getting Honorable Mention for it!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://github.com/grace-ac/grace-ac.github.io/raw/master/notebook-images/2023-11-15-wsn-recap/IMG_1970.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>img</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Lauren Schiebelhut, Dr.&nbsp;Jason Hodin, Dr.&nbsp;Alyssa Gehman, Me, Dr.&nbsp;Melanie Prentice, Tiffany Rudek, Dr.&nbsp;Drew Harvell, and Dr.&nbsp;Olivia Graham.</p>
<p>For fun, here’s a pretty photo of one of our adult <em>Pycnopodia helianthoides</em> from our Summer 2021 work that made many appearances in my talk:<br>
<img src="https://github.com/grace-ac/grace-ac.github.io/raw/master/notebook-images/2023-11-15-wsn-recap/IMG_3951.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="img"></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>wsn</category>
  <category>meeting</category>
  <category>seastar</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/grace-ac-WSN/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://github.com/grace-ac/grace-ac.github.io/raw/master/notebook-images/2023-11-15-wsn-recap/IMG_1750.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Insights from Pacific Oysters in a Heating Ocean</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-DM/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a recent <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16980">commentary by Donal T. Manahan</a>, the magnified effects of marine heatwaves on the mortality of triploid Pacific oysters have been thrust into the spotlight, underscoring the urgent need for deeper understanding of marine life’s tolerance to heat stress. Manahan’s piece, a commentary <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16880">our recent work led by Matt George</a>, delves into the realm where climate change meets marine biology and aquaculture.</p>
<section id="the-rising-heat-and-its-victims" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-rising-heat-and-its-victims">The Rising Heat and Its Victims</h2>
<p>The context is alarming: with ocean temperatures breaking records and coastal heatwaves causing mass marine mortality, researchers like Manahan stress the importance of grasping how different organisms will survive in this changing environment. The Pacific Northwest, as noted by White et al.&nbsp;(2023), has witnessed temperatures soaring to nearly 50°C, resulting in the death of over a million bivalve mussels in a mere 100-meter stretch.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-pacific-oyster-at-the-heart-of-study" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-pacific-oyster-at-the-heart-of-study">The Pacific Oyster at the Heart of Study</h2>
<p>Matt’s study, referenced by Manahan, brings under scrutiny the Pacific oyster, Crassostrea gigas, an organism of commercial significance and genetic interest. Their work dissects the responses of diploid and triploid oysters to heatwaves, revealing that the mortality rate among triploid oysters was 2.5 times higher than their diploid counterparts.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-triploid-dilemma" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-triploid-dilemma">A Triploid Dilemma</h2>
<p>Triploid oysters, engineered for their superior growth and yield, seem to face greater peril under thermal stress. Manahan points out that these oysters show signs of metabolic depression, reduced ATP production, and a slump in essential biological processes like glucose metabolism and immunity responses. This finding poses serious implications for aquaculture, as triploids are widely cultivated for food production.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-challenge-of-predicting-phenotypes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge-of-predicting-phenotypes">The Challenge of Predicting Phenotypes</h2>
<p>Manahan underscores a crucial challenge in marine biology: the prediction of phenotypes from gene expression. The commentary reflects on how data from different biological levels may not always align, and he calls for a cautious interpretation of such analyses. Integrative approaches are necessary for a comprehensive understanding of how organisms function and respond to environmental stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="energy-allocation-and-the-cost-of-reproduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="energy-allocation-and-the-cost-of-reproduction">Energy Allocation and the Cost of Reproduction</h2>
<p>The commentary also touches upon the energetic cost of being a triploid organism. With triploids being functionally sterile, Manahan questions whether there’s an unaccounted metabolic cost involved in maintaining redundant biosynthetic pathways.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-path-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-path-forward">A Path Forward</h2>
<p>Manahan highlights the value of multi-year, trans-generational breeding programs and commends the collaborative efforts exemplified by the team behind our study. Such partnerships across universities, governments, and industry are vital for sustained research and for breeding marine species that can withstand the pressures of climate change.</p>
<p>In summary, Manahan’s commentary not only sheds light on the specific challenges faced by triploid Pacific oysters under heat stress but also casts a wider net on the complexities of studying marine life’s response to a warming world. The findings are a crucial piece of the puzzle in our pursuit of sustainable “Blue Food” production and the broader understanding of marine ecosystem resilience.</p>
<p>Citation: Manahan, D. T. (2023). Marine heatwaves impact mortality of triploid Pacific oysters. Global Change Biology. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16980" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16980</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>triploid</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-DM/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_ChatGPT_2023-11-04_14-59-20.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AquaMine</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/aquamine/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="aquamine-a-treasure-trove-for-aquatic-genomics-research" class="level1">
<h1><strong>AquaMine: A Treasure Trove for Aquatic Genomics Research</strong></h1>
<p>Aquatic species are not just fascinating creatures of the deep; they are vital to the balance of our ecosystems and the prosperity of our aquaculture industries. As the demand for sustainable aquaculture and fisheries practices increases, so does the necessity for advanced research and development. Enter <a href="https://aquamine.elsiklab.missouri.edu">AquaMine</a>—a cutting-edge data mining system poised to revolutionize aquatic eumetazoan research by integrating genome assemblies and gene annotation data. This powerful tool is designed to empower researchers, enabling the creation of customized datasets that can be integrated with their own data. Here’s a closer look at AquaMine and its plethora of features.</p>
<section id="a-platform-with-immense-potential" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-platform-with-immense-potential"><strong>A Platform with Immense Potential</strong></h2>
<p>Built on the robust InterMine genomic data mining platform, AquaMine is a testament to the power of bioinformatics in modern research. The web application component of AquaMine boasts an impressive array of search tools tailored to the needs of researchers:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>A simple key word search for straightforward inquiries</p></li>
<li><p>Predefined template queries to streamline the research process</p></li>
<li><p>A QueryBuilder Tool that offers flexibility for crafting custom queries</p></li>
<li><p>A Regions Search Tool for those who require coordinate-based queries</p></li>
<li><p>A List Tool that allows for uploading and searching with lists of identifiers</p></li>
</ul>
<p>These features not only enhance the user experience but also optimize the research workflow, leading to more efficient and effective studies.</p>
</section>
<section id="aquamine-v1.2-whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="aquamine-v1.2-whats-new"><strong>AquaMine v1.2: What’s New?</strong></h2>
<p>The latest iteration, AquaMine v1.2, houses the genomic gold of 37 aquatic species that are of paramount importance to the US aquaculture and fisheries. This includes, but is not limited to, species such as the Arctic char, Atlantic salmon, channel catfish, and the Pacific white shrimp. AquaMine doesn’t stop there; it ensures that the annotation data for these species is comprehensive, including resources from RefSeq genes, Ensembl, KEGG, UniProt, Gene Ontology (GO), PubMed, and OrthoDB.</p>
<p>Moreover, the inclusion of genes from human, fruit fly, owl limpet, and zebrafish allows researchers to leverage model organism information through orthology, offering a broader perspective and facilitating comparative studies.</p>
</section>
<section id="enhancing-genetic-insight-with-aquamine-ortho-and-go-annotations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="enhancing-genetic-insight-with-aquamine-ortho-and-go-annotations"><strong>Enhancing Genetic Insight with AquaMine-Ortho and GO Annotations</strong></h2>
<p>AquaMine-Ortho, a precomputed orthology dataset within AquaMine v1.2, spans all included species and fills gaps not covered by databases like OrthoDB or Ensembl. The addition of a comprehensive GO annotation dataset for all species is another feather in AquaMine’s cap, providing a rich resource for gene enrichment analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="beyond-genomes-variants-and-expression-levels" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="beyond-genomes-variants-and-expression-levels"><strong>Beyond Genomes: Variants and Expression Levels</strong></h2>
<p>Staying true to its vision of comprehensive data provision, AquaMine v1.2 also introduces new genomic variant data from the Ensembl Variation Archive and extends its resources to include RNA-seq-based gene expression levels for selected species, offering a deeper understanding of genetic function and regulation.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-future-is-interactive-jbrowse-genome-browsers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-future-is-interactive-jbrowse-genome-browsers"><strong>The Future is Interactive: JBrowse Genome Browsers</strong></h2>
<p>AquaMine’s development team is tirelessly working to further enhance user interaction with genomic data. The introduction of new JBrowse genome browsers equipped with Apollo manual genome annotation tools for aquaculture species is on the horizon. This feature promises to offer an even more hands-on approach to genomic data navigation and analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-call-to-action-for-researchers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-call-to-action-for-researchers"><strong>A Call to Action for Researchers</strong></h2>
<p>The ongoing development of AquaMine underscores a collaborative spirit, as the team calls upon researchers to participate as beta-testers. This invitation to provide feedback is not merely a request for quality assurance but a rallying cry for the scientific community to shape a tool that reflects their needs and aspirations.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>
<p>AquaMine v1.2 is more than a mere database—it’s a beacon for aquaculture and fisheries research, guiding the way towards a more informed and sustainable management of aquatic resources. With its comprehensive datasets, versatile tools, and forward-thinking enhancements, AquaMine is set to become an indispensable ally for researchers and industry professionals alike. Dive into AquaMine, and surface with the insights needed to keep our waters teeming with life for generations to come.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/aquamine/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_ChatGPT_2023-11-04_15-16-26.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MarineOmics.io</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-marineomics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In an era where ecological genomics is garnering increased recognition, particularly within nonmodel species, the necessity for robust, reproducible, and accessible resources has never been more apparent. A <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14219">recent publication</a> led by a consortium of researchers introduces <a href="MarineOmics.io">MarineOmics.io</a>, a dynamic web resource tailored to meet the burgeoning needs of this scientific domain. This open-source platform aims to foster a collaborative environment for researchers at various stages of their career, promoting reproducibility, accessibility, and adaptability in genomic analyses.</p>
<p>MarineOmics.io emerges as a living document, meticulously curated to disseminate vital tutorials, reproducibility tools, and best principles pivotal for genomic research in marine and other nonmodel ecosystems. This endeavor is a testament to the collaborative spirit of the ecological genomics community, as the platform encapsulates current methodologies and recommendations across a myriad of genomic studies including whole-genome sequencing, RAD-seq, Pool-seq, and RNA-seq.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_17823668.pdf_2023-10-09_05-52-35.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>F I G U R E 1 Screenshot of one web page concerning a RAD-seq pipeline serving as an example of tutorial structure.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>What sets MarineOmics.io apart is its dynamic nature. Not only does it provide a repository of existing knowledge, but it also outlines a structured process for the aggregation and synthesis of methodological principles derived from the community. The platform invites submissions of new content, feedback, and topic requests from the community, thereby ensuring its content remains updated, relevant, and in tune with the rapidly evolving field of genomics.</p>
<p>The meticulous planning invested in MarineOmics.io is reflective in its guidelines for authorship, submission of new content, and protocols for community feedback. These guidelines are drafted with a vision to uphold the rigor and reproducibility in scientific inquiries, encouraging contributions from scientists spanning various skill sets and expertise levels. This collaborative ethos is further underscored by the availability of the site’s source code for contributors on GitHub, and a snapshot of the source code as of the time of submission, hosted on Zenodo.</p>
<p>The data and resources available through MarineOmics.io are not merely a contribution but a cornerstone for advancing ecological genomic research in nonmodel marine systems. By providing a structured, collaborative platform, MarineOmics.io is poised to catalyze a new wave of discoveries, fostering a community of researchers equipped to navigate the challenges and opportunities that lay ahead in the genomic era.</p>
<p>Citation: Bogan, S. N., Johns, J., Griffiths, J. S., Davenport, D., Smith, S. J., Schaal, S. M., Downey-Wall, A., Lou, R. N., Lotterhos, K., Guidry, M. E., Rivera, H. E., McGirr, J. A., Puritz, J. B., Roberts, S. B., &amp; Silliman, K. (2023). A dynamic web resource for robust and reproducible genomics in nonmodel species: marineomics.io. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 00, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14219</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>paper</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-marineomics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/img/marineomics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unveiling the Blueprints of the Sea</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/mytilus-genome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="unveiling-the-blueprints-of-the-sea-the-genome-of-mytilus-chilensis" class="level1">
<h1>Unveiling the Blueprints of the Sea: The Genome of Mytilus chilensis</h1>
<p>The blue mussel, Mytilus chilensis, is not only a delicacy on dinner plates but also a cornerstone of the booming aquaculture industry along the southern coast of Chile. Its iridescent shells and robust nature make it a favorite, but beneath the waves, this bivalve is locked in a constant battle against environmental stressors, diseases, and the effects of pollution. The secret to its resilience lies in its genetic code, a treasure trove of information until now largely uncharted.</p>
<section id="a-genomic-milestone" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-genomic-milestone">A Genomic Milestone</h2>
<p>In a groundbreaking study, researchers have presented the first chromosome-level genome assembly for a Mytilidae family member in South America. This scientific feat, detailed in a recent publication, offers a high-quality reference genome for M. chilensis. It’s a leap forward in our understanding of this species, providing a detailed map of the genetic factors that contribute to its survival and adaptation in a changing marine environment.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-genome-matters" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-genome-matters">Why Genome Matters?</h2>
<p>Imagine having a detailed instruction manual for building and maintaining an organism, one that could tell you how it can survive freezing waters, resist certain pathogens, or how it might react to the shifting chemistry of its habitat. That’s what a genome assembly provides. For aquaculture, this information is invaluable. It can lead to the development of hardier mussel strains, inform conservation efforts, and enhance the industry’s sustainability.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-economic-and-ecological-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-economic-and-ecological-impact">The Economic and Ecological Impact</h2>
<p>The aquaculture industry relies heavily on mussel farming, but it’s an enterprise not without its risks. With seeds collected from natural beds and translocated to varied farming conditions, the industry has been seeking ways to reduce losses and improve yields. The newly unveiled genome paves the way for breeding programs that can select for desirable traits, such as disease resistance or faster growth rates, potentially revolutionizing mussel farming.</p>
</section>
<section id="beyond-the-economic-horizon" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="beyond-the-economic-horizon">Beyond the Economic Horizon</h2>
<p>But the implications of this research extend beyond the realm of economics. Mussels serve as a filter for the ocean, playing a critical role in maintaining the health of marine ecosystems. Understanding their genetic makeup helps us appreciate not only how they contribute to their environment but also how they might be affected by our actions—be it through climate change or pollution.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>The journey of understanding Mytilus chilensis at the genomic level is just beginning. This initial assembly is a scaffold for future discoveries, a reference for comparative genomics, and a baseline for monitoring the genetic health of populations. As scientists continue to unravel the mysteries locked in its DNA, we move closer to a future where the blue mussel can continue to thrive, both as a species and an industry.</p>
<p>The study in discussion is not just a scientific achievement; it’s a testament to the intricate dance of life adapted to the ebb and flow of the sea. As we delve into the genome of Mytilus chilensis, we’re reminded of the resilience of life and the ingenuity of those who seek to understand and preserve it. The blueprints of the sea are laid bare, and with them, a new chapter in sustainable aquaculture beckons.</p>
<p>CITATION: Gallardo-Escárate, C.; Valenzuela-Muñoz, V.; Nuñez-Acuña, G.; Valenzuela-Miranda, D.; Tapia, F.J.; Yévenes, M.; Gajardo, G.; Toro, J.E.; Oyarzún, P.A.; Arriagada, G.; et al.&nbsp;Chromosome-Level Genome Assembly of the Blue Mussel Mytilus chilensis Reveals Molecular Signatures Facing the Marine Environment. Genes 2023, 14, 876. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes14040876" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.3390/genes14040876</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>mussel</category>
  <category>genome</category>
  <category>Chile</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/mytilus-genome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_ChatGPT_2023-11-04_15-08-02.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Marine science mentoring over the summer at FHL</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-fhl/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is an excerpt from a feature on the SAFS website. Please read the full article <a href="https://fish.uw.edu/2023/09/marine-science-mentoring-over-the-summer-at-fhl/">here</a>.</p>
<section id="marine-science-mentoring-over-the-summer-at-fhl" class="level1">
<h1>Marine science mentoring over the summer at FHL</h1>
<p>Spending the summer at&nbsp;<a href="https://fhl.uw.edu/">Friday Harbor Labs</a>&nbsp;(FHL), SAFS grad student <a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/people.html#chris-mantegna">Chris Mantegna</a> mentored four students – two as part of the NSF-funded&nbsp;<a href="https://fhl.uw.edu/research/summer-research-internships/">Research Experience for Undergrads-Blinks</a>&nbsp;(REU) program and two as part of the&nbsp;<a href="http://uwconservationscholars.org/">Doris Duke Conservation Scholars Program</a>&nbsp;(DDCSP). During the program, students get to collaborate on a research project with their scientist-mentor to build marine research skills.</p>
<p>Specifically geared towards enhancing diversity within the marine sciences, the program welcomes students from underrepresented groups. This year, Chris’ students came from institutions across the US, including Kentucky, Massachusetts, Vermont and North Carolina, to work with her on an intertidal monitoring survey on Yellow Island in the Salish Sea.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://fish.uw.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/29/2023/09/IMG_2457.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Ochre sea stars (Pisaster ocherous) found on the island at low tide.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The REU-Blinks program based out of FHL takes advantage of the pristine environment, remarkable biodiversity, and the scientific and technical resources available at the marine science research facility. The DDCSP program aims to increase diversity in conservation work and allows students from all over the US a chance to participate in a two-year program where second year scholars participate in an onsite internship of their choosing.</p>
<p>Yellow Island is a nature preserve that The Nature Conservancy purchased in 1980, that also doubles up as a marine reserve, with no boating or fishing allowed within 300 yards of the island. The island is being used by Chris and the research team as a proxy for health in the wider Salish Sea due to the lack of human disturbance.</p>
<p>As part of a wider program sponsored by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.blackinmarinescience.org/">Black In Marine Science</a>(BIMS) and The Nature Conservancy, Chris restarted a monitoring project to get a better idea of the biodiversity on the island, and this kicked off last year in 2022 with a pilot program nailing down methods for collecting data. This year, with her mentees, the team collected a full season of data, complemented with eDNA work.</p>
<p>continue reading <a href="https://fish.uw.edu/2023/09/marine-science-mentoring-over-the-summer-at-fhl/">here</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>fhl</category>
  <category>mentoring</category>
  <category>spotlight</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-fhl/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://fish.uw.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/29/2023/09/IMG_2415.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Uncovering Population-specific Resilience to Ocean Acidification in the Olympia Oyster</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-spencer-paper/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="a-deep-dive-into-our-latest-publication" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-deep-dive-into-our-latest-publication">A Deep Dive into Our Latest Publication</h2>
<p>We are thrilled to share our latest research paper, “Population-specific effects of ocean acidification in the Olympia oyster,” authored by Laura H Spencer, Steven B Roberts, and Katherine Silliman. The study has recently been published in bioRxiv and sheds light on the mechanisms underlying population-specific responses of Olympia oysters (Ostrea lurida) to ocean acidification. This research is groundbreaking in illustrating how different populations of the same species can exhibit varying levels of resilience to environmental stressors like acidification, a crucial factor for both conservation and marine food system sustainability.</p>
<section id="the-issue-at-hand-ocean-acidification" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-issue-at-hand-ocean-acidification">The Issue at Hand: Ocean Acidification</h3>
<p>Ocean acidification is a growing concern that is having a detrimental impact on marine ecosystems globally. The increased levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere are dissolving into our oceans, lowering their pH levels. Marine organisms like oysters are particularly vulnerable to such changes, as they rely on carbonate ions to build their shells. Understanding how different populations of marine species respond to this issue is key for effective conservation strategies and sustainable marine food systems.</p>
</section>
<section id="objectives-and-methods" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="objectives-and-methods">Objectives and Methods</h3>
<p>The study focused on three phenotypically distinct populations of Olympia oysters from Dabob Bay, Fidalgo Bay, and Oyster Bay, bred and reared in common conditions over four years. The team assessed various aspects such as growth, reproductive development, and transcriptional responses to ocean acidification within and across these populations.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-findings" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings">Key Findings</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Dabob Bay Population</strong>: Exhibited the slowest growth but had high survival rates. This population also mounted the largest transcriptional response to acidification without affecting its growth and reproduction.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fidalgo Bay Population</strong>: Exhibited the fastest growth rate but had the lowest fecundity. This population showed a moderate transcriptional response to acidification.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Oyster Bay Population</strong>: Had the highest fecundity but the lowest survival rates. Interestingly, this population did not respond at the transcript level and was the only group where acidification negatively affected growth and reproductive development.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Next Generation Impact</strong>: Acidification did not affect gene expression in the larval stage for any population, although the Oyster Bay population produced larger larvae, which might partly mitigate the negative effects of acidification.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="why-this-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h3>
<p>The findings are revolutionary for several reasons:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Conservation Implications</strong>: Populations with distinct resilience levels offer natural reservoirs of biodiversity that can be targeted for conservation efforts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Food System Sustainability</strong>: Understanding population-specific traits can help in developing more resilient aquaculture practices.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Genetic Insights</strong>: The study identified specific genes in the Dabob Bay population related to antibacterial and antiviral processes, metabolism, growth, and reproduction, providing crucial clues into the mechanisms of stress tolerance.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Microscale Variability</strong>: The research underscores that distinct physiotypes can exist among marine invertebrate populations even on small geographic scales, which has far-reaching implications for species resilience to environmental stressors.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="moving-forward" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="moving-forward">Moving Forward</h3>
<p>The research paves the way for future studies that can focus on leveraging these population-specific responses for the betterment of marine ecosystems and human needs. The identified genetic markers can also be used in selective breeding programs to improve resilience against ocean acidification.</p>
<section id="citation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h4>
<p>Laura H Spencer, Steven B Roberts, Katherine Silliman, “Population-specific effects of ocean acidification in the Olympia oyster,” bioRxiv 2023.09.08.556443; <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.08.556443">doi: 10.1101/2023.09.08.556443</a></p>
<p>Feel free to dive into the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.08.556443">full paper</a> for a more detailed understanding of our findings.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>paper</category>
  <category>acidication</category>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>ostrea</category>
  <category>tag-seq</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-spencer-paper/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/httpswww.biorxiv.orgcontent10.11012023.09.08.556443v1.full.pdf_2023-09-14_12-56-48.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
