<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Building Resilient Oysters: Launching the SORMI Project</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sormi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are excited to share that our proposal, <em>Development of SORMI (Summer Oyster Resilience and Mortality Index): A Quantitative Tool for Improving Field Survival</em>, has been funded through the Western Regional Aquaculture Center. This multi-institutional effort will address one of the most pressing challenges in shellfish aquaculture—<strong>recurrent summer mortality in Pacific oysters</strong>.</p>
<section id="the-challenge" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge"><strong>The Challenge</strong></h3>
<p>For decades, oyster growers across the West Coast have faced sudden, large-scale summer die-offs linked to rising seawater temperatures, disease, and other stressors. These events threaten farm productivity and the economic stability of the shellfish industry. Despite years of research, a single cause has never been identified. Instead, we are taking a new approach: focusing on why oysters survive rather than why they die.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-sormi" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-sormi"><strong>What Is SORMI?</strong></h3>
<p>SORMI—the <em>Summer Oyster Resilience and Mortality Index</em>—will be a <strong>generalized stress resilience index</strong> for Pacific oysters. By integrating a suite of physiological and metabolic assays, the index will help predict which oyster families are most resilient under real-world conditions. This tool will directly support breeding programs and hatcheries, providing a practical way to select for survival and reduce the frequency of catastrophic summer mortality events .</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-35-37.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="our-role-at-uw" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-role-at-uw"><strong>Our Role at UW</strong></h3>
<p>At the Roberts Lab, our team will be leading development of innovative, high-throughput stress assays, including a new <a href="http://oyster.pink"><strong>resazurin-based metabolic assay</strong></a> we have been refining as a cost-effective, scalable way to measure oyster metabolism. We will also work closely with partners to analyze stress resilience across hundreds of oyster families and link these traits to field survival outcomes. Our focus is on providing growers and breeding programs with actionable, science-based tools that are accessible and easy to implement.</p>
</section>
<section id="project-leadership-and-partners" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="project-leadership-and-partners"><strong>Project Leadership and Partners</strong></h3>
<p>This project is led by <strong>Bobbi Hudson</strong>, Executive Director of the <strong>Pacific Shellfish Institute (PSI)</strong>. The collaborative team brings together expertise and resources from across the region, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>University of Washington (Roberts Lab)</strong> – stress physiology and assay development</p></li>
<li><p><strong>USDA Agricultural Research Service (Neil Thompson, Pacific Oyster Genomic Selection project)</strong> – breeding program integration and genetic analysis</p></li>
<li><p><strong>NOAA Fisheries (Mackenzie Gavery)</strong> – environmental physiology and genomics</p></li>
<li><p><strong>California Sea Grant (Kevin Johnson, Cal Poly)</strong> – aquaculture extension and grower engagement</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Industry partners</strong> – Goose Point Oyster Company (WA) and Hog Island Oyster Company (CA)</p></li>
</ul>
<p>This broad coalition ensures the project is grounded in industry needs while pushing forward fundamental science .</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-36-23.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="implications-for-the-shellfish-industry" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-for-the-shellfish-industry"><strong>Implications for the Shellfish Industry</strong></h3>
<p>The ultimate goal of SORMI is to give oyster growers a <strong>practical decision-making tool</strong>. With a reliable index, farmers could anticipate when their stocks are stressed and take proactive measures—harvesting before a mortality event, adjusting management practices, or prioritizing resilient broodstock. For breeding programs, SORMI will add a measurable, heritable trait that can accelerate development of hardier oyster lines.</p>
<p>In short, this project will help secure the future of West Coast oyster farming by <strong>turning science into survival.</strong></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sormi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_SR_PSI_WRAC_2025_Full_Proposal_Draft_2025-09-06_06-42-09.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scientific Breakthrough in Sustainable Aquaculture</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sablefish/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As global demand for seafood continues to rise, the aquaculture industry faces growing pressure to produce more while minimizing ecological impacts. A key concern in marine fish farming is the risk of escapees interbreeding with wild populations, leading to genetic introgression and reduced fitness in native fish stocks. Now, a recent study led by former University of Washington CICOES postdoctoral researcher Dr.&nbsp;Yuzo R. Yanagitsuru offers a promising solution.</p>
<p>Published in <em>Aquaculture</em>, the study presents a <strong>proof-of-concept for a non-GMO, bath immersion–based technique for inducing sterility in sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria)</strong>—an emerging high-value aquaculture species also known as black cod. The approach targets a gene essential for reproductive cell development and aims to prevent escaped farmed fish from reproducing in the wild.</p>
<section id="a-scalable-gene-silencing-alternative-to-triploidy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-scalable-gene-silencing-alternative-to-triploidy"><strong>A Scalable, Gene-Silencing Alternative to Triploidy</strong></h3>
<p>While triploidization and genetic modification have been explored for sterility induction, both come with drawbacks—triploid fish can still be partially fertile, and GM fish face regulatory and public acceptance hurdles.</p>
<p>Instead, Dr.&nbsp;Yanagitsuru and collaborators used a <strong>Morpholino oligomer (MO)</strong> attached to a <strong>Vivo transporter</strong> to silence the <em>dead end</em> (<em>dnd</em>) gene—a critical regulator of primordial germ cell formation. The innovation lies in delivering this compound through a <strong>simple bath immersion</strong>, rather than invasive microinjection or genetic alteration.</p>
</section>
<section id="results-a-step-toward-sterile-sustainable-farming" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results-a-step-toward-sterile-sustainable-farming"><strong>Results: A Step Toward Sterile, Sustainable Farming</strong></h3>
<p>In controlled hatchery trials, sablefish eggs treated with the dnd-MO-Vivo compound before fertilization produced a subset of individuals that were completely sterile (8%) or had drastically reduced numbers of reproductive cells (18%). Importantly, sterile individuals developed normally in all other respects: they showed no major differences in growth, sex steroid hormone levels, or survival under semi-commercial rearing conditions.</p>
<p>Key findings include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Target specificity</strong>: dnd expression was limited to gonads and unfertilized eggs, confirming its value as a marker for germ cell presence.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>No adverse health effects</strong>: Sterile fish were physiologically indistinguishable from fertile fish in terms of somatic growth and overall condition.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Higher efficacy pre-fertilization</strong>: The sterility induction was more effective when the treatment was applied before fertilization, likely due to increased permeability of the egg chorion.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="why-it-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-it-matters"><strong>Why It Matters</strong></h3>
<p>This method opens a new path for <strong>scalable, publicly acceptable sterility induction in marine finfish aquaculture</strong>. By eliminating the reproductive capability of escapees, it reduces ecological risk and helps safeguard the genetic integrity of wild populations—while also offering potential gains in growth efficiency and product quality for farmers.</p>
<p>Sablefish, already known for its rich flavor and high omega-3 content, now also stands to become a model species for innovative, sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next"><strong>What’s Next?</strong></h3>
<p>The authors emphasize that <strong>further optimization is needed</strong> to improve sterility rates and ensure consistent results across large-scale operations. Future research will likely explore different concentrations, immersion times, and additional species to assess broader applicability.</p>
<p>But for now, this work—driven by Dr.&nbsp;Yanagitsuru’s leadership—marks an important milestone in the development of non-GMO solutions to one of aquaculture’s biggest challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Citation</strong>:</p>
<p>Yanagitsuru, Y.R., Hayman, E.S., Fairgrieve, W.T., Zohar, Y., Wong, T-T., &amp; Luckenbach, J.A. (2025). <em>Proof-of-concept for sterility induction in sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria) via a scalable immersion-based gene silencing approach</em>. <em>Aquaculture</em>, 609, 742945. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2025.742945" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2025.742945</a></p>
<p>Podcast Episode featuring work: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/gene-pooling/id1802677296?i=1000718173868" class="uri">https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/gene-pooling/id1802677296?i=1000718173868</a></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>sterility</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-sablefish/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Yanagitsuru_et_al_SterilityInduction_dnd_BathImmersion_SablefishProofOfConcept_2025.pdf_2025-07-20_13-09-45.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Celebrating Undergraduate Research</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-capstone/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This spring, two outstanding undergraduate researchers in our lab—Genevieve Buchanan and Henry Berg—presented their senior capstone projects, showcasing months of hard work and scientific curiosity. Their research tackled critical questions related to marine invertebrate resilience in the face of environmental stress, and each presentation offered fresh insight into how shellfish species respond to changing ocean conditions.</p>
<section id="genevieve-buchanan-thermal-tolerance-in-a-stressful-world" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="genevieve-buchanan-thermal-tolerance-in-a-stressful-world">🦪 Genevieve Buchanan: Thermal Tolerance in a Stressful World</h2>
<p>Genevieve’s project, “Effects of Salinity and Ocean Acidification Stress on Pacific Oyster (Magallana gigas) Thermal Tolerance”, examined how prior exposure to low salinity and acidic conditions influences oyster survival during subsequent heat stress. Pacific oysters are economically vital to aquaculture industries and ecologically foundational to coastal ecosystems, yet they face increasing threats from climate change-induced stressors.</p>
<p>Through a carefully controlled experiment using oysters from the Point Whitney Shellfish Hatchery, Genevieve tested whether low pH or reduced salinity exposure would compound mortality under acute thermal stress. Her findings showed that, surprisingly, these prior stressors did not significantly impact thermal tolerance. This suggests that Pacific oysters may be energetically adapted to the variable conditions of the Pacific Northwest, offering a glimmer of hope for aquaculture resilience in the face of climate extremes.</p>
<p>🔗 <a href="https://youtu.be/4Yz1z1yZRGQ">Watch Genevieve’s full presentation on YouTube</a></p>
<p>📄 <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Genevieve_Buchanan_-_Capstone_Presentation.pptx">Download Genevieve’s Presentation Slides (PPTX)</a></p>
<p>⸻</p>
</section>
<section id="henry-berg-mussel-threads-and-climate-stress" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="henry-berg-mussel-threads-and-climate-stress">🧵 Henry Berg: Mussel Threads and Climate Stress</h2>
<p>Henry’s capstone, “Physiological Markers Associated with Byssus Attachment Following Environmental Perturbations in Marine Mussels”, focused on the byssal threads that mussels use to anchor themselves to surfaces—an essential trait for survival and aquaculture yield.</p>
<p>Comparing Mytilus trossulus and Mytilus galloprovincialis, Henry exposed mussels to ocean acidification, warming, and hypoxia, then measured thread production and metabolic rates. His results were striking: ocean acidification increased thread production in both species, while warming favored M. galloprovincialis. Hypoxia, however, drastically reduced thread output, particularly in M. galloprovincialis. These species-specific responses highlight the complexity of climate resilience and point to potential physiological markers that could inform aquaculture site selection and selective breeding strategies.</p>
<p>🔗 <a href="https://youtu.be/wkkv9eZpcik">Watch Henry’s full presentation on YouTube</a></p>
<p>📄 <a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Marine_Mussels_Presentation.pptx">Download Henry’s Presentation Slides (PPTX)</a></p>
<p>⸻</p>
<p>A Proud Moment for Undergraduate Research</p>
<p>Projects were conducted under the guidance of Ariana Huffmyer and Matt George, respectively, and reflect the high caliber of undergraduate research in our lab. We are incredibly proud of Genevieve and Henry—not only for their scientific contributions but also for their clarity, creativity, and commitment to advancing our understanding of marine organism resilience in a changing world.</p>
<p>Please take a moment to view their presentations and join us in celebrating their accomplishments.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>shellfish</category>
  <category>capstone</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-capstone/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-06-16_10-44-13.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spotlight on Fellowship Success</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-fellowships/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are proud to celebrate two exceptional students in our lab who have each recently received prestigious fellowships in recognition of their innovative research tackling the urgent challenges of climate change and biodiversity conservation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_lab-photo-20250213-edited-SJW-01.JPG_36302626_pixels_2025-06-11_18-26-37.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>photo of fellows</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="zachary-bengtsson-nw-casc-fellow" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="zachary-bengtsson-nw-casc-fellow">Zachary Bengtsson – NW CASC Fellow</h2>
<p><a href="https://zbengt.github.io/notebook/">Zach</a> has been awarded a <strong>Northwest Climate Adaptation Science Center (NW CASC) Fellowship</strong>, joining a distinguished cohort of graduate researchers from institutions across the Northwest. His project, titled <em>Developing computational tools for genetic risk assessment of Olympia oyster (Ostrea lurida) populations in the Puget Sound</em>, focuses on advancing genetic tools that help guide the sustainable restoration of Washington’s native oyster.<br>
</p>
<p>Zach’s research integrates environmental drivers of local adaptation, hatchery management, and climate resilience to evaluate how restoration practices affect the genetic diversity of wild oyster populations. The selection committee praised his proposal for its clear relevance to stakeholder needs—highlighted by strong support from the Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife—and his deep commitment to co-produced, actionable science. His work will provide valuable tools for conservation managers as they balance ecological recovery with long-term resilience in Puget Sound estuaries.</p>
</section>
<section id="kathleen-durkin-smithsonian-fellow" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kathleen-durkin-smithsonian-fellow">Kathleen Durkin – Smithsonian Fellow</h2>
<p><a href="https://shedurkin.github.io/Roberts-LabNotebook/">Kathleen</a> has received a fellowship to conduct groundbreaking research at the <strong>Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History</strong>, where she will pioneer the use of <strong>nanopore sequencing to map DNA methylation in archival coral specimens</strong>. Her project represents one of the first efforts to explore historical DNA methylation (hDNA) in invertebrates using museum collections.</p>
<p>Drawing from coral samples that span over a century of collection history, Kathleen’s work will assess how epigenetic changes—particularly DNA methylation—can offer insights into coral stress responses and environmental resilience over time. By applying Oxford Nanopore Technology’s direct sequencing platform, she aims to overcome the limitations of traditional bisulfite sequencing in degraded DNA and establish a robust method for tracking historical epigenomic signatures.</p>
<p>This innovative research will not only advance our understanding of coral adaptation during a period of unprecedented climate change but also expand the utility of natural history collections for modern genomic and conservation science.</p>
<hr>
<p>These fellowships reflect the drive and creativity that Zach and Kathleen bring to their work, and we are excited to watch their projects unfold over the coming year. Their success exemplifies the kind of interdisciplinary, forward-thinking science that will shape the future of marine conservation and climate adaptation.</p>
<p>Please join us in congratulating Zachary and Kathleen on these outstanding achievements!</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>climate</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-fellowships/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_lab-photo-20250213-edited-SJW-01.JPG_36302626_pixels_2025-06-11_18-26-37.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Decoding Marine Memory</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-epimar/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>At EPIMAR2025 in Barcelona, a gathering of global marine scientists illuminated the hidden world of epigenetic regulation in marine invertebrates. These tiny organisms, often overlooked in genomic studies, are now at the forefront of revealing how life beneath the waves adapts, survives, and thrives in rapidly changing oceans.</p>
<p>In this post, we highlight key presentations that explored how DNA methylation, RNA modifications, and chromatin remodeling influence invertebrate development, stress response, and even intergenerational adaptation.</p>
<hr>
<section id="mussels-and-methylation-maps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mussels-and-methylation-maps">Mussels and Methylation Maps</h3>
<p><strong>Enrico D’Aniello</strong>&nbsp;and colleagues presented the first high-resolution DNA methylation map in the mussel&nbsp;<em>Mytilus galloprovincialis</em>. This map revealed key regulatory elements and tissue-specific methylation patterns, providing a baseline for understanding how gene expression is modulated in response to environmental shifts.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="modifications-in-oysters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modifications-in-oysters">Modifications in Oysters</h3>
<p>In&nbsp;<em>Crassostrea gigas</em>,&nbsp;<strong>Natacha Clairet</strong>&nbsp;demonstrated that m6A RNA methylation plays a pivotal role in neural development and transcript splicing. Her work showed that these epitranscriptomic changes are not only developmentally regulated but may also mediate environmental responses.</p>
<p>Building on the oyster story,&nbsp;<strong>Guillaume Rivière</strong>&nbsp;showed that thermal stress leaves lasting epigenetic marks on oyster gill tissues. This “epigenetic memory” alters gene expression patterns in subsequent exposures, pointing to methylation as a resilience mechanism.</p>
<p>Meanwhile,&nbsp;<strong>Sophie Valk</strong>&nbsp;examined oysters undergoing natural sex transitions, finding unique DNA methylation signatures in hermaphrodites. Her work hints at epigenetic regulation as a driver of reproductive plasticity.</p>
<p><strong>Elyna Bouchereau</strong> from the University of Perpignan explored the methylome of <em>Vibrio aestuarianus</em>, a bacterial pathogen of oysters, revealing how epigenetic signatures may influence virulence and host interaction, while <strong>Amélie Dellong</strong> presented a multi-omics approach to decipher chromatin structure in <em>Magallana gigas</em>, offering new insight into the regulatory architecture of oyster genomes.</p>
<p><strong>Marta Pascual</strong> presented a population epigenomics study of <em>Crassostrea gigas</em> along the Iberian Atlantic coast, showing that DNA methylation patterns vary significantly between wild and farmed populations, suggesting a potential role in local adaptation and domestication.</p>
<p><strong>Lénaig Boulard</strong> investigated the epigenetic responses of Pacific oysters to ocean acidification, demonstrating methylation changes in genes associated with shell formation and oxidative stress defense.</p>
<p><strong>Céline Cosseau</strong> explored transgenerational epigenetic inheritance in oysters, showing that environmental exposures in adult oysters can lead to stable methylation changes in offspring, particularly in stress-response genes.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="corals-and-the-code-of-light" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="corals-and-the-code-of-light">Corals and the Code of Light</h3>
<p>Reef-building corals were another highlight.&nbsp;<strong>Kathleen Durkin</strong>&nbsp;described how miRNAs and lncRNAs shape coral development and immunity under heat stress.&nbsp;<strong>Kelly Gómez-Campo</strong>&nbsp;added that light exposure during development can modulate DNA methylation patterns and downstream gene networks in corals, underscoring how tightly environment and epigenome are interlinked.<br>
<strong>Hollie Putnam</strong> presented a comprehensive study on the spatial and temporal dynamics of epigenetic regulation in reef-building corals, while <strong>Jill Ashey</strong> highlighted the critical roles of non-coding RNAs during early coral development, particularly in mediating the maternal-to-zygotic transition.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="histone-modifications-in-sea-anemones" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="histone-modifications-in-sea-anemones">Histone Modifications in Sea Anemones</h3>
<p>In the heat-stressed sea anemone&nbsp;<em>Exaiptasia diaphana</em>,&nbsp;<strong>Mascha Dix</strong>&nbsp;presented findings on histone modifications (H3K27me3 and H3K4me3) as key players in regulating gene expression. These modifications allow rapid but reversible responses to changing thermal conditions.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="hypoxia-and-neural-epigenetics-in-sea-hares" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hypoxia-and-neural-epigenetics-in-sea-hares">Hypoxia and Neural Epigenetics in Sea Hares</h3>
<p><strong>Javier Rodriguez-Casariego</strong>&nbsp;studied the sea hare&nbsp;<em>Aplysia californica</em>&nbsp;and showed that DNA methylation shifts in neural tissues under hypoxic conditions suggest a role for epigenetic plasticity in environmental stress tolerance.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-epigenetics-as-a-unifying-language" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-epigenetics-as-a-unifying-language">Conclusion: Epigenetics as a Unifying Language</h3>
<p>These studies collectively show that epigenetic mechanisms are not just molecular curiosities—they are central to how marine invertebrates sense, remember, and adapt to their environment. Whether through methylation, non-coding RNA, or histone marks, the language of the epigenome is being translated into actionable insights for conservation, aquaculture, and understanding evolution under climate change.</p>
<p>EPIMAR2025 made one thing clear: the future of marine biology will be written in epigenetic code.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-epimar/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_EPIMAR_2025__Barcelona_Spain_-_May_27-30_2025-06-11_17-59-29.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>🌟 Undergraduate Research Highlight</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-baird/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’re excited to share that <strong>Madeline Baird</strong>, an undergraduate researcher in the Roberts Lab, will present her research at the <strong>2025 Mary Gates Undergraduate Research Symposium</strong>.</p>
<p>Her poster presentation, titled</p>
<p><strong>“Application of Metabolic Assays to Characterize Thermal Tolerance in Pacific Oyster (Magallana gigas) Early Life Stages,”</strong></p>
<div class="text-center">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_UWURS_Oyster_Poster.pdf_2025-05-15_09-17-36.png" class="img-fluid" style="width: 75%;"></p>
</div>
<p>investigates how parental immune priming affects offspring resilience in a changing ocean. Collaborating with the <strong>Jamestown Shellfish Hatchery</strong>, Madeline reared juvenile oysters from immune-challenged parents and assessed growth, survival, and metabolism under a wide range of temperatures.</p>
<p>Using high-throughput <strong>resazurin metabolic assays</strong>, she found that immune-primed offspring showed greater thermal tolerance—especially between 36°C and 40°C—highlighting a potentially important role of <strong>metabolic flexibility</strong> in inherited stress resilience.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>🔬 These findings support the idea that <strong>non-genetic inheritance</strong> may help oysters adapt to increasing marine heatwaves—an insight with valuable implications for aquaculture and conservation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Madeline’s work was supported by the <strong>USDA</strong>, <strong>Washington Sea Grant</strong>, and the <strong>UW Population Health Initiative</strong>, which recognized her with a <strong>2025 Population Health Recognition Award</strong>.</p>
<p>We’re proud to support Madeline’s research and scientific growth, and we look forward to seeing where her work leads next!</p>
<p>🧪 View her research, lab notebook, and more:</p>
<p>👉 <a href="https://linktr.ee/madsmarine" class="uri">https://linktr.ee/madsmarine</a></p>
<p>See her in in the lab!</p>
<video width="640" controls="">
<source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/OysterLabworkVideo.MOV" type="video/quicktime">
<p>Your browser does not support the video tag. </p>


<!-- -->


</video> ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-baird/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_UWURS_Oyster_Poster.pdf_2025-05-15_07-34-59.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Environmental Priming in Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lewis-smith/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We're proud to share a new publication by former lab member <strong>Connor Lewis-Smith</strong>, now a Social Scientist with NOAA's Northwest Fisheries Science Center. His article, <em>"Navigating ocean acidification in shellfish aquaculture: Stakeholder perspectives of developing strategies in the U.S. Pacific Region"</em>, was just released in <em>Aquaculture Reports</em> and offers an in-depth look at how shellfish growers across the U.S. Pacific Coast are responding to ocean acidification and related environmental stressors.</p>
<p>The study draws on structured interviews with producers from Washington, Oregon, California, Alaska, and Hawaii to capture evolving perceptions of ocean acidification and industry interest in emerging adaptation strategies. Notably, concern about ocean acidification appears to have declined in the past decade, as growers increasingly focus on intersecting threats such as harmful algal blooms, disease, and rising temperatures.</p>
<p>The paper explores two adaptation strategies under development: <strong>parental priming</strong>—a technique involving exposure of broodstock to stressful conditions to enhance offspring resilience—and <strong>native species portfolio expansion</strong>. While industry support for both strategies was mixed and often contingent on further scientific validation, the study emphasizes the importance of early engagement between researchers and growers to co-develop viable solutions.</p>
<p>Importantly, this research aligns directly with <strong>ongoing environmental priming work in our lab</strong>, where we are experimentally testing how exposure to low pH and high temperature conditions in adult shellfish can influence offspring performance. By integrating physiological, transcriptomic, and lipidomic data, our current NOAA-funded work seeks to identify the mechanisms underlying carryover effects and inform hatchery practices that enhance larval resilience under future ocean conditions.</p>
<p>Connor's collaboration with our group helped build the interdisciplinary foundation for this kind of applied science—where social, biological, and ecological factors intersect to shape adaptation in real-world settings. We're excited to see how his work complements and extends our efforts to support a more resilient shellfish aquaculture sector.</p>
<p>Read the full article <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aqrep.2025.102858">here</a>.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/frontpage/sr320-lewis-smith/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-05-07_11-42-09.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring the Non-Coding RNA Landscape in Reef-Building Corals</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lncRNA-rep/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Coral reefs are among the most biodiverse ecosystems on the planet, yet they are increasingly threatened by climate change and human activities. Understanding the molecular mechanisms that govern coral resilience is crucial for their conservation. A <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.15.643469.">new study by Ashey et al.&nbsp;(2025)</a> provides a groundbreaking look into the non-coding RNA (ncRNA) repertoire of reef-building corals, shedding light on how these regulatory molecules contribute to coral gene expression and environmental adaptability.</p>
<section id="why-non-coding-rnas-matter" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-non-coding-rnas-matter"><strong>Why Non-Coding RNAs Matter</strong></h3>
<p>Long dismissed as “junk” DNA, ncRNAs have emerged as vital regulators of gene expression across all domains of life. Unlike protein-coding genes, ncRNAs do not translate into proteins but instead play critical roles in controlling genetic pathways, chromatin organization, and stress responses. In corals, these molecules could be key players in their ability to withstand environmental stressors such as rising ocean temperatures and pollution.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-study-a-comprehensive-analysis-of-coral-ncrnas" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-study-a-comprehensive-analysis-of-coral-ncrnas"><strong>The Study: A Comprehensive Analysis of Coral ncRNAs</strong></h3>
<p>Ashey et al.&nbsp;conducted the first large-scale characterization of ncRNAs in three ecologically significant coral species from Mo’orea, French Polynesia:&nbsp;<em>Acropora pulchra</em>,&nbsp;<em>Pocillopora tuahiniensis</em>, and&nbsp;<em>Porites evermanni</em>. These species exhibit diverse physiological traits and symbiotic relationships, making them excellent models for studying ncRNA variation.</p>
<section id="key-findings" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings"><strong>Key Findings:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Diverse ncRNA Repertoires:</strong>&nbsp;The study identified a broad array of ncRNAs, including long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs), microRNAs (miRNAs), and piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs), indicating that corals possess a complex ncRNA regulatory system.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Limited Conservation Across Species:</strong>&nbsp;While a few miRNAs (such as&nbsp;<em>mir-100</em>) were conserved across all three species, most lncRNAs and other ncRNAs exhibited high evolutionary turnover, suggesting species-specific adaptations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Functional Insights:</strong>&nbsp;Many ncRNAs were associated with immune regulation, stress response, and genomic stability. For example, lncRNAs were often found near immune-related genes, while piRNAs were enriched in transposable element regions, which are crucial for maintaining genomic integrity.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>miRNA-Target Interactions:</strong>&nbsp;The study predicted miRNA targets involved in immune response pathways and cellular stress mechanisms, providing new insights into how corals regulate gene expression in response to environmental changes.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="implications-for-coral-resilience" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-for-coral-resilience"><strong>Implications for Coral Resilience</strong></h3>
<p>These findings underscore the importance of ncRNAs in coral biology. By regulating gene expression and protecting genome stability, ncRNAs may influence corals’ ability to acclimate to shifting environmental conditions. This research also sets the stage for future studies on the role of ncRNAs in coral bleaching, symbiosis dynamics, and adaptation.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions"><strong>Future Directions</strong></h3>
<p>Given the rapid decline of coral reefs worldwide, understanding the molecular underpinnings of coral resilience is more critical than ever. Further investigations into ncRNA functions across additional coral species and environmental conditions will enhance our ability to predict and mitigate the impacts of climate change on these vital ecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts"><strong>Final Thoughts</strong></h3>
<p>The study by Ashey et al.&nbsp;provides a significant step forward in coral molecular biology, revealing how ncRNAs contribute to the complex regulatory networks that sustain coral health. As researchers continue to explore these molecular mechanisms, such insights could inform conservation strategies aimed at preserving coral reefs in a warming world.</p>
<p>For more details, the full study is available on bioRxiv:&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.15.643469" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.03.15.643469</a>.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>coral</category>
  <category>lncRNA</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lncRNA-rep/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_httpswww.biorxiv.orgcontent10.11012025.03.15.643469v1.full.pdf_2025-03-17_08-01-04.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unlocking the Future of Shellfish Aquaculture Through Genomics</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-genomics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Aquaculture is undergoing a revolution. The integration of cutting-edge genomic tools into breeding programs is transforming the industry, allowing for enhanced growth rates, disease resistance, and environmental adaptability in farmed species. While finfish often take center stage in discussions about genomic innovation, shellfish—particularly oysters, clams, and other bivalves—stand to benefit tremendously from these advancements. A recent review by <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-025-11247-z">Andersen et al.&nbsp;(2025), published in BMC Genomics</a>, outlines the progress and future priorities for U.S. aquaculture genomics, with significant implications for shellfish industries.</p>
<section id="why-genomics-matters-for-shellfish" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-genomics-matters-for-shellfish">Why Genomics Matters for Shellfish</h2>
<p>Shellfish farming is a cornerstone of coastal economies, providing a sustainable protein source while contributing to water filtration and habitat structure. However, challenges such as disease outbreaks, climate change-driven stressors (e.g., ocean acidification, salinity fluctuations), and genetic bottlenecks in breeding programs pose significant hurdles. The integration of genomics and multi-omics approaches is helping researchers and industry stakeholders address these issues head-on.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Advancing Reference Genomes for Shellfish</li>
</ol>
<p>One of the key priorities identified in the review is the need for high-quality genome assemblies for shellfish species. Reference genomes serve as blueprints for breeding programs, guiding selective breeding efforts toward desirable traits such as disease resistance, growth efficiency, and stress tolerance.</p>
<p>For instance:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The Pacific oyster (Magallana gigas) and Eastern oyster (Crassostrea virginica) now have improved genome assemblies, which are crucial for mapping genes associated with disease resilience.</p></li>
<li><p>Structural variations in oyster genomes have been linked to breeding success, helping hatcheries refine their selection of broodstock.</p></li>
<li><p>Functional annotation efforts, like those undertaken by the international FAANG (Functional Annotation of ANimal Genomes) initiative, are improving our understanding of how genes are regulated in response to environmental stressors.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Multi-Omics Approaches: Beyond the Genome</li>
</ol>
<p>While genomic sequencing provides a foundational understanding of shellfish biology, integrating other “omics” layers—epigenomics, transcriptomics, and microbiomics—adds depth to the picture.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Epigenomics &amp; Environmental Adaptation: Studies have shown that DNA methylation plays a key role in how oysters respond to stress, such as changes in salinity and temperature. This suggests that breeding for resilience might not just be about genetics but also about harnessing heritable epigenetic modifications.</p></li>
<li><p>Transcriptomics &amp; Disease Resistance: RNA sequencing has revealed that oysters activate specific immune pathways when exposed to pathogens like Perkinsus marinus (which causes Dermo disease). Understanding these pathways helps identify candidate genes for selective breeding.</p></li>
<li><p>Microbiomics &amp; Shellfish Health: The microbial communities living on and inside shellfish significantly impact their growth and survival. Some studies suggest that manipulating the oyster microbiome could enhance disease resistance.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Genomic Selection &amp; Breeding Programs</li>
</ol>
<p>Traditional shellfish breeding has relied on mass selection or family-based selection, which can be slow and inefficient. Genomic selection—where DNA markers are used to predict an individual’s breeding value—has revolutionized selective breeding in finfish and livestock, and now it is being applied to shellfish.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The use of genomic selection in oysters is improving survival rates in low-salinity environments, a crucial trait given the increasing frequency of extreme weather events that introduce large freshwater inputs into coastal farming areas.</p></li>
<li><p>Marker-assisted selection (MAS) is being employed to accelerate breeding for traits like shell strength, which is vital for both consumer preference and post-harvest handling.</p></li>
<li><p>Researchers are also exploring CRISPR and other gene-editing technologies to validate gene function, though regulatory challenges remain.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Overcoming Challenges: From Research to Industry Application</li>
</ol>
<p>Despite these advancements, challenges remain in translating genomic discoveries into tangible benefits for shellfish farmers.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Cost &amp; Accessibility: While sequencing costs are declining, implementing genomic selection on a commercial scale still requires investment in infrastructure, training, and data management.</p></li>
<li><p>Regulatory Landscape: The potential application of gene-editing technologies in aquaculture is still subject to regulatory scrutiny. While some countries are moving toward acceptance, others remain cautious.</p></li>
<li><p>Data Integration: The vast amount of genomic and phenotypic data generated requires sophisticated bioinformatics tools for analysis. Efforts like AquaMine (a genomic database for aquaculture species) are helping streamline this process ￼.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead-the-future-of-shellfish-aquaculture" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead-the-future-of-shellfish-aquaculture">Looking Ahead: The Future of Shellfish Aquaculture</h2>
<p>The next decade of shellfish aquaculture will be defined by how well the industry can harness the power of genomics. As sequencing technology becomes more affordable and bioinformatics tools become more accessible, we are likely to see:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>More refined and efficient breeding programs using genomic selection.</p></li>
<li><p>Greater adoption of multi-omics approaches to understand complex traits like disease resistance and stress tolerance.</p></li>
<li><p>The potential emergence of gene-edited shellfish with enhanced resilience to climate change.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>By integrating these tools into aquaculture operations, we can ensure that shellfish farming remains a sustainable and resilient industry—one that continues to provide ecological and economic benefits to coastal communities while supporting global food security.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-025-11247-z">The review by Andersen et al.&nbsp;(2025)</a> highlights an exciting and rapidly evolving field. Shellfish may not have received as much genomic attention as salmon or tilapia in the past, but that is changing. With continued investment in research, training, and industry partnerships, shellfish aquaculture is poised to become a model for sustainable, high-tech food production in the 21st century.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-genomics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Advancing_genetic_improvement_in_the_omics_era_status_and_priorities_for_United_States_aquaculture__BMC_Genomics__Full_Text_2025-02-21_12-15-32.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cracking the Code of Pacific Cod</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Spencer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-cod2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What if the future of an entire fish population hinged on tiny changes in their DNA? In the frigid waters of the North Pacific, juvenile Pacific cod are facing an uncertain future as ocean temperatures rise. Our research is uncovering how these fish respond to warming waters—at the molecular level—and what that means for their survival.</p>
<p><strong>The Science Behind Survival</strong></p>
<p>At first glance, Pacific cod might seem like just another fish. But beneath the surface, their genetic makeup holds clues to how they adapt—or struggle—when faced with environmental stress. In our latest study, we’re diving deep into the connection between a cod’s genes and its ability to thrive in different temperatures.</p>
<p>We analyzed DNA and gene activity (transcriptomics) in young Pacific cod exposed to a range of temperatures, from icy 0°C to a heatwave-like 16°C. By combining this “genome-to-phenome” data—essentially linking genetic information to physical traits—we’re beginning to see which fish have the genetic tools to survive in a warming world.</p>
<p><strong>A Genetic Blueprint for Resilience</strong></p>
<p>One of the most intriguing findings comes from a process called <strong>Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS)</strong>, where we scan the entire genome for small genetic differences linked to key traits. One of the most revealing traits we studied is the <strong>hepatosomatic index (HSI)</strong>—a measure of how much energy a fish stores in its liver. Since fat storage is critical for surviving harsh winters, understanding which fish can accumulate liver lipids under stress is essential.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-17-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our data revealed <strong>specific genetic variants linked to liver size</strong>, some of which are connected to genes regulating appetite and metabolism. One gene in particular, likely involved in serotonin signaling (which affects hunger), seems to influence whether a juvenile cod stores enough fat when temperatures rise.</p>
<p><strong>Can Genes Predict Performance?</strong></p>
<p>Beyond genetics, we also examined how <strong>gene expression (RNA activity) relates to fish growth and condition</strong>. We identified a set of genes that are highly active in the strongest, most resilient fish under warm conditions. This genetic “signature” could help scientists predict which fish populations are best suited to handle climate shifts.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-18-11.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>By looking at <strong>composite performance indices (CPI)</strong>—which combine growth rate, body condition, and liver fat content—we found a distinct pattern: some fish are naturally equipped to thrive in warming seas, while others may struggle.</p>
<p><strong>A Look to the Past—and the Future</strong></p>
<p>To understand if these genetic traits have changed over time, we’re also analyzing historical samples from Pacific cod collected near Kodiak, Alaska, dating back to 2008. This will help us determine if recent marine heatwaves have already begun shaping the genetic makeup of young cod. If we find shifts in key genes over time, it could be a sign that natural selection is at work—favoring fish that can cope with temperature extremes.</p>
<p><strong>Next Steps: From Lab to Ocean Conservation</strong></p>
<p>Right now, we’re fine-tuning our analyses and comparing our results with other research teams, including NOAA scientists studying broader environmental factors. Our goal? To pinpoint the most critical genetic regions that influence temperature tolerance—and ultimately, to inform fisheries management strategies that support the resilience of Pacific cod populations.</p>
<p>As marine heatwaves become more frequent, understanding these genetic adaptations is more than just an academic pursuit. It’s about safeguarding a vital species in the face of climate change—ensuring that Pacific cod, and the people who depend on them, have a future in our warming oceans.</p>
<section id="products-this-period" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="products-this-period">Products this period:&nbsp;</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer at the NOAA NWFSC Manchester Research Station monthly meeting on December 11th, 2025, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Manchester-Presentation-Dec2024.pdf">link to slides</a>.&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer at the NOAA AFSC groundfish seminar on December 17th, 2024, <a href="https://bcove.video/3DxO7xy">link to recording</a>, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Groundfish%20Seminar%2C%202024.pdf">link to slides</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Methods and preliminary results were presented by Laura Spencer during the poster session of the Alaska Marine Science Symposium on January 27th, 2025 in Anchorage, AK, <a href="https://github.com/RobertsLab/project-cod-temperature/blob/main/reports/Spencer%2CLH_Poster-AMSS-2025-final.pdf">link to poster</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Laura Spenccer’s lab notebook updates on analyses, lab work, and products, <a href="https://laurahspencer.github.io/LabNotebook/">link to notebook</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://d.pr/f/Cq3nsF">Technical Report</a>.</p></li>
</ul>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-cod2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2025-02-17_09-15-38.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Harnessing Shellfish Environmental Memory for a Resilient Future</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-WSG/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Shellfish aquaculture is facing increasing challenges due to climate change, ocean acidification, and other environmental stressors. However, research is showing that environmental memory—the ability of organisms to retain and transmit adaptive responses to stress—may offer a promising strategy for improving resilience in aquaculture species.</p>
<p>At the 2025 Washington Sea Grant workshop, researchers and industry professionals came together to explore how environmental priming—exposing shellfish to controlled stress conditions—could be leveraged to enhance survival, growth, and performance.</p>
<section id="industry-engagement-and-perceptions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="industry-engagement-and-perceptions">Industry Engagement and Perceptions</h2>
<p>To better understand industry perspectives, a survey of shellfish growers was conducted to gauge their views on environmental priming as an adaptation strategy. The results were enlightening:<br>
• 78% of hatchery operators indicated they would consider implementing environmental priming, though most preferred to see supporting data first.<br>
• 70% of respondents said they would be willing to pay more for primed seed, provided evidence from test plots or research-supported literature was available.</p>
<p>This feedback underscores the importance of continued scientific research to validate environmental priming techniques and demonstrate their effectiveness in real-world aquaculture operations.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-environmental-priming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-environmental-priming">What is Environmental Priming?</h2>
<p>Environmental priming involves exposing shellfish to controlled stressors—such as temperature fluctuations, salinity changes, or immune challenges—to enhance their resilience later in life. Research has shown promising results across multiple species:</p>
<p>• Olympia oysters: Parental priming increased offspring survival in field conditions.<br>
• Pacific geoduck: Early-life priming led to improved growth rates later in life.<br>
• Manila clams: Offspring from primed parents exhibited better growth and survival rates.</p>
</section>
<section id="ongoing-research-and-applications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ongoing-research-and-applications">Ongoing Research and Applications</h2>
<p>Scientists are now working to optimize environmental priming strategies across different species. Ongoing research at institutions like NOAA’s Manchester Field Station and the Jamestown S’Klallam Hatchery is exploring how priming can enhance the performance of shellfish under various stress conditions.</p>
<p>For Pacific oysters, researchers are testing multiple priming approaches, including:<br>
✅ Immune challenges<br>
✅ Temperature stress<br>
✅ Salinity shifts<br>
✅ Combination stress exposures</p>
</section>
<section id="moving-forward-bridging-science-and-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="moving-forward-bridging-science-and-industry">Moving Forward: Bridging Science and Industry</h2>
<p>The insights from this research are critical for both hatchery operators and policymakers as they work toward sustainable shellfish aquaculture. With growing industry interest and evidence-based strategies, environmental priming may become a tool in ensuring the future resilience of shellfish populations.</p>
<p>Slidedecck: https://github.com/sr320/talk-WSG-2025</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>wsg</category>
  <category>talk</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-WSG/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_2025-WSG-Roberts_2025-02-10_07-20-44.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Coral Larvae and Thermal Stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/ariana-paper/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As climate change continues to drive rising ocean temperatures, coral reef ecosystems face an unprecedented crisis. Coral bleaching events, characterized by the breakdown of the mutualistic relationship between corals and their algal endosymbionts (Symbiodiniaceae), have become increasingly common, threatening the persistence of coral reefs worldwide. While much research has focused on adult corals, new studies are shedding light on how early life stages respond to thermal stress. <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3002875">A recent study by Huffmyer et al.&nbsp;(2024), published in&nbsp;<em>PLOS Biology</em></a>, provides novel insights into how coral larvae cope with increased temperatures by modifying nitrogen assimilation to stabilize symbiotic relationships and mitigate bleaching risk.</p>
<section id="the-crucial-role-of-coral-larvae-in-reef-resilience" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-crucial-role-of-coral-larvae-in-reef-resilience"><strong>The Crucial Role of Coral Larvae in Reef Resilience</strong></h3>
<p>Reef-building corals rely on their symbionts to produce energy-rich photosynthates that fuel metabolic processes. However, when subjected to thermal stress, this delicate exchange can be disrupted, leading to the expulsion of symbionts and loss of critical energy sources. Understanding how coral larvae respond to environmental stress is particularly important, as their ability to establish symbiosis and successfully settle onto reefs determines the future of coral populations.</p>
<p>The study focused on&nbsp;<em>Montipora capitata</em>, a dominant reef-building coral in Hawai‘i that vertically transmits Symbiodiniaceae to its offspring. The researchers subjected symbiotic larvae to a 2.5°C increase in temperature for three days and assessed metabolic responses, photosynthetic performance, and stable isotope-labeled metabolite exchange.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-nitrogen-assimilation-as-a-protective-mechanism" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-nitrogen-assimilation-as-a-protective-mechanism"><strong>Key Findings: Nitrogen Assimilation as a Protective Mechanism</strong></h3>
<p>Contrary to expectations, the study found that while larvae exhibited significant metabolic depression under high temperatures—indicated by a 19% reduction in respiration rates—they did not experience bleaching or a decline in survival and settlement rates. Photosynthetic activity remained stable, and the symbiont population density was maintained despite thermal stress.</p>
<p>A crucial discovery was that coral larvae increased ammonium assimilation and urea metabolism while sequestering nitrogen into dipeptides. This shift suggests that larvae actively modulate nitrogen cycling to maintain symbiotic balance. By limiting nitrogen availability to the symbionts, the coral hosts may be promoting sustained photosynthate translocation, ensuring that energy supply remains uninterrupted under heat stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="metabolic-trade-offs-and-implications-for-coral-survival" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="metabolic-trade-offs-and-implications-for-coral-survival"><strong>Metabolic Trade-offs and Implications for Coral Survival</strong></h3>
<p>While glucose translocation from symbiont to host was maintained, the study revealed reduced metabolism of glucose through central carbon pathways such as glycolysis. This metabolic shift implies a trade-off: larvae prioritize nitrogen assimilation over carbohydrate breakdown, potentially conserving energy for essential physiological functions.</p>
<p>The authors propose that nitrogen limitation imposed on Symbiodiniaceae encourages continued carbon transfer to the host, preventing the symbionts from hoarding fixed carbon, which could otherwise disrupt the mutualistic relationship. This mechanism highlights a potential resilience strategy in coral early life stages that may influence reef recovery following bleaching events.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions-and-conservation-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions-and-conservation-implications"><strong>Future Directions and Conservation Implications</strong></h3>
<p>Understanding the physiological mechanisms that allow coral larvae to withstand heat stress has significant implications for reef conservation and restoration efforts. If coral larvae can naturally modulate nitrogen metabolism to maintain symbiosis, selective breeding or assisted evolution approaches may enhance these traits in vulnerable species.</p>
<p>Additionally, further research should investigate whether similar nitrogen assimilation strategies are present in adult corals or if this is a life-stage-specific adaptation. Given the increasing frequency of marine heatwaves, identifying and promoting heat-resilient traits in corals could be a crucial component of future conservation strategies.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>Huffmyer et al.&nbsp;(2024) provide compelling evidence that coral larvae can mitigate thermal stress through nitrogen assimilation, maintaining stable symbiosis even under elevated temperatures. By uncovering this metabolic adaptation, the study advances our understanding of coral resilience mechanisms and underscores the importance of protecting early life stages in reef conservation efforts. As climate change accelerates, these insights may inform new strategies to support coral reef survival in a warming world.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>paper</category>
  <category>coral</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/ariana-paper/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Coral_larvae_increase_nitrogen_assimilation_to_stabilize_algal_symbiosis_and_combat_bleaching_under_increased_temperature__PLO_2025-02-08_12-36-36.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Turning the tide</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-boundless/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Chris is featured on UW’s “Be Boundless” site. Read full article <a href="https://www.washington.edu/boundless/turning-the-tide-marine-biology/">here</a>. Below is a short snippet of the feature along with an amazing video!</strong></p>
<p>On a windy June afternoon, Chris Mantegna, ’21, encourages a half-dozen undergraduates to flip over barnacle-studded rocks and sift through seaweed. Equipped with clipboards to record their findings, they’re creating a snapshot of the organisms in the island’s intertidal zone — from orange sea cucumbers to the camouflaged armored mollusks called chitons.</p>
<p>Mantegna, a third-year graduate student in aquatic and fishery sciences, has spent the past three summers in Washington’s San Juan Islands, mentoring undergrads here on Yellow Island — a pristine 11-acre nature preserve owned by the Nature Conservancy. She created this eight-week program for students to get their hands dirty in the field and learn cutting-edge lab techniques at the UW Friday Harbor Laboratories — where she had a transformational research experience herself as a Husky undergrad.</p>
<p>This mentorship program reflects Mantegna’s passion both for advancing the science and for making it more inclusive and accessible to others. Her face lights up when she spots a small chiton (her favorite) clinging to the bottom of a rock, and she invites others to feel the mollusk’s tough plated back. Even Mantegna’s doctoral work — examining the genetic response of shellfish to contaminants in Puget Sound waterways — has a focus on community outreach and environmental literacy.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VLLocGcP9S8?si=UzEadZGT7XryVpEV" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Mantegna says we have a better chance at fighting climate change when everyone — scientists and community members — feels connected to their environment and each other. “I can tell you that the ocean is dying or that we have too much acidification,” says Mantegna, a U.S. Navy veteran who is the first in her family to graduate from college. “But it doesn’t matter if you’ve never had the chance to feel the joy that comes from this place.”</p>
<p>Finish feature <a href="https://www.washington.edu/boundless/turning-the-tide-marine-biology/">here</a>.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>dna</category>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-boundless/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-07_12-56-13.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring Pacific Cod Resilience in a Warming Ocean</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Spencer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/posts/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In our latest update on the Pacific cod juvenile temperature study, we've gained deeper insights into how these remarkable fish respond to different temperatures. This research is part of a larger effort to understand the resilience of marine species in changing environments.</p>
<p><strong>Genetic Insights Reveal Population Origins</strong></p>
<p>We began with genetic analyses, using data from thousands of genetic markers to determine the origin of our experimental fish. All our test fish were linked to the spawning grounds in the western Gulf of Alaska (wGOA) and the Eastern Bering Sea (EBS). This finding allows us to focus on the thermal resilience of cod from this particular region, which is vital as they face shifts in temperature in their natural habitats.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-00-51.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Temperature's Role in Energy and Lipid Storage</strong></p>
<p>Our collaborator Louise Copement analyzed liver lipids in these juvenile cod, focusing on triglycerides and other key lipid types that are crucial for overwinter survival. The results showed a clear trend: energy storage, primarily in the form of triglycerides, peaked at 9°C, then dropped sharply at higher temperatures, especially at 16°C. This suggests that extreme warmth could deplete essential energy reserves, reducing the fish's survival prospects in the cold winter months.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-01-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Optimal Growth Temperatures and Physiological Responses</strong></p>
<p>We also observed that juvenile cod exhibit optimal growth at approximately 12.3°C, slightly higher than previous findings. With higher temperatures, growth rates plateau or decline, mirroring the energy storage patterns. Interestingly, the gene expression data from liver tissues revealed significant temperature-driven shifts, especially in energy production, lipid metabolism, and immune response genes. This molecular data adds a new layer to our understanding of temperature tolerance.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_15-01-22.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Integrated Data: A Pathway to Genomic Resilience Markers</strong></p>
<p>Combining growth, lipid, and gene expression data, we've started identifying genes that correlate with enhanced resilience at specific temperatures. This approach could spotlight genetic markers for thermal resilience, offering clues about cod populations best suited to future ocean conditions.</p>
<p>In summary, this research underscores the delicate balance juvenile Pacific cod must maintain in their energy reserves and growth under variable temperatures. These findings will help guide conservation and management efforts as we work to protect Pacific cod populations in a warming world.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/posts/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-11-06_13-57-57.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep dive into the handbook</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-handbook/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A unique perspective. You will never guess what they reveal!</p>
<section id="audio" class="level1">
<h1>Audio</h1>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/handbook.wav"></video></div>
</section>
<section id="transcript" class="level1">
<h1>Transcript</h1>
<p>Welcome to The Deep Dive, where we dig into the nitty gritty of fascinating topics.</p>
<p>Today, we’re taking a deep dive into the Roberts Lab at the University of Washington, and we’re doing that through the lens of their handbook.</p>
<p>It’s more than just a rule book, though, isn’t it?</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p>It’s like a window into their whole approach to science.</p>
<p>Everything from, like, groundbreaking research to how they actually build their research culture.</p>
<p>And they’re known for being incredibly transparent, which this handbook really embodies.</p>
<p>Yeah, it’s refreshing.</p>
<p>And speaking of refreshing, I have to ask you about this freezer alarm situation.</p>
<p>Oh, yes.</p>
<p>So they have, like, a dedicated alarm for their ultra-low temperature freezers, right?</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>But there’s this 15-minute delay before anyone actually gets notified if it goes off.</p>
<p>Can you imagine?</p>
<p>It’s like a slow-motion heart attack for a researcher.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>All those precious samples.</p>
<p>I’d be a wreck.</p>
<p>It really highlights the fragility of these biological materials they’re working with.</p>
<p>RNA, proteins, these things have to be stored at, like, negative 80 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Wow.</p>
<p>Even a short power outage could be disastrous.</p>
<p>So is that delay, like, a safety net to give the system a chance to recover?</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>It’s a calculated risk.</p>
<p>They’re trying to balance preventing false alarms while also, you know, protecting those invaluable research materials.</p>
<p>Makes sense.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And it seems like that emphasis on meticulousness, on minimizing risk, it really comes through in the whole handbook, especially when they talk about lab safety and chemicals.</p>
<p>It’s serious business.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>Like with Arnazole RT, they’re very clear about it being corrosive, potentially harmful if you inhale it, even disposing of it.</p>
<p>It’s a whole multi-step process.</p>
<p>Well, they’re dealing with some pretty potent stuff.</p>
<p>It underscores their dedication to, you know, not just scientific rigor, but the actual well-being of their researchers.</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>It’s like they’re creating an environment where cutting-edge science can happen, but it can happen safely.</p>
<p>Safety first.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And that meticulousness, that doing things by the book, it goes beyond just lab safety, you know.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>It’s woven into their whole research philosophy, which makes you wonder, if they’re this careful with safety, how does that translate to, say, data management or collaboration?</p>
<p>Good question.</p>
<p>And as luck would have it, that’s exactly what we’re going to be digging into in the rest of this deep dive.</p>
<p>You know, it’s funny you should mention that because the next thing that really struck me about this handbook was their code of conduct.</p>
<p>Oh, interesting.</p>
<p>How so?</p>
<p>Well, for one, it’s incredibly detailed, even for like their diversity, equity, and inclusion meetings.</p>
<p>You don’t always see that level of, I don’t know, formality in a lab handbook.</p>
<p>What kinds of things are we talking about here?</p>
<p>They have these great phrases like, “Elevate impact above intent,” and, “Expect and accept non-closure.”</p>
<p>Like, really specific guidelines.</p>
<p>Huh.</p>
<p>It sounds like they’re trying to foster a very specific kind of research environment.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>One where people feel comfortable admitting they don’t know everything, which, let’s be honest, is most of the time in research, right?</p>
<p>Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p>Science is all about embracing uncertainty.</p>
<p>But it takes a certain culture to really allow for that.</p>
<p>Totally.</p>
<p>And it seems like they’re putting a lot of emphasis on making sure everyone feels heard and respected, especially in those DEI meetings.</p>
<p>Well, and that makes sense, right?</p>
<p>If you want to have those tough conversations about diversity and inclusion, you need to create a space where people feel safe to speak their minds.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>No, you’re right.</p>
<p>It all ties together.</p>
<p>And then there’s this whole thing about mentorship.</p>
<p>They really encourage lab members to have multiple mentors, not just one.</p>
<p>That’s interesting.</p>
<p>Most labs I’ve seen, it’s pretty standard to have one primary mentor.</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>So I thought that was really unique.</p>
<p>It kind of speaks to this idea of providing a well-rounded experience, right?</p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p>Different mentors bring different perspectives, different areas of expertise.</p>
<p>It can really enrich a researcher’s training.</p>
<p>Okay, so we’ve got meticulous safety protocols, a very deliberate approach to their lab culture.</p>
<p>But we also know they’re dealing with a massive amount of data.</p>
<p>Like their handbook mentions Nightingale for sequencing this whole network attached storage system called Gannett.</p>
<p>Don’t forget the supercomputer.</p>
<p>MOCs, was it?</p>
<p>Oh, right.</p>
<p>MOCs.</p>
<p>I mean, it’s a lot.</p>
<p>It really makes you wonder how they manage it all.</p>
<p>It’s a data tsunami.</p>
<p>How do they keep from drowning?</p>
<p>Well, for one thing, they’re incredibly organized.</p>
<p>Like religiously organized.</p>
<p>Give me the details.</p>
<p>Think detailed metadata for every single experiment, strict folder structures on their network.</p>
<p>They even have readme files.</p>
<p>Readme files for every folder, seriously.</p>
<p>Seriously.</p>
<p>And it’s all part of this commitment to open science.</p>
<p>They want their research to be accessible, transparent.</p>
<p>So anyone could theoretically go in and understand their data, their methods.</p>
<p>That’s the idea.</p>
<p>It’s about breaking down those silos, you know, fostering collaboration, avoiding unnecessary redundancy, ultimately speeding up discoveries.</p>
<p>It’s kind of inspiring, actually.</p>
<p>It’s like they’re playing the long game, advancing science as a whole, not just their own work.</p>
<p>Exactly.</p>
<p>But okay, even with perfect organization, all that data analysis, it’s got to be intense.</p>
<p>They mentioned Jupiter notebooks in the handbook.</p>
<p>Right, and mocks the supercomputer.</p>
<p>And they even talk about using like the command line.</p>
<p>Hard course, so they’re not messing around.</p>
<p>Well, they’re equipping their researchers with a seriously powerful toolkit.</p>
<p>But it goes beyond just the tech.</p>
<p>They even recommend this book, Getting Things Done.</p>
<p>Time management.</p>
<p>Time management.</p>
<p>It’s all about efficiency.</p>
<p>They don’t just give them the tools.</p>
<p>They give them the training, the resources to actually use them well.</p>
<p>It’s like they’ve thought of everything.</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>And it doesn’t stop there.</p>
<p>They have a whole section on conferences, funding opportunities, even like travel grants.</p>
<p>They want their researchers to be well-rounded, right?</p>
<p>Not just stuck in the lab, but out there presenting, collaborating, getting their work funded.</p>
<p>It’s impressive, I have to say.</p>
<p>Looking at the Roberts Lab this way, through their handbook, you really get a sense of the thoughtfulness, the care that goes into building a successful research environment.</p>
<p>It’s not just about, you know, the results, the discoveries.</p>
<p>It’s the people, the culture.</p>
<p>And that commitment to moving science forward in a way that’s open and collaborative, it’s really something.</p>
<p>Makes you wonder what they’ll accomplish, what amazing discoveries are on the horizon for them.</p>
<p>It does, doesn’t it?</p>
<p>And that’s something to ponder as we wrap up this deep dive into the world of the Roberts Lab.</p>
<p>Until next time, keep exploring, keep questioning, and keep diving deep.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>handbook</category>
  <category>audio</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-handbook/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Roberts_Lab_Handbook_2024-09-14_13-23-52.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hatchery-based Environmental Conditioning Activities</title>
  <dc:creator>Steven Roberts</dc:creator>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-usda-report/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>During this past year a series of hatchery-based environmental conditioning activities (referred to as hardening) were completed with oysters out-planted onto three farms to evaluate performance. Additionally, climate resiliency was assessed in hardened oysters under controlled conditions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_overview.png_2024-08-29_13-35-45.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Experimental Overview</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="farm-outplanting" class="level1">
<h1>Farm Outplanting</h1>
<p>Early in the season, a cohort of oysters were subject to (a) daily thermal hardening for approximately two weeks prior to out planting in hanging bags on a farm in Sequim Bay, alongside a control group. These oyster will be assessed in early Autumn 2024. Later in the season oysters were subjected to a more diverse series of hardening conditions with oyster split between two commercial farms, one located in Willapa Bay and a second in the San Juan Islands. The combination of age classes and hardening conditions were as follows: b) small seed / daily thermal hardening, c) adult / daily thermal hardening, d) small seed / weekly thermal hardening, e1) large seed / weekly thermal hardening, e2) large seed / weekly zero salinity hardening. These hardening activities spanned from several weeks to months. For all hardening efforts controls were also outplanted. Oysters out planted in Willapa Bay will be assessed for survival and growth in early September 2024. Oysters out planted in the San Juan Islands have be subject to more routine monitoring. At this site we are currently observing a trend where oysters subjected to the daily hardening regime are surviving better than controls.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-37-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Wescott Bay Outplanting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-1" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 1</h1>
<p>To assess the effectiveness of hardening within a hatchery setting, four ages classes of oysters were examined: adults (40-100mm), juveniles (20-55mm), seed (6-15mm), and spat ()1-6mm). In order to assess hardening potential and environmental memory, oysters were subject to an initial chronic temperature stress, then subjected to a secondary stress to see if the response to secondary stress was impacted by initial exposure. During the chronic temperature stress period, oysters from each age class were exposed to a daily 25ºC temperature spike. This repeated for 14 days starting on October 1. Control oysters from each cohort were maintained at an ambient temperature of approximately 17ºC during the same time period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-38-28.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Hardening and acute stress temperature timeline</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Adult oysters in stress conditions were also subject to mechanical stress at day 1, 7, and 48, which was induced by 15 minutes. At day 147 (7 weeks after initial chronic stress), both stressed and non-stressed adult, juvenile, spat, and seed were subjected to a secondary stress of 30 minutes in 32ºC. Gill tissue was sampled immediately after and placed into RNAlater. Spat and seed that were too small to dissect gill tissue were sampled whole with all tissue used in gene expression assays. To date we have analyzed gene expression data from seed and spat. There was no mortality during this trial. Hardening increased growth (compared to controls) in spat. Further there was a reduced transcriptional response in spat. These data suggest temperature hardening of spat could result in a resiliency to later temperature stress whereby energy resources could favor growth.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-39-30.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Growth Performance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Gene expression profiles (spat)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_env_hardening..._-_Google_Slides_2024-08-29_13-40-54.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic physiology explanation when hardened spat are exposed to acute temperature stress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="physiological-assessment-2" class="level1">
<h1>Physiological Assessment 2</h1>
<p>In a second experimental regime, juvenile oysters were subjected to four hardening conditions 1) high temperature (35°C), 2) high temperature and freshwater, 3) freshwater, and 4) poly I:C immersion. These were exposures that occurred every other day for about 3 weeks. Approximately 1 month after hardening, oysters were brought to the lab and subjected to metabolic assessment using resazurin at 18°C and 42°C. Resazurin is a dye that is commonly used in cell viability, and it works by changing color as an organism consumes oxygen. Survival was assessed during the resazurin assay and 24 hours later. To date, our analysis suggests metabolic activity of the 42°C oysters was higher in the control oysters than previously hardened oysters. In the near future we will assess the relationship of metabolic activity and survival however it appears higher metabolic rate directly correlates with mortality. Taken together these sets of controlled experiments suggest hardening does have an impact on resiliency, though dependent on age, hardening duration, and subsequent environmental conditions.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_logo-resazuring_2024-08-29_13-50-31.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Resazurin assay (4 hour / 2 temperatures) on hardened oysters"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-usda-report/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-29_13-10-49.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Assessing Oyster Viability Under Environmental Stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lsamp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As part of our ongoing commitment to fostering innovative research, this summer was particularly thrilling due to the strides made in the <a href="https://www.washington.edu/omad/louis-stokes-alliance-for-minority-participation/">LSAMP Scientist Program</a>. One of our standout projects, led by an ambitious student researcher, Colby Elvrum, brought new insights into the resilience of oysters against environmental stressors. Get a <a href="https://genefish.wordpress.com/author/colbyelvrum/">first hand account of all of Colby’s science from his notebook!</a></p>
<section id="the-genesis-of-the-study" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-genesis-of-the-study">The Genesis of the Study</h3>
<p>Oysters, a crucial component of aquatic ecosystems, serve as indicators of environmental health and sustainability. Recognizing their role and the urgent need to understand how environmental changes affect these organisms, we embarked on a project to utilize a novel application of the resazurin assay, traditionally a cell viability test in microbiology. This assay, which exploits the color-changing properties of the resazurin dye in response to oxygen consumption, was adapted to measure the metabolic activity of oysters under stress.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-we-aimed-to-discover" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-aimed-to-discover">What We Aimed to Discover</h3>
<p>Our research was driven by two pivotal questions: Can resazurin effectively measure metabolism in oysters, and does prior exposure to stress (stress hardening) alter their metabolic response to subsequent stressors? Through meticulously designed experiments, Colby led the charge in optimizing the assay conditions, ensuring the reliability and accuracy of our measurements.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-33-23.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Colby presenting his research at the Summer Research Symposium</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-and-methodological-innovations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-and-methodological-innovations">Key Findings and Methodological Innovations</h3>
<p>Our findings were enlightening. We observed that resazurin is not only a viable marker for oyster metabolism but also that it clearly illustrates the metabolic shifts caused by environmental stressors such as temperature fluctuations. Notably, oysters exposed to elevated temperatures displayed a rapid increase in metabolic rate, which was a precursor to subsequent mortality. This initial surge and later plateau in metabolism provided critical clues about the stress thresholds of these organisms.</p>
<p>Moreover, the study also highlighted how oysters previously conditioned to withstand stress exhibited altered survival rates under extreme temperatures, suggesting a potential sensitization rather than hardening effect. These insights are crucial for understanding how oysters might respond to the escalating challenges of climate change.</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-ahead" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h3>
<p>The implications of this research extend beyond the academic sphere. They beckon a reevaluation of how we manage and conserve our aquatic resources in the face of rapid environmental changes. The potential to scale up this assay and automate aspects of the procedure could revolutionize aquaculture, and provide a more dynamic understanding of environmental impacts on marine life.</p>
</section>
<section id="gratitude-and-acknowledgments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gratitude-and-acknowledgments">Gratitude and Acknowledgments</h3>
<p>This research was made possible through the support of the National Science Foundation. We are immensely proud of Colby and all associated researchers for their dedication and hard work.</p>
<p><strong>Poster</strong> (<a href="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Colby_Poster_LSAMP.pdf">download hi-res pdf</a>)</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-40-33.png" class="img-fluid"></p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>stress</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lsamp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/2024-08-21_11-42-08.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Intertidal Innovators</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-intertidal/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_1373.png_2024-08-19_12-59-21.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 16, participants in the Intertidal Innovators program presented their work to the community. The program, which was a collaboration sponsored by the UW Earthlab program, provided students with the opportunity to learn about marine science and conservation through art.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-19_13-09-47.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Quote
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This program has lasted for 10 days, but during those days we have learned and worked very hard to give you this project. And we are proud to say that there are a bunch of hard working members in our program that have learned new skills and have gained knowledge in this program So in this journey, you will learn a lot about our work and marine life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>At the community showcase, students guide small groups around the intertidal, sharing their art with tablets and speakers. It was a great experience that showcased videos, poems, live demonostrations, and stories. Anyone can checkout their guided tour at Golden Garden Park via the echoes app - <a href="https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC" class="uri">https://explore.echoes.xyz/collections/jJtrYdYIdtZ8eCpC</a></p>
<p>Below is a video that takes you behind the scenes on the 10-day experience students participated in.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PsVyUPzu2_A" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-intertidal/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_The_Golden_Hour_-_a_geolocated_audio_walk_by_Intertidal_Innovators_on_ECHOES_2024-08-19_12-50-25.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ostras en Chile</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-ostras/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_IMG_6806.jpg_19801320_pixels_2024-08-14_11-49-59.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On August 6, 2024, approximately sixty participants gathered at the Professor Alamiro Robledo Auditorium of the Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences at the University of Concepción. They were there to delve into the promising sector of oyster aquaculture in Chile during the seminar titled “Oysters in Chile: Opportunities and Challenges for Aquaculture Diversification.” This event was meticulously organized by the Interdisciplinary Center for Aquaculture Research (INCAR).</p>
<p>The seminar showcased six presentations from both national and international experts, followed by a panel discussion. The diverse audience included academia, public and private sector representatives, producers, aquaculturists, industry leaders, professionals, and both secondary and postgraduate students. The gathering aimed to foster a comprehensive dialogue on the development of oyster aquaculture in the country.</p>
<p>Manira Matamala, the regional director of the Undersecretary of Fisheries and Aquaculture (Subpesca) for Valparaíso, O’Higgins, and Maule, commended INCAR’s initiative. She highlighted the seminar’s focus on enhancing the genetic and genomic understanding of oysters, which is vital for promoting sustainable aquaculture practices.</p>
<p>Among the speakers, Justo García, an aquaculturist and founder of “Cultivos Cholche,” shared insights from his hands-on experience in various stages of oyster production, emphasizing the importance of adding value to the aquaculture processes.</p>
<p>Key Presentations Highlighted at the Seminar:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Steven Roberts from the University of Washington offered an international perspective with his presentation on the “<a href="https://github.com/sr320/talk-ostras-2024">Olympia Oyster (Ostrea lurida) Restoration in the United States</a>,” focusing on physiological and genomic insights.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardo-Escárate, deputy director of Incar, discussed the genome of the Chilean oyster (Ostrea chilensis) as a critical tool for the restoration and conservation of natural oyster banks.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Francisco Cárcamo shared experiences on co-cultivating Japanese oysters and algae both in field and laboratory settings, presenting an alternative approach for Environmental Performance Enhancement (APE). Justo García recounted his local experiences in small-scale aquaculture for both Chilean and Japanese oysters.</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Rodrigo Rojas from the Catholic University of the North introduced advances from a technological program aimed at the sustainable development of Japanese oyster cultivation.</p></li>
<li><p>Meyling Tang, vice president of the Cocinamar Foundation, proposed strategies to reinvigorate oyster consumption in Chile with her presentation titled “Oysters Everywhere: Ideas to Reactivate Oyster Consumption in Chile.”</p></li>
<li><p>Dr.&nbsp;Renato Quiñones, the director of Incar, emphasized the seminar’s role in bringing together experts from varied fields to create a multidimensional space for all stakeholders involved in oyster cultivation. This interaction is crucial for transforming scientific knowledge into a community and national heritage.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The event concluded with a panel discussion moderated by Dr.&nbsp;Doris Soto, principal investigator at Incar, where experts discussed the multifaceted opportunities and challenges facing aquaculture diversification in Chile.</p>
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-36-29.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This seminar not only highlighted the collaborative efforts required to advance oyster aquaculture but also showcased the commitment of INCAR to foster a sustainable and innovative aquaculture industry in Chile.</p>


<!-- -->


 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>presentation</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-ostras/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Monosnap_2024-08-14_11-33-39.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring How Environmental Conditions Impact Atlantic Salmon’s Defense Against Sea Lice</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38876411/">In our latest study, we delved into the complex interplay between environmental factors and the immune responses of Atlantic salmon (<em>Salmo salar</em>) during infestations by sea lice (<em>Caligus rogercresseyi</em>).</a> This research is particularly significant for both aquaculture and the management of natural marine ecosystems.</p>
<section id="our-research-approach" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-research-approach">Our Research Approach</h4>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Cristian Gallardos’ team set up an experimental infestation of Atlantic salmon with sea lice, controlling for variations in temperature and salinity: specifically, conditions were set at 8°C and 16°C, and 32 and 26 practical salinity units (PSU). We then collected tissues from these fish to conduct analyses via reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) and whole transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq).</p>
</section>
<section id="key-discoveries" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-discoveries">Key Discoveries</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Impact of Environment on Parasitic Load</strong>: We observed that the parasitic load varied significantly with environmental conditions, noting the lowest abundance of lice in salmon kept at cooler and less saline conditions (8°C/26PSU).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Transcriptional Changes and Splicing Events</strong>: Environmental conditions were found to influence the salmon’s transcriptome profiles substantially. Notably, there was an increase in alternative splicing events in fish under low temperature and salinity, suggesting that environmental stress can induce genomic adaptations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Methylation Patterns</strong>: We also noted significant changes in methylation levels in response to temperature variations, with more pronounced differential methylation regions (DMRs) at the higher temperature of 16°C. These methylation changes correlated with the expression of alternatively spliced transcripts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Biological Pathways</strong>: Our analyses revealed significant correlations between methylation, transcript expression, and key biological pathways such as Ferroptosis and TLR signaling pathways, which are crucial for immune response and cellular integrity.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="implications-of-our-findings" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-of-our-findings">Implications of Our Findings</h4>
<p>This research highlights the nuanced ways in which environmental conditions can influence the genomic and epigenomic landscapes of marine organisms. For the aquaculture industry, understanding these dynamics is essential for developing effective management strategies to combat sea lice infestations, which are a major challenge for the sustainability and economic success of salmon farming.</p>
<p>Moreover, the link between environmental conditions, alternative splicing, and methylation opens new research avenues into the genetic mechanisms of resilience and adaptability in marine organisms. This knowledge advances our understanding of how species adapt to their changing environments, which is critical for preserving and enhancing the health of our global marine resources.</p>


<!-- -->

</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>salmon</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/posts/sr320-lice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_Environmental_influence_on_the_Atlantic_salmon_transcriptome_and_methylome_during_sea_lice_infestations_-_ScienceDirect_2024-08-14_12-12-07.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
