<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>robertslab.info</title>
<link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/projects.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/projects.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Using next-generation sequencing techniques to assess adaptive capacity and illuminate mechanisms underlying the effects of high pCO2 on Alaskan crab and fish species</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/crabcod.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Ingrid Spies</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Researchers at the Alaska Fisheries Science Center (AFSC) and the University of Washington are interested in the effects of ocean acidification (OA) on commercially and economically important crab and fish species. It appears that many species are negatively affected by exposure to pH levels predicted to occur throughout their ranges under climate change.&nbsp; The effects of OA include physiological consequences including decreased growth, altered embryonic development, reduced exoskeleton strength, increased metabolic rate, altered immune system, altered behavior, and increased mortality.&nbsp; Environmental changes may select for adapted individuals, resulting in populations that are less vulnerable to OA than the current population. Estimating the degree to which acclimation and adaptation will alter the experimental effects of OA and combined effects with other stressors is thus critical to accurately predicting how these stressors will affect future fisheries yields.&nbsp; We are using next-generation sequencing techniques to identify the specific alterations in the molecular, metabolic, and physiological pathways of individuals exposed to OA. We are looking for a post-doctoral researcher to perform bioinformatics on RNA transcriptomic data of Pacific cod and crabs exposed to OA conditions in an experimental setting. In addition, the researcher will be responsible for writing up their methods and results and drafting peer-reviewed manuscripts.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-004600 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 143)<br>
GR014801 TASK II SEQ TECHNIQUES - 62-7490 - 2021</p>
<p>AWD-004600 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 151)<br>
GR015296 TASK II SEQ TECH PD - 62-8482 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>UW CICOES Task II Seq Techniques (62-7490) / Seq Tech PD (62-8482) NOAA - NA20OAR4320271</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>7/1/2022 – 6/30/2025</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$328,323</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>crab</category>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <category>acidification</category>
  <category>02-RBE</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/crabcod.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Field-based Education and Research at Regional Aquaculture Sites (FERRAS)</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/safs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Aquaculture operations serve as a vital cog in our local economy, playing an integral role in conservation efforts and holding cultural significance. Primarily, my laboratory’s research program is devoted to enhancing aquaculture practices in the Pacific Northwest, having received several research awards in collaboration with tribes, industry players, and conservation organizations.</p>
<p>Despite having various projects involving shellfish transfer to the field for commercial or conservation purposes, budget constraints and directives in specific Requests for Proposals (RFPs) have hindered us from leveraging these opportunities to engage students and staff in fieldwork components. Thus, the purpose of this proposal is to request funds that would facilitate student and staff involvement in ongoing field grow-outs, thereby creating unique opportunities for SAFS community members. The funding will cover travel expenses, field sampling, and reagents and equipment for physiological analysis.</p>
<p>Our partnerships span both local and regional scopes, enabling a range of experiences. For instance, local sites include shellfish farms in Puget Sound, as well as with sites associated with the MusselWatch program via UW Tacoma. These local sites provide a platform for integrating field research into courses like FISH 441/541 Integrative Environmental Physiology. Traditionally, the lab has exclusively engaged in lab-based environmental manipulation. However, this funding would enable us to shift focus to comparative studies across different field sites, offering students a more immersive experience in data collection and physiological assessment. Additionally, students would gain the invaluable experience of observing active aquaculture operations, providing them with practical insights into the application of their classroom knowledge. With some necessary constraints, students would be given the freedom to design their experiments. For instance, they could assess the stress response in oysters from two different field sites, formulating hypotheses to test based on natural conditions.</p>
<p>Moreover, as part of a recent USDA award, we are dispatching oysters to commercial producers in Oregon. These field sites would provide an excellent framework for studies, which may be more apt for graduate students or scientific staff due to the need for accommodation. This experience would also illuminate the variations in environmental conditions and aquaculture practices across the region, fostering the expansion of research networks for our students.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/safs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FACT: AquaMine - A High Performance Genomic Data Mining System for Species of Importance to US Aquaculture</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/aquamine.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>PI: Christine G. Elsik, University of Missouri</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><a href="http://aquamine.org/">AquaMine</a> is a data mining system that integrates genome assemblies and gene annotation data for aquatic eumetazoan species of importance to US aquaculture and fisheries, with the goal of enabling researchers to create customized annotation datasets integrated with their own data. AquaMine was developed using the InterMine genomic data mining platform, which includes a web application with several search tools, including a simple key word search, predefined template queries, a QueryBuilder Tool for creating custom queries, a Regions Search Tool for coordinate-based queries, and a List Tool for uploading and searching with lists of identifiers. AquaMinev1.2 contains genomes of 37 aquatic species, including Arctic char, Atlantic salmon, California yellowtail, channel catfish, coho salmon, eastern oyster, giant tiger prawn, Nile tilapia, Pacific oyster, Pacific white shrimp, rainbow trout, striped sea bass and yellow perch. Annotation data includes RefSeq genes and additional data sources that may be available for each species, including Ensembl, KEGG, UniProt, Gene Ontology (GO), PubMed, and OrthoDB. Genes of human, fruit fly, owl limpet and zebrafish are included so model organism information can be leveraged using orthology. A precomputed orthology dataset called AquaMine-Ortho encompasses all species, including those not found in OrthoDB or Ensembl. New in AquaMinev1.2 is a comprehensive GO annotation dataset, covering all species, that can be used with a built-in gene enrichment analysis tool. AquaMinev1.2 also includes new genomic variant data from the Ensembl Variation Archive and RNA-seq-based gene expression levels for some species. We are currently developing new JBrowse genome browsers with Apollo manual genome annotation tools for the aquaculture species and will present the rainbow trout genome browser. We seek beta-testers from the research community to provide feedback on the AquaMine data mining tools and genome browsers.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/aquamine.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Improved climate resilience in oysters through optimization of hatchery-based environmental conditioning practices</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/usda.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Matt George</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>As academic, industry, and tribal stakeholders, our collective goal is to ensure the sustainable expansion of oyster aquaculture within the U.S. by reducing the frequency and severity of mass mortality events by improving the climate resilience of oyster stocks. The specific research objectives are: Optimize early-life stage environmental conditioning to improve climate resilience Assess carry-over benefits of broodstock husbandry practices on offspring performance Objective 1. Optimize early-life stage environmental conditioning to improve climate resilience. Developmental plasticity occurs when the environment experienced by an organism during development alters the phenotype of the same organism during later life-stages (Figure). To assess the potential for developmental plasticity to produce positive carry-over effects that improve resilience, we will expose oysters to a variety of environmental stressors at nonlethal levels during larval rearing. The performance of larvae will be assessed during early development and compared with performance after summer deployment at grow-out sites.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://gannet.fish.washington.edu/seashell/snaps/Monosnap_USDA_SRGARP_Proposal_2022_-_Google_Docs_2023-09-01_10-42-25.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>fig</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Objective 2. Assess carry-over benefits of broodstock husbandry practices on offspring performance. Transgenerational plasticity occurs when the environment experienced by parents influences the phenotype of their offspring (Fig. 4B). To assess the potential for transgenerational plasticity to produce positive carry-over effects that improve offspring resilience, we will expose oyster broodstock to a variety of environmental stressors at nonlethal levels prior to broodstock conditioning and spawning. The performance of offspring will then be assessed during the pre- and post-settlement larval stages and compared with performance after summer deployment at grow-out site</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-008583 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 1)<br>
GR014587 CLIMATE RESILIENCE - 62-7174 - 2021021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p><a href="https://d.pr/f/7JPaPP">USDA / 2022-70007-38284 (62-7174)</a></p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>9/1/2022 – 8/31/2024</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$299,374</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>carryover</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/usda.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Effects of temperature change and Hematodinium sp. infection (Bitter Crab Disease) on Tanner crab (Chionoecetes bairdi)</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/nprb.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Pamela Jensen</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Changing climate conditions, due to increasing releases of CO2 into the atmosphere, are causing warming of the world’s oceans. Changes in seawater temperatures are predicted to cause a shift in the distribution and a change in the abundance of most plants and animals. For most species, the magnitude of the impact, the potential for adaptation to future temperatures, and the mechanisms for adaptation are unknown. Features of parasite/disease ecology are also predicted to change as oceans warm, including susceptibility of hosts to disease, host ability to combat disease once infected, and alterations in pathogen virulence. Alaskan Tanner crab stocks, supporting fisheries worth $21 million in 2014, are expected to be significantly impacted directly and indirectly by warming temperatures. The Alaska Department of Fish and Game considers bitter crab disease, caused by a parasitic dinoflagellate, Hematodinium, to be the ‘principle threat’ to Alaskan Tanner crab stocks. Infection rates in the Bering Sea and southeast Alaska range from 2-5% and 0-100%, respectively. In heavily infected hosts, the meat is soft and chalky with a bitter taste, rendering the crabs unmarketable. The disease is believed fatal, although the time from infection to death remains uncertain. Recent worldwide spread of Hematodinium infections appears to have closely followed warming trends in the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans. We postulate that increased temperature in the North Pacific will physiologically stress Tanner crabs and also lead to increased prevalence of Hematodinium infections, either of which may lead to increased mortality in Tanner crabs. We propose to hold healthy and Hematodinium-infected Tanner crabs under different temperature regimes testing for a genetic response to infection and temperature. Our research will provide insight into the underlying mechanistic linkages between potential effects of climate change and important processes such as recruitment, growth and natural mortality on Alaskan Tanner crab stocks.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>crab</category>
  <category>disease</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <category>02-RBE</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/nprb.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gene activity and genetic selection in Pacific cod reared under thermal stress</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/cod.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Louise Copeman (co-PI)</p>
<p>Ben Laurel (co-PI)</p>
<p>Krista Nichols (co-PI)</p>
<p>Ingrid Spies (co-PI)</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Recent heat wave stress in the Gulf of Alaska has resulted in significant declines of Pacific cod, Gadus macrocephalus, in that region. In particular, overwintering success of juveniles is hypothesized to represent a critical bottleneck with food availability the previous summer affecting juvenile lipid reserves and thus, their ability to survive winter. The physiological and transcriptional responses of Pacific cod and whether selective mortality is present under thermal stress are unknown. The proposed project will address these questions critical to their survival under climate change by identifying regions of the genome and epigenome that respond to thermal stress and starvation. Juvenile Pacific cod will be reared in three temperatures under feeding and non-feeding conditions, then an integrated genomic approach will identify genes, gene variants, and epigenetic markers that respond to thermal stress and confer resilience. To complement the genomic approaches and further investigate temperature influences on energy resources, we will perform lipid analyses. This work will inform predictions of genetic selection and molecular response of Pacific cod in the Gulf of Alaska under climate change.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-008727 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 1)<br>
GR031727 COD THERMAL STRESS - 66-9283 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>Pacific States Marine Fisheries Commission / 23-084G (66-9283)</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>11/1/2022 – 7/31/2025</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$524,788</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>cod</category>
  <category>Alaska</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>01-EE</category>
  <category>02-RBE</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/cod.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A collaborative partnership to address mass mortalities in oyster aquaculture through improved field monitoring, husbandry practices, and workforce development</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/wsg-ec.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Emily Carrington</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>As a collaborative partnership, our collective goal is to ensure the sustainable expansion of oyster aquaculture within Washington State by reducing the frequency and severity of mass mortality events that result from the interaction between OsHV-1 infection and extreme climate events such as marine and aerial heatwaves. The specific research and outreach objectives we will use to achieve this goal are:</p>
<p>Objective 1. Determine susceptibility of Washington shellfish farms to heatwaves. Air and water temperatures experienced by oysters during grow-out will be monitored at farms within the Salish Sea and Willapa Bay in collaboration with industry partners. Continuous monitoring of environmental conditions in combination with oyster mortality data will be used to generate a climate risk assessment model for commercial growing areas within Washington State.</p>
<p>Objective 2. Develop a commercially viable hatchery husbandry protocol that improves oyster heat tolerance. Oyster seed (“spat”) from OsHV-1 resistant families supplied by the USDA-ARS’ Pacific Shellfish Breeding Center (PSBC) will undergo sublethal exposure to simulated marine and aerial heat waves within a hatchery setting. The summer survival of stress-primed spat out-planted at farms with Puget Sound and Willapa Bay will inform the creation of a husbandry protocol that improves oyster climate resilience.</p>
<p>Objective 3. Develop an enhanced workforce training curriculum for shellfish industry technicians. To address the industry’s need for skilled technicians, students from Bellingham Technical College’s (BTC) Fisheries and Aquaculture Sciences Program will be integrated into research objectives; this collaboration will be used to generate an enhanced workforce training curriculum that uses OsHV-1 and heat waves as case studies. Students will also gain exposure to training opportunities by serving as hatchery technicians, summer interns at shellfish farms, and student ambassadors during regular partner meetings.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>TBD</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p><a href="https://d.pr/f/dIGn9L">TBD</a></p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>2/2024 – 1/2026</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$280,000</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>disease</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/wsg-ec.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Identifying genomic architecture features that contribute to critical phenotypes in shellfish</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/nrsp8.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Mackenzie Gavery, Matt George</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Shellfish are a key component of domestic seafood production. Shellfish aquaculture is one of the most economically important sectors of the US industry, with major species including oysters and clams. As is the case with all farmed species, there are a suite of desirable phenotypes that directly correspond to increased environmental and economic sustainability. The ability to identify genomic predictors of phenotype offer a framework to increase aquaculture production. In shellfish aquaculture key phenotypes continue to be resilience and stress tolerance. Understanding the physiological underpinnings of these phenotypes in oysters and clams has been a focus in our group. To this end we have archived hundreds of samples from families with diverse phenotypic responses to stress. For example, as part of one effort to examine the influence of ploidy on oyster stress tolerance we have Standard Metabolic Rate (SMR) and enzyme activity data on oysters that reveal diverse physiological profiles. In response to the NRSP-8 Small Funding Possibilities for US Aquaculture Groups, we are proposing to 1) identify genomic architecture variation contributing to desired phenotypes in shellfish and 2) develop a community platform to share data and analytical approaches. These objectives are in direct response to Program Objective 2: Advance genome-to-phenome prediction by implementing strategies and tools to identify and validate genes and allelic variants predictive of biologically and economically important phenotypes and traits. Additionally the proposed work will address Program Objective 1, by … providing a deep functional annotation of assemblies, and comparison across species to understand structure and function of animal genomes.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>triploidy</category>
  <category>acidification</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>01-EE</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/nrsp8.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Vernon: Development of innovative approaches to support sustainable aquaculture and understand the effects of ocean acidification on marine species</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/vernon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Mackenzie Gavery</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Environmental variability due to climate change and ocean acidification (OA) are having multifaceted impacts on marine species, ecosystems and human industries such as marine aquaculture. It is absolutely critical to understand how marine organisms, and industries that rely on them, will respond to these changing conditions. Arguably, it will be just as important to provide tools and best practices to mitigate these effects, and in the case of marine aquaculture – find solutions to increase sustainability of the sector broadly, to create resilience even in the face of environmental uncertainty. Innovative scientific solutions are required to meet these ongoing and future challenges. In this project, we will add capacity to collaborative research between partners at the University of Washington and the Northwest Fisheries Science Center, addressing objectives of key importance to the National Marine Fisheries Service mission. These include innovative problem-solving approaches to address challenges facing sustainable aquaculture development, understanding the impacts of climate variability on marine fish and shellfish, and woven throughout these research activities is the development of ’omics and bioinformatics workflows for both data generation and data analysis (bioinformatics). Through this composite project, our goal is to contribute to applications to support sustainable aquaculture, increase our understanding of the effects of OA on marine fish and shellfish and contribute bioinformatic capacity, tools and workflows for research related to aquaculture, genomics and climate change.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-004600 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 128)<br>
GR012147 TASK II VERNON - 62-3837 - 2021</p>
<p>AWD-004600 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 3)<br>
GR011321 TASK II OMICS TECH - 62-2795 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>UW CICOES Task II Vernon (62-3837) / NOAA - NA20OAR4320271</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>7/2022 – 6/2024</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$1,182,294</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>acidification</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/vernon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Development of environmental conditioning practices to decrease impacts of climate change on shellfish aquaculture</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/ffar.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Hollie Putnam</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>The project will be completed using commercial hatchery rearing of geoduck clams. We will test and implement shellfish performance enhancement methods through the use of environmental stressor preconditioning, or “hardening”. The objectives of this work are to A) Identify key stages in the geoduck life cycle when environmental conditioning can be applied for optimal benefits to productivity, including: – Broodstock conditioning and reproductive performance, – Larval growth and survivorship, and – Juvenile resistance to stress through repeated exposures, B) Use genomics and epigenomics to identify underlying mechanisms involved in enhanced performance. This will provide mechanistic information that enables the application of optimal preconditioning approaches in other shellfish species. This project directly addresses the research topics of genomics, quantitative genetics, and phenomics in the less studied, yet viable, geoduck clam. The proposed work is based on our group’s prior finding that some exposure to low pH conditions can improve larval and juvenile performance traits. The research proposed will integrate and further test these findings in a commercial shellfish hatchery setting and determine the genetic and epigenetic markers associated with improved performance. In addition, we will explore how the “memory” of prior exposure increases later performance such that epigenetic markers could be leveraged in broodstock management and hatchery practices. A number of phenotypes will be assessed, as well as the underlying genomic factors, including fecundity, survival, and growth.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>clam</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/ffar.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Enhancing sustainability of shellfish aquaculture through streamlined maturation control</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/wsg-sc.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Mackenzie Gavery</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>The proposed objectives cover the essential first steps toward generating sterile bivalves via molecular disruption of germ cell formation. The first step in the process is the identification of genes involved in primordial germ cell (PGC) specification in bivalves via single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA- Seq). This cutting-edge technique is particularly suited to identify germ cell markers in bivalves, since germ cell precursors represent a small number of cells in developing embryos. This information is integral to being able to control germ cell fate for reproductive sterilization of aquaculture species, and our proposed use of scRNA-Seq for directed application to aquaculture is both novel and potentially highly beneficial to the broader shellfish aquaculture community. Our first specific research aim is to characterize genomic processes involved in germ cell specification in Pacific oysters. A second fundamental step in the process is the optimization of techniques to deliver targeted, gene-regulating molecules to embryos to inhibit germ cell formation. Methods to optimize delivery techniques, including the use of CRISPR-Cas9 and morpholino constructs, have yet to be developed for bivalve embryos. Therefore, our second specific research aim is to optimize delivery techniques of custom gene-regulating molecules to oyster embryos. The completion of these objectives sets the stage for a more effective and sustainable approach for sterilization of shellfish.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>scRNAseq</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>02-RBE</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/wsg-sc.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Increasing Environmental Connection, Literacy and Engagement through an Art + Science Collaborative Education Practice</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/art.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p><strong>Research Team:</strong><br>
<strong>Principal Investigator:</strong>&nbsp;Steven Roberts, UW Seattle, College of the Environment, Aquatic &amp; Fishery Science<br>
<strong>Community Lead:</strong>&nbsp;Tiara Moore, CEO, Black in Marine Science<br>
<strong>Student:</strong>&nbsp;Chris Mantegna, UW Seattle, College of the Environment, Aquatic &amp; Fishery Science<br>
<strong>Collaborators:</strong>&nbsp;Tivon Rice, UW Seattle College of Arts &amp; Sciences, Digital Arts &amp; Experimental Media<br>
Symone Barkley,&nbsp;Black in Marine Science<br>
Rosalind Echols, UW Seattle College of the Environment, Aquatic &amp; Fishery Science<br>
Savannah Smith, Sea Potential<br>
Ebony Welborn, Sea Potential<br>
Ángel Quimbita, Sea Potential</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>As the country comes to a reckoning on education and the environment, we are forced to interrogate the historic events that have led to such crises and how we can support inclusive solutions. Covid-19 has offered us an unprecedented glimpse into the challenges students face in the K-12 education system. It has also profoundly impacted socio-economically disadvantaged communities through the exposure of crippled or missing infrastructure. These same communities have been deliberately disconnected from building relationships with the natural world. In the face of complex problems like climate change, which will disproportionately impact these communities, we must act urgently to support the students who have historically been excluded from environmental science education. Our project starts with reconnecting community to environment, followed by engaging learners dynamically through the co-production of place-based knowledge. Although disadvantaged communities are highly engaged in climate change mitigation, this is often limited to anecdotes about water quality during trash pick-ups or community beautification projects led by outside non-profit volunteers, rather than building knowledge and strength within the community. Rarely do students have the opportunity to access their local environment through a non- problem solving lens and participate as equal partners. We want to change who is leading the learning as well as how the learning is done. Partnering with Sea Potential and Black in Marine Science, our team of scientists and digital arts experts will co-produce an arts based learning approach to increase environmental literacy in the communities most regularly overlooked. We will empower students to engage with the intertidal ecosystem, a defining feature of all coastlines and an accessible and dynamic place to learn about ocean science, organismal resilience, and community composition. Student projects will demonstrate how they understand the intertidal ecosystem, their connection to it, and its relationship to their home neighborhoods. Each of the projects will be presented to their academic and familial communities as well as used to create a teaching toolkit for local and national educators to replicate our art- and science-integrated student centered learning model for intertidal ecology.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/17_axfXCQT40AwWRnbkPRHgO5avcb3RZy">Drive</a></p>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">

</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">

</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">

</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">

</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>02-RBE</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/art.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Readying sustainable aquaculture for a changing ocean: uncovering the mechanisms associated with intergenerational carryover effects to enhance bivalve resilience to acidification</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/wsg-clam.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Mackenzie Gavery</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>The proposed effort will identify how parental environmental conditions drive shellfish offspring performance, including describing underlying mechanisms. To do this we will examine intergenerational effects of ocean acidification in the Manila clam, a globally cultured species that will serve as a model for marine bivalves and related taxa. By comprehensively investigating gamete status following parental pCO2 exposures, this project will uncover the non-genetic carriers of information across generations while simultaneously identifying factors that predict high performance of larvae in acidified conditions. By leveraging and working closely on a complementary NOAA supported project, we are able to expand our traditional research objectives with an objective centered around increasing diversity and inclusion in marine sciences. The specific objectives include 1) Characterize carryover performance in clams in response to ocean acidification, 2) Identify maternal macromolecule contribution of intergenerational plasticity and carryover performance, 3) Identify paternal epigenetic signatures associated with intergenerational plasticity and carryover performance, and 4) Develop inclusive educational experiences and products for underserved groups. The proposed work supports Washington Sea Grants commitment to cultivating partnerships and practicing a commitment to diversity, equity and inclusion. The objectives directly align with the critical program areas of Sustainable Fisheries and Aquaculture, Ocean Literacy and Workforce Development, and Healthy Coastal Ecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1eJtVsJ7tXpFlP8RmqeQecYmWLiCoKhNxPHc7zgKFlbM/edit"><em>notes</em></a></p>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-007435 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 14)<br>
GR013472 SG ROBERTS_R_SFA15 - 62-5534 - 2021</p>
<p>AWD-001657 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 51)<br>
GR014879 SG ROBERTS_VADOPALAS - 62-7661 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>Washington Sea Grant / R_SFA-15 (62-5534) and Puget Sound Partnership (co-funding) / 2022-44 (63-5817)</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>02/2022 – 1/2024</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$279,374</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>clam</category>
  <category>acidification</category>
  <category>carryover</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <category>01-EE</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/wsg-clam.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Collaborative Research: Does ocean acidification induce a methylation response that affects the fitness of the next generation in oysters?</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/ceabigr.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Katie Lotterhos</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Living organisms may acclimate to environmental changes through epigenetic modifications to DNA, which alter the way genetic instructions are interpreted without altering the DNA code itself. While these modifications to organismal phenotype or function can be reversible, some of them may be inherited by offspring, potentially producing multiple, heritable outcomes from a single genome and affecting ecological and evolutionary outcomes. This project uses symbiotic, metabolically complex reef building corals as a model system to test the connections between physiological, epigenetic, and metabolic states, and predict how population and community dynamics are influenced by epigenetically-modulated phenotypes. This work will advance biological knowledge by delineating fundamental links (Rules of Life) between ubiquitous organismal energetic processes, epigenetics, and eco-evolutionary outcomes. The Broader Impacts activities parallel the project’s integrative approach, linking insights from Environment x Energetics x Epigenetics x Ecology for Education into an E5 platform. The E5 platform will provide i) early career STEM training, ii) local and global community education, and iii) educational resources for open science, quantitative approaches, and research reproducibility. Further, this E5 platform will train and inform the next generation of diverse scientists and public by combining local and global initiatives focusing on groups underrepresented in STEM.</p>
<p>This project examines how nutrient metabolism in the mitochondria generates cofactors and energy that will instruct the epigenetic machinery in the cell nucleus to modulate genome function to appropriately respond to environmental conditions. Environmentally-responsive metabolic function and energetic-epigenetic linkages act as drivers of complex emergent phenotypes. To elucidate relationships that are the basis for Rules of Life with respect to epigenetics, this project will use integrative experimental and modeling approaches focused on reef building corals to: 1) link nutritionally-provisioned metabolites with epigenetic and organismal state through seasonal sampling across environmental gradients; 2) expand current Dynamic Energy Budget (DEB) models for symbiotic organisms to further integrate critical facets of nutritional symbiosis and calcification; 3) experimentally modulate metabolic and therefore epigenetic states through repeated exposure to increased temperature and nutrients, to test intra- and trans-generational epigenetic inheritance; 4) use DEB theory to identify shifts in energetics associated with epigenetic modulation, and link these sub-organismal processes to higher levels of organization; and 5) integrate findings into a generalizable, predictive eco-evolutionary model that links nutritional interactions, metabolic states, and subsequent epigenetic effects to the timescales regulating organismal processes and eco-evolutionary outcomes. This effort will provide characterization of environmental epigenetic phenomena in ecosystem-engineering marine invertebrates. This characterization includes determining the mechanisms and the degree of epigenetic ‘memory’ both within and across generations. By including information on environmental legacies, propagated by epigenetics, this project will advance both organismal and population-based models and improve capacity to predict responses to acute and chronic environmental signals.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
<p>The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4563060</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>oyster</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>acidification</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>01-EE</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/ceabigr.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Oyster adaptation to climate change via transgenerational plasticity</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/aust.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Dr Laura Parker<br>
Chief Investigator</p>
<p>Dr Wayne O’Connor<br>
Prof Pauline Ross<br>
Prof Thiyagarajan Vengatesen</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Summary: Across the globe, oysters need to rapidly respond to climate change. Increased concentrations of atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2) are warming and acidifying estuaries, especially along the south-eastern coast of Australia, at a rate an order of magnitude greater than that predicted for oceans (Collins et al.&nbsp;2013; Scanes et al.&nbsp;2020). For Indigenous Australians, oysters create an unbroken connection with the coast and sea that has persisted over time (National Oceans Office 2002) and are the focus of Aboriginal-led reef restoration projects. Assessing the capacity of oysters and other marine organisms to acclimate or adapt to global climate change stressors presents one of the most important research challenges of our time. Acclimation through the mechanism of transgenerational plasticity (TGP) is now at the leading edge of research providing hope that oysters and other marine organisms may persist into the future (Parker et al.&nbsp;2012, 2015, 2017a, Gibbs et al.&nbsp;accepted a, b). This project takes the next critical step in research: to identify whether the TGP response of oysters differ across genotypes, the capacity of TGP responses to persist within and across generations, and the epigenetic mechanisms which underlie them. How well we understand this, will determine our ability to ensure marine food security into the future and to protect the cultural heritage of Indigenous Australians – identified as a major concern for Indigenous people (National Oceans Office 2002). Globally, oysters form large aquaculture industries worth $6.8 billion per annum (Food and Agriculture Organization 2014) and provide services vital to the ecosystem (Lemasson et al.&nbsp;2017).<br>
<br>
AIM: Focussing on the ecologically, economically, and culturally important Sydney rock oyster, Saccostrea glomerata – we will use an innovative combination of state-of-the-art climate change mesocosm exposure systems and internationally established epigenetic and genetic techniques, with an ultimate aim to protect and conserve oysters against climate change to the benefit of Australians. Specific aims: Using the unique resource of pair-mated family lines of the Sydney rock oyster, S. glomerata, we will:<br>
1. Measure the variation in transgenerational plasticity responses to ocean warming and acidification within and among genotypes<br>
2. Characterise the role of epigenetic inheritance (DNA methylation) in transgenerational plasticity responses<br>
3. Assess the capacity of transgenerational plasticity responses to persist across life stages and generations</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-006084 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 1)<br>
GR032859 UNSW-OYSTER - 68-7511 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>University of New South Wales via ARC / IN220100054 (68-7511)</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>5/2/2023 – 12/31/2024</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$90,255</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <category>01-EE</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/aust.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Collaborative Research: URoL : Epigenetics 2: Predicting phenotypic and eco-evolutionary consequences of environmental-energetic-epigenetic linkages</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/e5.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Hollie Putnam<br>
Jose Eirin-Lopez<br>
Roger Nisbet<br>
Holly Moeller<br>
Ross Cunning</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Living organisms may acclimate to environmental changes through epigenetic modifications to DNA, which alter the way genetic instructions are interpreted without altering the DNA code itself. While these modifications to organismal phenotype or function can be reversible, some of them may be inherited by offspring, potentially producing multiple, heritable outcomes from a single genome and affecting ecological and evolutionary outcomes. This project uses symbiotic, metabolically complex reef building corals as a model system to test the connections between physiological, epigenetic, and metabolic states, and predict how population and community dynamics are influenced by epigenetically-modulated phenotypes. This work will advance biological knowledge by delineating fundamental links (Rules of Life) between ubiquitous organismal energetic processes, epigenetics, and eco-evolutionary outcomes. The Broader Impacts activities parallel the project’s integrative approach, linking insights from Environment x Energetics x Epigenetics x Ecology for Education into an E5 platform. The E5 platform will provide i) early career STEM training, ii) local and global community education, and iii) educational resources for open science, quantitative approaches, and research reproducibility. Further, this E5 platform will train and inform the next generation of diverse scientists and public by combining local and global initiatives focusing on groups underrepresented in STEM.</p>
<p>This project examines how nutrient metabolism in the mitochondria generates cofactors and energy that will instruct the epigenetic machinery in the cell nucleus to modulate genome function to appropriately respond to environmental conditions. Environmentally-responsive metabolic function and energetic-epigenetic linkages act as drivers of complex emergent phenotypes. To elucidate relationships that are the basis for Rules of Life with respect to epigenetics, this project will use integrative experimental and modeling approaches focused on reef building corals to: 1) link nutritionally-provisioned metabolites with epigenetic and organismal state through seasonal sampling across environmental gradients; 2) expand current Dynamic Energy Budget (DEB) models for symbiotic organisms to further integrate critical facets of nutritional symbiosis and calcification; 3) experimentally modulate metabolic and therefore epigenetic states through repeated exposure to increased temperature and nutrients, to test intra- and trans-generational epigenetic inheritance; 4) use DEB theory to identify shifts in energetics associated with epigenetic modulation, and link these sub-organismal processes to higher levels of organization; and 5) integrate findings into a generalizable, predictive eco-evolutionary model that links nutritional interactions, metabolic states, and subsequent epigenetic effects to the timescales regulating organismal processes and eco-evolutionary outcomes. This effort will provide characterization of environmental epigenetic phenomena in ecosystem-engineering marine invertebrates. This characterization includes determining the mechanisms and the degree of epigenetic ‘memory’ both within and across generations. By including information on environmental legacies, propagated by epigenetics, this project will advance both organismal and population-based models and improve capacity to predict responses to acute and chronic environmental signals.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
<p>The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4563060</p>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-002762 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 1)<br>
GR006094 NSF-ROL - 61-0552 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>NSF / EF-1921149</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>09/2019-8/2024</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$871,336</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>coral</category>
  <category>epigenetics</category>
  <category>01-EE</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/e5.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Applying cutting-edge technology for reproductive control in emerging bivalve species</title>
  <link>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/psmfc.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="collaborators" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborators">Collaborators</h2>
<p>Mackenzie Gavery</p>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Given the supreme importance of maintaining ecological security in expanding shellfish farming to meet the global demand for environmentally sustainable protein, our goal is to engage a novel mix of disciplines to create new knowledge leading to an optimal approach for conferring sterility in emerging shellfish species. We have assembled an interdisciplinary team including aquaculture specialists, molecular physiologists, and single cell genomicists to tackle the critical initial step in this approach: the identification of genes involved in germ cell fate at the earliest developmental stages in geoducks. We anticipate identifying several germ cell- specific genes that when disrupted effectively turn off germ cell differentiation, yielding sterile products that do not undergo gonadogenesis, exhibit superior performance, and cannot disrupt genetic structure of ecosystems. Identification of these genes will be the measure of success for the proposed work. These gene targets will be the focus of future stages of research that determines how to best disrupt reproductive function without impacting growth performance.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Codes</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Proposal ID</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Dates</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Amount</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<p>AWD-002979 Grant Revenue (RC1054) (Line 1)<br>
GR019591 BIVALVE REPRO CONTROL - 63-9405 - 2021</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<p>Pacific States Marine Fisheries Commission / 20-04G-1 (63-9405)</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<p>7/8/2019 – 4/30/2024 (NCE)</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<p>$93,400</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>clam</category>
  <category>scRNAseq</category>
  <category>aquaculture</category>
  <category>02-RBE</category>
  <category>03-ARD</category>
  <category>open</category>
  <guid>https://faculty.washington.edu/sr320/research/psmfc.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 20:50:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
